<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<documents>
  
    
		USWNT wins Women's World Cup thanks to Megan Rapinoe and Rose Lavelle goals
Lyon, France (CNN)When a novice is faced with a foe as experienced and ruthless as the USWNT at the Women's World Cup, the outcome is almost inevitable and so it was on a muggy early evening in Lyon when the reigning world champion defended its title with a comfortable 2-0 win over the Netherlands.

Competing in its first World Cup final, few gave the Dutch hope. The reigning European champion it may be, but it had not yet come up against the best team in the world, the dominant force of its generation.
The Netherlands held on for over an hour but two goals within eight minutes sealed the underdog's fate.
This was the tournament where Megan Rapinoe transcended her sport, and so it was perhaps apt that the 34-year-old opened the scoring, coolly drilling home a penalty before a Rose Lavelle thunderbolt made sure of a second successive title, and a fourth in eight editions.
Much has been written during this tournament about the European teams in rapid pursuit of the USWNT, posing a threat to a soccer dynasty.
That it was both Lavelle and Rapinoe, representing the team's youth and experience respectively, who scored was a perfect way to illustrates that the US possess the personnel to see off challengers for some time to come.
Leading the chase are those European countries whose men's national teams have traditionally been superpowers of the beautiful game.
The Dutch, English and French football federations have started to invest heavily in women's football. But, in France at least, all have been vanquished. Thailand, Chile, Sweden, Spain, France, England and now the Netherlands have been swept aside by a team unbeaten in 17 World Cup matches.
"The level around the world is going exponentially every year," Jill Ellis, the first coach to win the Women's World Cup twice, told reporters after the match.
"Four years on, this was incredibly difficult because the opponent is better The teams that we had to come through are some of the best teams in the world. In terms of the path and the level, this was pretty challenging."
The Netherlands soaked up the US pressure in the first half. There were white shirts coming at them from every direction, aiming crosses from wide, from deep, attempting cute through-balls to catch the first-time finalists off their guard.
Those in orange needed to summon up the concentration levels of a chess grand master, but that's what it's like facing a team with an unceasing desire to win. They are always in motion; keeping possession, positioning themselves high up the pitch, never resting. Opponents are left to backpedal, to organize and resist when under intense stress, but the grandest of sporting stages are always as much a mental battle as physical.
And then there was the predominantly American crowd raising the decibels; moving towards the edge of their seats in anticipation of that killer through ball, roaring at every shot that seems to be flying towards goal, making it impossible to forget that this is a match like no other. Grand masters, at least, have the privilege of focusing in silence.
Penalty after VAR review
That the Netherlands withstood the US until the hour mark was admirable. It is the only team in this tournament which the USWNT has been unable to breach within the opening 12 minutes.
Much of the credit will be heaped on the acrobatic Dutch goalkeeper Sari van Veenendaal. First, she saved a Julie Ertz volley, then the woodwork assisted her gather of the first of two Alex Morgan attempts. It was pure instinct which saw her deny Morgan for the second time before the break.
Had the Netherlands maintained its composure in the final third then history could have come to regard this as the match where the emerging force knocked the USWNT off its perch.
The Netherlands did cause the USWNT a moment of worry. Alyssa Naeher had to sprint off her line at the sight of Lineth Beerensteyn charging towards goal with the score goalless. It was a move which highlighted the US defense's occasional vulnerability to be cut open with a clever pass.
But after the break the USWNT cut loose. When French referee Stephanie Frappart opted to bring VAR into play, showing Stefanie van der Gragt to have felled Morgan, it felt almost certain that the penalty would be awarded.
Rapinoe stepped up to score her sixth goal of the tournament and celebrated with arms outstretched in a pose which became iconic when she celebrated in the same way in scoring against France just days after irking US President Donald Trump.
Her teammates engulfed her near the corner flag, with even the substitutes sprinting half the length of the pitch to join the celebrations. Given the doggedness of Dutch resistance, the relief of the US team was tangible.
The penalty secured Rapinoe the Golden Boot, beating teammate Morgan -- who also ended the tournament with six goals and three assists -- courtesy of minutes per goal. Rapinoe, only the second player in history to start in three World Cup finals, was also awarded the Golden Ball, given to the tournament's best player.
It was only after going 1-0 down that the Netherlands attack, its most potent weapon, seemed to feel at ease in its surroundings, but teams who fall behind to the USWNT rarely recover. And so it proved as Lavelle, who watched the 2015 final in a pizza shop, struck quickly to double the advantage.
Gathering the ball in the center circle, Lavelle surged forward -- the 24-year-old's mastery of the ball at pace making it impossible for her opponents to thwart her. With a swivel of the hips, she evaded two oncoming Dutch defenders before hitting the bottom-right corner.
Were it not for Van Veenendaal -- who wears boots a size too small out of superstition -- the score could have been higher. The 29-year-old stopped Morgan, Tobin Heath and Crystal Dunn from making it three.
"We'd have loved to have win this final but we didn't, our opponent was better today," said Netherlands coach Sarina Wiegman.
"We're second in the world and I'm very proud of that, I'm proud of the team and proud of the staff. And I think we can still improve."
	
  
  
    
		Serena Williams, Andy Murray win Wimbledon mixed doubles opener
The dream mixed-doubles partnership of Serena Williams and Andy Murray didn't disappoint in their long awaited Wimbledon debut.

Due to play on Center Court Friday, there was no room for the grand slam winning pair after teen phenom Cori "Coco" Gauff's dramatic late victory but Williams and Murray got their slot Saturday after a trio of quick singles matches and downed Germany's Andreas Mies and Chile's Alexa Guarachi 6-4 6-1.
"Andy and I both love the competition," Williams said earlier Saturday after a singles win over Julia Goerges 6-3 6-4. "I know we both want to do well. We're not here just for show. We want to play well. We both have been champions at Wimbledon. It's like we want to continue to do that."
Williams added that Murray only had to adhere to one rule.
"I always play the forehand side. If you want to play with me, I play forehand," she said.
And Murray did.
The result was particularly important for him, since the 32-year-old lost in the men's doubles earlier with Frenchman Pierre Hugues Herbert against sixth-seeds Franko Skugor and Nikola Mektic 6-7 (4-7) 6-4 6-2 6-3.
Thank Roger Federer, Rafael Nadal and Ashleigh Barty for speeding up proceedings on the most famous court in the world on Day Six, each of them winning in straight sets in the third round. Perennial history maker Federer became the first man to collect 350 grand slam victories.
Williams and Murray cruised to victory in one hour and 16 minutes, creating 17 break points and not dropping serve.
Wimbledon was meant to be Murray's swansong, having said on the eve of the Australian Open in January he wished to play his last tournament at SW19 this year after being ravaged by a hip injury.
A hip resurfacing procedure saved his career, however, and thankfully the twice singles champion at SW19 now doesn't plan on retiring this year.
Murray focusing on doubles
But he still isn't comfortable enough to play singles, instead focusing on doubles.
He combined with Feliciano Lopez to lift the title at Queens and then said he would compete in men's doubles at Wimbledon with Herbert.
And when he considered playing mixed doubles, he asked the likes of Barty and France's Kristina Mladenovic. Others volunteered their services, including Maria Sharapova and Victoria Azarenka.
Murray says he's 'pain free' after hip surgery 02:31
After Murray lightheartedly said he would be keen to partner Williams -- who has won 14 doubles grand slams with older sister Venus -- it eventually happened.
They are friends and parents who have expressed admiration for each other in the past.
Seeing the pair in the mixed doubles at an official event is rare -- Williams last competed at the 2012 French Open with Bob Bryan, who underwent surgery last year for the same type of hip problem afflicting the Scot, while Murray last featured at the 2016 Olympics with Heather Watson.
Williams a singles winner
Unlike Murray, she won her first match of the day, against Goerges in a repeat of last year's semifinal to reach the fourth round.
It was the American's best performance so far as she bids once again to equal Margaret Court's all-time record of 24 majors.
Serena Williams and Andy Murray were on the same side of the court in mixed doubles at Wimbledon on Saturday.
Williams' famed serve was working, delivering seven aces. She didn't face a break point, either.
Another player Williams has praised is Barty, the new world No. 1 and French Open champion.
The down to earth Aussie tallied her 15th straight win and 20th straight set, dispatching Britain's Harriet Dart 6-1 6-1.
Barty and Williams could meet in the quarterfinals.
Meanwhile Nadal and Federer could meet in the semifinals, in what would be their first duel at Wimbledon since the 2008 final that many consider the greatest tennis match of all time.
There is still a ways to go but both will feature Monday after Wimbledon's usual day off Sunday.
Nadal -- two days after his grudge match with Nick Kyrgios -- crushed a disappointing Jo-Wilfried Tsonga 6-2 6-3 6-2 and Federer ousted Lucas Pouille 7-5 6-2 7-6 (7-4) in what was a disappointing day for the French men.
Fognini controversy
Fabio Fognini faces a potential ban after saying he wished a bomb would explode at Wimbledon during a defeat to American Tennys Sandgren.
"Wish a bomb would explode on this club. A bomb should explode here," microphones on court caught him saying in Italian.
The controversial Fognini said "sorry" in his briefing with reporters afterward but it might not be enough to spare him from a suspension.
In 2017, he was fined $96,000 and thrown out of the US Open for verbally abusing a female chair umpire and told he would miss two grand slams if he committed another major offense in the next two seasons.
Bombs damaged a part of Center Court in 1940 during World War II.
	
  
  
    
		He has dazzled at Pebble Beach in the past, but Tiger Woods had to "grind" and "fight" to stay in contention at the 119th US Open Thursday.

The peerless Woods won by a record 15 shots when the US Open was held at the picturesque Monterey venue in 2000, but the 43-year-old 2019 version ground out a one-under 70 to sit five off the lead of England's Justin Rose.
"It's typical Pebble Beach where the first seven holes you can get it going, and then after that you're kind of fighting and kind of hanging on," Woods told reporters afterwards.
"I had it going early and had to fight off through the middle part of the round and hung in there with pars. It's just fighting it out and grinding it out."
Woods' Masters victory in April for a 15th major and first in 11 years renewed talk of his quest to pass Jack Nicklaus' record of 18 majors but a missed cut at the PGA Championship last month tempered expectations.
After four back operations, including spinal fusion surgery, Woods has to manage his body carefully, but he said the problem was his iron play on a short, tight course with small greens that demand strategy and accuracy above brute power.
"I didn't hit my irons as crisp as I'd like," said the world No. 5, who also won the US Open in 2002 and 2008.
"I tried to miss the ball in the correct spots, and a couple of times where I had wedges in my hand I was just dumping, center of the green, get my 30-, 40-footer and move on. I took my medicine when I was in a bad spot and just kind of grind it out."
Finding positives
Rose, playing alongside Woods, compiled a stunning 65 as he chases a second major title to add to his 2013 US Open triumph at Merion, Pennsylvania.
"This is just a very small step towards the outcome," said the 38-year-old. "You don't feel like that buzz that you would on a Sunday, but you can't help but look around over your shoulder, and [think] dam, this is Pebble Beach. Shot 65 and you're in the US Open. It's a cool moment. Whatever transpires the rest of the week, it was a cool moment."
Defending champion Brooks Koepka was another who had to embrace his stoic side on the shores of Carmel Bay.
The 29-year-old, bidding to become only the second player after Willie Anderson (1903-1905) to win three straight US Opens, carded a two-under 69 after escaping from a number of tricky spots including having to play his second off a concrete cart path on the 18th.
"I try to find some positive and try to spin it, even when something negative happens," said world No.1 Koepka, who has won four of his last eight majors.
One shot behind Rose was the quartet of Rickie Fowler, Xander Schauffele, Louis Oosthuizen and Aaron Wise.
"It was very stress free. It felt like the worst I could have shot," said world No.11 Fowler, who is still chasing his first major title.
'Two perfect shots, Michael'
Jordan Spieth, who won the last of his three majors at the Open in 2017, became the subject of much chatter on social media after he was heard to criticize caddie Michael Greller during the round.
The former world No.1, who is trending in the right direction after a mini slump of late, found the Pacific Ocean with his tee shot on the eighth hole before firing his third through the green.
"Two perfect shots, Michael," Spieth said to long-time caddie Greller. "You got me in the water on one and over the green on the other."
The pair are famous for their vocal discussions on the course, and Spieth regularly refers to himself as "we" when discussing his play, in a nod to Greller's input.
When he was quizzed about his comments afterward, Spieth told reporters: "When you hit a couple of shots exactly where you want to, and one's in the water and the other's dead over the green, I'm gonna be frustrated that, as a team, we didn't figure out how to make sure that didn't happen.
"I may have looked like the bad guy there but my intentions there were that we should have been in play if the ball is hit solidly and I was out of play on both shots."
When Spieth won the Open Championship at Royal Birkdale in 2017, he shouted to Greller: "Go get that," and pointed to the hole after sinking a 50-foot eagle putt on the 15th hole.
He later explained it had somehow lodged in his head after seeing loops of old Open footage while in the gym, in which caddies regularly fetched the ball from the hole.

	
  
  
    
		Mikaela Shiffrin on learning to ignore social media 'haters'
Mikaela Shiffrin is growing into one of the most dominant and influential female sports stars on the planet, but she knows that her success in ski racing comes at a price -- abusive comments on social media.

The 24-year-old dominated skiing's World Cup circuit this season and has taken over the mantle of skiing's biggest star from the retired Lindsey Vonn.
But she is aware that her profile, and active use of social media, makes herself vulnerable to trolls and negativity.
And she had sympathy for Australian Football League player Tayla Harris, who received a torrent of what she called "sexual abuse" on social media this week for a picture of her kicking a ball.
Even Australian Prime Minister Scott Morrison weighed in, calling those responsible "cowardly grubs."
Shiffrin said she couldn't understand why the picture of Harris would evoke the reaction it has, and told CNN World Sport in New York she is learning to ignore her own "haters."
The American, who has more than 800,00 Instagram followers, says she is realizing "you can't make everybody happy."
"Something I really value is freedom of speech, freedom of expression and freedom of opinion," she said.
"And their troll-like hater comments is a bummer, it hurts, it kind of gets you in the heart but at the same time it's like, 'OK, they're allowed to think that and I have to be OK with that.'
"It doesn't mean it doesn't hurt, but say what you want and I'll just keep moving forward."
Shiffrin dominated ski racing this season, winning a record 17 World Cup races and clinching a third straight overall crown to go with a fourth consecutive slalom world title and numerous other honors.
Her achievements moved her to fifth on the all-time list of most successful ski racers with 60 career wins, behind only Annemarie Moser-Proll, Marcel Hirscher, Vonn and Ingemar Stenmark, who holds the record with 86.
And Shiffrin is sensing a blurring of the boundaries between genders, certainly in ski racing.
"It's not about whether you're a female in sports who's powerful or a male in sports who's powerful, you're a person in sports who's powerful," she said.
"That's kind of a shift I'm starting to feel but I guess it takes a little while.
"There's always going to be that description of gender but right now, especially in ski racing, what I'm able to achieve in the sport is very even with what a man is able to achieve in sport and that's a really special feeling.
"The opportunity is there."
Shiffrin has grown up in the spotlight since making her debut on the circuit as a 16-year-old in 2012, and she says the sport has helped her "bloom as a person.
"I've definitely grown, I've come out of my shell in many ways," she added. "I've definitely become more confident in myself."
She pointed to her growing collection of clips from her life on social media, including a recent one of her dancing.
"In high school I wouldn't be caught dead dancing in front of anybody," she said. "But I always loved to dance and I wanted to be a good dancer and now I don't really care if I'm a good dancer, I just like to dance.
"I've become much more comfortable kind of being silly, not feeling like I have to be perfect. Just being myself and sharing that with the world and it's pretty cool."
	
  
  
    
		Israel Folau looks for $2.1 million in legal battle with Rugby Australia
Israel Folau, who was sacked by Rugby Australia following a homophobic social media post, is crowdfunding A$3 million (US$2.1 million) to pursue a legal battle against the governing body.

Folau, a devout Christian who has been capped 73 times by his country, was found guilty of a code of conduct breach and stripped of his contract last month for an Instagram post that said "hell awaits" gay people.
On Thursday, he published a GoFundMe page and a YouTube video asking members of the public to donate money as a contribution towards his legal battle with Rugby Australia.
Visit CNN.com/sport for more news, videos and features
"My fight with Rugby Australia to defend my right to practice my religion has so far cost my wife Maria and me over A$100,000 in legal fees," Folau says in the video.
"Rugby Australia has an army of lawyers at their disposal and they have already said they will divert significant resources to fight me in court.
"The cost to me and my family of continuing my legal action against Rugby Australia is expected to be significant."
Rugby Australia didn't immediately respond to CNN's request for comment.
In an April Instagram post, which has not been deleted, Folau listed "drunks, homosexuals, adulterers, liars, fornicators, thieves, atheists and idolaters," underneath which was written "Hell awaits you."
The 30-year-old's contract lasted until 2022 and he was expected to play a leading role with the Wallabies at the upcoming Rugby World Cup.
Folau was also stripped of sponsorship deals with car manufacturer Land Rover and sportswear brand Asics. He is reportedly seeking A$10 million (US$7 million) in damages from the legal battle.
"As Australians, we're born with the right to freedom of religion and freedom of expression," Folau added.
"The Christian faith has always been a part of my life and I believe it is my duty as a Christian to share God's word. Rugby Australia tore up my employment contract for doing just that, and that's wrong.
"Every Australian should be able to practice their religion without fear of discrimination in the workplace."
Folau's brother John, a teammate of the fullback at the NSW Waratahs, was recently granted immediate release from his club contract, with coach Daryl Gibson stating that the 24-year-old had "divided loyalties to his family and his brother, but then also to the team."
	
  
  
    
		Mick Schumacher to drive in dad Michael's old Ferrari at Hockenheim
Mick Schumacher admits he will have a "big grin" on his face when he drives in one of his dad Michael's former Ferraris as part of an exhibition at the German Grand Prix next month.

The F2004 was the Ferrari in which the elder Schumacher won the last of his seven Formula 1 titles 15 years ago.
His son will be at the wheel at Hockenheim on July 27 prior to qualifying, then also the next day ahead of the drivers' parade.
The 20-year-old is currently racing in Formula 2 for PREMA Racing and the Ferrari driver academy, with Hockenheim not on the F2 calendar.
Visit CNN Sport for more news, features and videos
"I think it's mega driving this car in Hockenheim," the German told F1's website. "The last time I was on this track was when I celebrated my Formula 3 championship title, and now I'll be able to drive one of the strongest cars in Formula 1 history there. A big grin creeps into my face.
"All motorsport crazy people can look forward to a very special and wonderfully loud moment."
Ross Brawn, Ferrari's former technical director who forged a dominant partnership with Michael Schumacher, said it would be an "emotional moment."
An 'emotional moment'
"It will be an emotional moment seeing Mick at the wheel of a car linked to so many great memories," said Brawn, now F1's managing director of motorsport. "The F2004 was a fantastic car, which took 15 wins and both championship titles in a season that can be seen as the culmination of a golden period, which was the result of all the hard work from an amazing group of people and Michael Schumacher, a supremely talented driver.
"I'm sure that all the fans at Hockenheim will be pleased to see it roaring around the track again, especially with Mick in the cockpit.
"One of the requests we get most often from fans is to see the cars that wrote F1 history back on track, so this demonstration run at Hockenheim will be truly unmissable."
Michael Schumacher continues to rehabilitate at home after suffering a serious head injury while skiing in France in December 2013. He underwent two operations and was put into a medically induced coma.
Six months later his manager said Schumacher was no longer in a coma, but few details about his condition have been made public.
	
  
  
    
		Bern E-Prix: Jean Eric-Vergne closes on second straight title after Swiss success
In a four-way last lap tussle, it was Jean Eric-Vergne who kept his nerve to win the Bern E-Prix Saturday to boost his hopes of become Formula E's first back-to-back world champion.
The Swiss capital was staging its first Formula E race, marked by a first-lap pile up then a thrilling climax as a late rain shower made the 2.75km, 14-turn circuit treacherous.
Vergne, from pole, had led throughout, but was coming under constant pressure from New Zealand's Mitch Evans (Jaguar Racing), with home hope Sebastien Buemi (Nissan e.dams) and his DS Techeetah teammate Andre Lotterer taking close order.
With the Frenchman driving cautiously to ensure he made no late mistakes, it left Evans and the other chasers with a chance of victory, Vergne holding them off as all four finished nose to tail.
In a dramatic twist, Lotterer was later given a 22-second penalty, dropping him to 14th, for ignoring a pit exit light, wrecking his championship chances.
Vergne has a 32-point lead over Berlin winner Lucas di Grassi and in a commanding position to claim successive titles, with just the New York double-header remaining.
READ: Di Grassi steps up title charge with Berlin win
'That was a hell of a race," said Vergne, who was claiming his third win of the season and third podium in a row.
"Nothing is won in Formula E, but 32 points is pretty good and more than last year," he added.
Vergne was boosted before the start by qualifying fastest and seeing main title rival di Grassi only manage 19th spot.
The race was almost immediately red flagged after a collision between Mahindra Racing's Pascal Wehrlein and Geox Dragon's Max Gunther, with Wehrlein's teammate Jerome d'Ambrosio also shunting into Robin Frijns of Virgin Racing.
Di Grassi (Audi Sport Abt Schaeffler) had weaved his way through the field in the ensuing chaos, but race stewards ruled that the overtakes were under a yellow flag and that restart would be in original grid order, much to his disappointment.
"This is completely wrong," said di Grassi, who found support from former F1 star and fellow Brazilian Felipe Massa, competing in his first season in Formula E.
READ: Mercedes and Porsche to enter 2019/20 championship
Di Grassi did move into the points in eventual ninth spot following Lotterer's demotion, but his title bid hangs by a thread.
Evans was also left frustrated that he could not convert the obvious race pace of his car into a victory, unable to find a way past the wily Vergne despite looking the quicker on the undulating street circuit.
Former champion Buemi finished a fine third in his home race, with Britain's Sam Bird promoted to fourth.
The result has left Techeetah with a commanding 43-point lead in the constructors' title race over Audi Sport ahead of the championship finale in the Big Apple next month, with Vergne on the verge of making Formula E history.

	
  
  
    
		At Intermission, the Mets Stagger Off the Stage
There was a carnival in the plaza outside Citi Field on Sunday morning. Bouncy houses, balloon animals and a dunk tank welcomed Mets fans as they walked off the No. 7 train. It was put on by Send in the Clowns, the team’s official party provider. Still, Corey Johnson, a stadium greeter, knew optimism would be a tough sell.

“It’s a thank you for coming,” he said. “It’s rough being a Mets fan right now.”

Indeed, it was the Phillies, the Mets’ opponents on Sunday, who stepped right up when the game began. In merry-go-round fashion, they made their way around the basepaths to take a 4-0 lead after just one inning.

It would be more than enough. For in their final game before the All-Star break, the Mets did not even manage a hit against Phillies pitcher Aaron Nola until the sixth inning. The hit was a two-run homer by the rookie slugger Pete Alonso, giving him a resounding 30 for the season, but even so it only narrowed the Phillies’ lead to 6-2. And by game’s end, the Mets had lost yet again, this time by an 8-3 score, as they fell to a disheartening 40-50 on the season.

They are 13½ games out of first place in the National League East, and seven games out of a wild-card spot. And while Manager Mickey Callaway expressed defiant optimism after the game, it’s doubtful many of the team’s fans would agree with his assessment.

Marc Stein's Newsletter
Marc Stein has covered Jordan. He's covered Kobe. And LeBron vs. the Warriors. Go behind the N.B.A.'s curtain with basketball's foremost expert.

SIGN UP
Taking the loss was Mets starter Zack Wheeler, who may be sent elsewhere by the time the trading deadline arrives at the end of the month. He said he thought he knew why the Phillies were able to knock him around as soon as Sunday’s game began.

“Honestly, I think they had my pitches,” he said. “I thought it was a little weird when they were turning on fastballs.”

Jay Bruce, the outfielder whom the Mets traded to Seattle in the off-season as part of the ambitious deal to acquire Edwin Diaz and Robinson Cano, contributed to the first-inning onslaught with a run-scoring single. By game’s end, he had added two home runs in just the latest reminder that the trade has not worked out at all the way the Mets envisioned.

Still, Callaway remained positive. “I feel like we can make a run at this thing,” he said. “We can sneak into the wild card. We can sneak back into the division. I’ve seen it all. Anything can happen in baseball.”

That may be, but the season’s intermission could not come soon enough for the Mets. They are flailing in fourth place despite boasting Jeff McNeil, the best hitter in the majors with a .349 average; Alonso, the front-runner for rookie of the year in the National League; and Jacob deGrom, the defending Cy Young Award winner in the N.L. and a pitcher who has produced seven consecutive quality starts.

Editors’ Picks

He’s Spent Just One Night on His Private Island. He’s Had Enough.

The Sports Bra Seen Round the World Has New Meaning 20 Years Later

On the Fourth of July, Melania Trump Dresses for Independence
All three had their bags packed for Tuesday night’s All-Star Game in Cleveland. Alonso will participate in the home run derby Monday night. He leads all rookies in home runs, runs batted in (68), extra-base hits (53), on-base percentage (.372), slugging percentage (.634), total bases (206), runs (57), hits (91), multi-hit games (28), walks (37) and doubles (21).

“I just feel continually blessed,” Alonso said. “I’m living out a fantasy right now.”

If only his team was. Instead, they keep losing, and over the weekend they also became ensnared in some bad blood with the Phillies after Mets third baseman Todd Frazier was hit by a pitch on Saturday night. It was the second time in as many nights he had been hit and the third time this season a Philies pitcher had plunked him.

Both teams were issued a warning by the umpire after Saturday’s episode, but Frazier was ejected for arguing that the Mets should not have received one. Callaway ended up being tossed, too. And Jake Arrieta, the pitcher who hit Frazier on Saturday, took exception to Frazier’s complaints afterward, saying: “He can come see me and I’ll put a dent in his skull.’’

“A little overboard,” Frazier said Sunday morning when asked about Arrieta’s comment.

In Sunday’s game, the Mets appeared to retaliate in the seventh inning when Wilmer Font threw a fastball that hit Phillies first baseman Rhys Hoskins in the leg. Neither team reacted at that point, although Hoskins answered back with a home run in the ninth.

A few minutes later, the Mets were done for the day. They will resume their season on Friday in Miami, where they start a 10-day road trip.

When asked what the Mets must do to improve, Alonso, the upbeat rookie, said they needed to show confidence despite all the setbacks in the first half of the season.

“I think that we need to get the ball rolling as soon as the break is over,” he said. “Everybody needs to rest up.’
	
  
  
    
		Rangers Sign Artemi Panarin, a Top Free-Agent Forward
The Rangers continued their roster revamp with their biggest splash yet on Monday, signing the high-scoring forward Artemi Panarin to a seven-year, $81.5 million contract.

Panarin, a 27-year-old Russian, was among the most-sought free agents. He had 28 goals and 59 assists for the Columbus Blue Jackets last season, his fourth year in the N.H.L.

The addition of Panarin continues a dramatic overhaul of the Rangers roster after they missed the playoffs for the second straight season.

John Davidson, the former president of the Blue Jackets, joined the Rangers in the same capacity in May. The Rangers have since acquired the elite defenseman Jacob Trouba from the Winnipeg Jets and drafted the Finnish forward Kaapo Kakko second overall last month. They also expect to have the Russian forward Vitali Kravtsov, a first-round pick last year, on the team next season.

Marc Stein's Newsletter
Marc Stein has covered Jordan. He's covered Kobe. And LeBron vs. the Warriors. Go behind the N.B.A.'s curtain with basketball's foremost expert.

SIGN UP
“I’m ecstatic about getting Panarin here to join this group. I think he falls right into our plan,” Davidson said. “He’s always wanted to be in the big city and there’s no bigger city than New York.”

The signing comes a day after the Knicks, with the same owner and arena as the Rangers, failed to land the N.B.A. free agents Kevin Durant and Kyrie Irving, who signed with the Nets instead. Panarin had also been courted by the Islanders, who share an arena with the Nets.

Panarin represents the type of pure scorer the Rangers haven’t had since Marian Gaborik registered two 40-goal seasons after signing as a free agent in 2009.

“There’s something special about Panarin in the way he plays the game, the way he looks at the game and the way he thinks about the game,” Davidson added. “In watching him play in big spots, he just seems to love it.”

Panarin has 116 goals and 204 assists in four seasons with Chicago and Columbus. He won the Calder Trophy as the league’s best rookie in 2015-16 and is one of three undrafted players in league history to record at least 70 points in each of their first four seasons.

Editors’ Picks

He’s Spent Just One Night on His Private Island. He’s Had Enough.

Is Cold Brew Better Than Iced Coffee?

On the Fourth of July, Melania Trump Dresses for Independence
Rangers General Manager Jeff Gorton emphasized that in addition to adding an experienced scorer of Panarin’s pedigree, his mentoring potential is equally vital.

“We’re trying to get better every day,” Gorton said. “We have a lot of young players. One of the reasons we made this move is to help with our young players.”

The Rangers also traded forward Jimmy Vesey to the Buffalo Sabres for a third-round draft pick in 2021. Vesey, 26, was a coveted free agent out of Harvard in the summer of 2016. He had 40 goals and 50 assists in 240 games over three seasons with the Rangers.

And the Rangers signed free-agent forward Greg McKegg, 27, who played 41 games last season for the Carolina Hurricanes and Danny O’Regan, a 25-year-old center who played for A.H.L. Rochester last season.

The Islanders made two key moves on Monday, signing 31-year-old goaltender Semyon Varlamov to a four-year deal to replace Robin Lehner and re-signing power forward Anders Lee, 28, to a seven-year, $49 million contract.

“We feel very good about our team, our core players,” said Lou Lamoriello, the Islanders’ president of hockey operations. “Having them all back for the most part is important.”

Lee had 28 goals and 23 assists last season after he replaced John Tavares as team captain, then helped the Islanders finish with 103 points and reach the second round of the playoffs.

Varlamov spent the last eight seasons with the Colorado Avalanche. He has a career .916 save percentage.

Lehner, who had a memorable 25-win, .930 save percentage season for the Islanders last season, signed a one-year, $5 million contract with the Chicago Blackhawks.

“You never leave relationships or friendships. Unfortunately things didn’t work out for different reasons,” Lamoriello said. “He’s a quality human being — certainly an outstanding goaltender — and we wish him the best.”

The Islanders also re-signed forward Tom Kuhnhackl to a one-year contract.

Also on Monday, the former Ranger Mats Zuccarello, traded to Dallas in February, joined the Minnesota Wild with a five-year contract worth $30 million.

“I really enjoyed New York. They brought me from a kid into the league. They will always have a special place in my heart,” Zuccarello said on a conference call. “I’m real excited to spend the next five years in Minnesota. It’s a hockey-crazy state.”

The top forward Matt Duchene, 28, signed a seven-year, $56 million with the Nashville Predators. He finished last season with Columbus after a trade from Ottawa, scoring a career-best 31 goals overall.

Goalie Sergei Bobrovsky, 30, Panarin’s former teammate in Columbus, signed a seven-year, $70 million deal with the Florida Panthers.

The former Anaheim star Corey Perry, 34, signed a one-year deal with Dallas after 14 seasons with the Ducks. The Stars also signed former Sharks captain Joe Pavelski to a three-year deal.

The Toronto Maple Leafs signed the veteran forward Jason Spezza, 36, and completed a six-player trade with Ottawa, sending Nikita Zaitsev, 27, and two others to the Senators in exchange for Cody Ceci, Ben Harpur and a minor leaguer.

Toronto made a second major trade later Monday, sending veteran forward Nazem Kadri, defenseman Calle Rosen and a third-round pick in 2020 to the Colorado Avalanche for defenseman Tyson Barrie, forward Alexander Kerfoot and a sixth-round pick in next year’s draft.

The former Devils goaltender Keith Kinkaid, 29, signed a one-year deal with Montreal.

Detroit signed 35-year-old forward Valtteri Filppula after he scored 17 goals in 72 games for the Islanders last season. Filppula spent the first eight seasons of his N.H.L. career with the Red Wings.

The Devils signed right wing Wayne Simmonds to a one-year, $5 million contract. The 30-year-old Simmonds, a six-time 20-goal scorer during eight seasons with the Philadelphia Flyers, joins P.K. Subban and first overall draft pick Jack Hughes as key additions for the Devils after they missed the playoffs last season.
	
  
  
    
		The Giants Changed Corey Ballentine’s Life. Hours Later So Did a Bullet.
Ballentine was drafted by the Giants in April. Hours later, he was struck by gunshot in a tragic moment that took the life of his best friend.
TOPEKA, Kan. — It was 2 a.m., but Navarro Simmons’s mobile phone kept ringing and Corey Ballentine’s name kept flashing across the screen. Simmons was pretty sure what it was about, so he ignored the calls, at first.

Several hours earlier Simmons had called to congratulate Ballentine, who had just been selected by the Giants in the sixth round of the N.F.L. draft. Simmons had also called his son Dwane, knowing that Dwane was with Ballentine and would be just as excited about the big news. He assumed they were just getting back to him.

Still in bed, Simmons finally clicked on his phone and began congratulating Ballentine again, asking how he felt on what was surely the best day of his young life.

“Not good, Mr. Simmons,” Ballentine said. “You need to get here. Me and Dwane have been shot.”

In an instant, the greatest day of Corey Ballentine’s life had turned into by far the worst. A bullet had torn through his buttocks, and his best friend was mortally wounded.
The shooting that April night was like so many others in a country where gun violence plagues so many cities and towns. Rarely, though, does a bullet find an N.F.L. prospect on the night he is drafted.

Simmons and Ballentine were the innocent victims of a random act, a conclusion drawn from interviews with the police, coaches, teachers, neighbors and family members.

Simmons was the fifth homicide victim this year in Topeka, a city of about 128,000 in which there have been 53 homicides in the last 30 months (the most recent reported a month ago, about two blocks from where Simmons was killed). That puts the homicide rate in Topeka, where the median household income is roughly $45,000, ahead of the national average. Simmons, who was 23, and Ballentine were immensely popular around town, so this killing shattered the community.

“He was just a college kid who was scheduled to graduate in the fall of 2019 with a degree that he would have shined in,” Simmons said. “It just makes no sense.”

Around 12:45 a.m. on April 28, Ballentine and Simmons, the starting cornerbacks on the Washburn University football team, were shot by unknown assailants as they left a party near campus. The motive has not been established, though the police say investigators have leads on who carried out the shooting and are optimistic they will make an arrest.

“Corey and Dwane were not looking for trouble,” Bill Cochran, chief of the Topeka Police Department, said in a telephone interview. “There was none of that afoot. They were just out having a good time.”
Teammates, Roommates, Best Friends
Corey Ballentine and Dwane (pronounced “dwon”) Simmons met in their freshman year at Washburn University, a neatly trimmed Division II college in the heart of Topeka that bears an unusual school nickname, the Ichabods, taken from its founder, Ichabod Washburn.

Simmons was a walk-on cornerback from Lee’s Summit West High School. Ballentine was a track star at Shawnee Heights High School in Tecumseh, Kan., who fell in love with football.

Brad Nicks, Ballentine’s track and field coach and defensive coordinator on the Shawnee Heights football team, said Ballentine could have run track at plenty of Division I schools, but preferred football.

Ballentine and Simmons held much in common. Both were from strong, supportive families with professional parents. Both grew up in suburban areas and demonstrated a passion for sports. Ballentine’s father is a salesman for a home improvement firm, and Navarro Simmons, 40, is a financial adviser who recently took up bodybuilding.

At Washburn, their sons became instant friends and eventually roommates in an off-campus apartment, not far from where the shooting occurred. Their parents often sat together in the stands, watching their sons play cornerback.

According to those who knew them best, Dwane and Corey were inseparable. Simmons, who majored in mass media, was the more outgoing one, a gregarious sort with a magnetic smile, a penchant for hilarious impersonations and friends across campus, many of whom attended a vigil for him after he died.

The Washburn football coach, Craig Schurig, said he often envisioned Simmons as a future entertainer. And when time came to rev up the defense before a game, Simmons was its conductor.

“Dwane always made you laugh,” said Braden Rose, a freshman defensive end. “He had a smile that lit up the room.”

Ballentine, who was born in Jamaica and moved to Kansas when he was about 6, was quieter and more focused on his schoolwork and training regimen.

“Dwane got Corey to open up and be more social,” Navarro Simmons said. “Corey pushed Dwane with his books and workouts.”

Simmons sustained two torn A.C.L.s, impeding his career, but Ballentine’s flourished as he developed into a fiercely competitive defensive back and an electrifying special teams player. He won the Cliff Harris Award as the top defensive player in the country from a smaller college.

Schurig, who has coached Washburn for 17 years, said if Ballentine had played at a major program like Kansas or Missouri, an N.F.L. team would have drafted him no later than the third round.

”There won’t be a D-back in the league more powerful than him,” Schurig said.

A Night of Great and Terrible Fortune
Ballentine and his father, Karl Vaughn, declined to be interviewed for this article, but a few days after the shooting, Navarro Simmons said he spoke to Corey again and asked him to recount everything from the day his son died.

Talking about his son, Simmons said, especially with the friend who was with him at the end, helped both of them cope in the weeks after Dwane died. Navarro Simmons also knows that if he is still in shock, Ballentine must also still be traumatized by the events and wary that the killers remain at large, aware by now of exactly whom they attacked.

Simmons says it is vital to set the record straight about what happened in the hours leading up to the shooting.

As usual, the pair were together. First, they went to Ballentine’s parents’ home in a well-manicured subdivision of Topeka to await the results of the draft along with family and friends. Soon after the Giants chose Ballentine with the 180th pick, Ballentine spoke on a conference call with reporters, assuring them that he would not be overwhelmed by big-city life.

“I have no character issues,” he said. “I have none of those issues.”

Later, the friends celebrated, first at a small gathering with teammates. Eventually, Simmons and Ballentine ended up at a house rented by fellow students near the corner of Southwest 13th and Southwest Lane Streets, in a residential area, to celebrate with members of the Washburn women’s soccer team and others.

“There was nothing wrong about where they were,” Navarro Simmons said. “They are college students out on a Saturday night.”

Shortly after midnight, Ballentine, Simmons and a few others left the party and convened on 13th Street. They contemplated their next move. According to Cochran, the police chief, a car rolled up and people in it asked the men on the street if they had any drugs, and were told no. Then people in the car asked the players’ names, but were rebuffed again.

The car then moved forward about 30 yards, witnesses told the police, stopped, and someone opened fire, as many as 40 rounds, some neighbors said.Vandellia Clarke, a 24-year-old caregiver who lives around the corner, said she heard the shots clearly.

“We’ve been living here 20 years and there has never been any issues,” she said. “But it sounded like a war zone.”

Cochran said the seemingly arbitrary nature of the crime makes solving it a challenge. “It was one of those things, probably to scare people, with no real intent. Just senseless gun violence.”

Ballentine told Navarro Simmons that he did not know he had been struck until he sought safety in the nearby home of a friend, and called another friend to take him to the hospital — all the while growing increasingly alarmed that Dwane Simmons did not answer his phone.

“Everybody was like, ‘Why did Corey leave Dwane?’” Navarro Simmons said. “Understand, Corey was shot, too. Corey was scared, too. You hear shots, you run.”

After speaking with Ballentine, Navarro Simmons and Dwane’s mother embarked on a panicked, one-hour drive to Topeka. By the time they arrived, their son was dead.

Life Without Dwane
The Giants sent two representatives to the funeral, a former player and special assistant, Jessie Armstead, along with the athletic trainer, Ronnie Barnes. Navarro Simmons said he was not aware of the gesture, but is now very appreciative.

“I didn’t know who was there,” he said. “I was just focused on my son in front of me in a casket.”

Ballentine was granted time to recover before he had to report to the team in May for rookie workouts.

Schurig, who spoke at the funeral, said that the university was preparing a scholarship in Dwane Simmons’s name and that the team would honor him in additional ways, including naming an award for him.

On a recent afternoon, Navarro Simmons met a reporter in his favorite coffee shop in Kansas City, Mo., wearing a T-shirt bearing a photograph of Dwane flashing his signature smile. A high school classmate of Navarro’s stopped to offer condolences, which Simmons said happens continually now.

As he attempts to process his loss, Simmons said he hoped Ballentine could do the same. He also encouraged Ballentine to make the most of this opportunity with the Giants. Dwane, he said, would have wanted Corey to show the world just how good Washburn cornerbacks are.

“Dwane was so happy for Corey,” Simmons said. “He loved Corey. That was his brother.”
	
  
</documents>