<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<documents>
  
    
ICE Used Facial Recognition to Mine State Driver’s License Databases WASHINGTON — Immigration and Customs Enforcement officials have mined state driver’s license databases using facial recognition technology, analyzing millions of motorists’ photos without their knowledge.

In at least three states that offer driver’s licenses to undocumented immigrants, ICE officials have requested to comb through state repositories of license photos, according to newly released documents. At least two of those states, Utah and Vermont, complied, searching their photos for matches, those records show.

In the third state, Washington, agents authorized administrative subpoenas of the Department of Licensing to conduct a facial recognition scan of all photos of license applicants, though it was unclear whether the state carried out the searches. In Vermont, agents only had to file a paper request that was later approved by Department of Motor Vehicles employees.

The documents, obtained through public records requests by Georgetown Law’s Center on Privacy and Technology and first reported on by The Washington Post, mark the first known instance of ICE using facial recognition technology to scan state driver’s license databases, including photos of legal residents and citizens.
Sign Up for On Politics With Lisa Lerer
A spotlight on the people reshaping our politics. A conversation with voters across the country. And a guiding hand through the endless news cycle, telling you what you really need to know.

SIGN UP
Privacy experts like Harrison Rudolph, an associate at the center, which released the documents to The New York Times, said the records painted a new picture of a practice that should be shut down.

“This is a scandal,” Mr. Rudolph said. “States have never passed laws authorizing ICE to dive into driver’s license databases using facial recognition to look for folks.”

He continued: “These states have never told undocumented people that when they apply for a driver’s license they are also turning over their face to ICE. That is a huge bait and switch.”

The use of facial recognition technology by law enforcement is far from new or rare. Over two dozen states allow law enforcement officials to request such searches against their databases of driver’s licenses, a practice that has drawn criticism from lawmakers and advocates who say that running facial recognition searches against millions of photos of unwitting, law-abiding citizens is a major privacy violation.

The F.B.I., for example, has tapped state law enforcement’s troves of photos — primarily those for driver’s licenses and visa applications — for nearly a decade, according to a Government Accountability Office report. The bureau has run over 390,000 searches through databases that collectively hold over 640 million photos, F.B.I. officials said.
Editors’ Picks


Our Best Fourth of July Recipes: Hamburgers, Coleslaw, Homemade Ice Cream and More

He’s Spent Just One Night on His Private Island. He’s Had Enough.

The House Where My Husband Doesn’t Exist

The Georgetown researchers’ documents covered 2014 to 2017, and it was not immediately clear if those states still comply with the ICE requests. Representatives for the states’ motor vehicles departments could not immediately be reached for comment Sunday night.

Matt Bourke, an ICE spokesman, said the agency would not comment on “investigative techniques, tactics or tools” because of “law-enforcement sensitivities.”

But he added: “During the course of an investigation, ICE has the ability to collaborate with external local, federal and international agencies to obtain information that may assist in case completion and subsequent prosecution. This is an established procedure that is consistent with other law enforcement agencies.”

The researchers sent public records requests to each state, searching for documents related to law enforcement’s relationship with state motor vehicles departments. They received varying degrees of responsiveness but discovered the ICE requests in Utah, Washington and Vermont, which have come under fire before for sharing driver’s license information with the agency.

The Seattle Times reported last year that Washington State’s Department of Licensing turned over undocumented immigrants’ driver’s license applications to ICE officials, a practice its governor, Jay Inslee, pledged to stop. And a lawsuit in Vermont filed by an activist group cited documents obtained under public records law that showed that the state Department of Motor Vehicles forwarded names, photos, car registrations and other information on migrant workers to ICE, Vermont Public Radio reported this year.

The relationship between Washington’s Department of Licensing and ICE officials may prove to be particularly interesting to privacy experts because of a law the State Legislature passed in 2012 stipulating that the department could use a facial recognition matching system for driver’s licenses only when authorized by a court order, something ICE did not provide.

Facial recognition technology has faced criticism from experts who point to studies that show that recognition algorithms are more likely to misidentify people of color — and in particular, women of color. At least 25 prominent artificial-intelligence researchers, including experts at Google, Facebook and Microsoft, signed a letter in April calling on Amazon to stop selling its facial recognition technology to law enforcement agencies because it is biased against women and racial minorities.
The use of the technology has also come under fire from a bipartisan group of lawmakers. The House Homeland Security Committee, led by Representative Bennie G. Thompson, Democrat of Mississippi, will hold a hearing on Wednesday grilling Department of Homeland Security officials about their use of facial recognition. The chairman of the House Committee on Oversight and Reform, Representative Elijah E. Cummings of Maryland, has pledged to investigate the use of the rapidly expanding technology in the public and private sectors.

“This technology is evolving extremely rapidly, without any, really, safeguards, whether we are talking about commercial use or government use,” Mr. Cummings said at a hearing on the issue last month. “There are real concerns about the risks that this technology poses to our civil rights and liberties, and our right to privacy.”
  
    
    
Justice Dept. to Replace Lawyers in Census Citizenship Question Case
WASHINGTON — The Justice Department announced on Sunday that it was replacing the legal team defending the Trump administration’s effort to place a citizenship question on the next census, a change that is all but unprecedented in legal battles as consequential as the one over the 2020 head count.

The department said in a statement that it was “shifting these matters to a new team of Civil Division lawyers going forward.” It offered no explanation for the en masse change, which came on the heels of an extraordinary week in a yearlong clash over the issue that has raised concerns about whether the department’s arguments for adding the question could be believed.

And it strongly suggested that the department’s career lawyers had decided to quit a case that at the least seemed to lack a legal basis, and at most left them defending statements that could well turn out to be untrue.

“There is no reason they would be taken off that case unless they saw what was coming down the road and said, ‘I won’t sign my name to that,’” Justin Levitt, a former senior official in the Justice Department under President Barack Obama, said on Sunday.
Sign Up for On Politics With Lisa Lerer
A spotlight on the people reshaping our politics. A conversation with voters across the country. And a guiding hand through the endless news cycle, telling you what you really need to know.

SIGN UP
Kerri Kupec, a department spokeswoman, cast the change in a positive light, saying in a statement that the lawyers had “given countless hours to defending the Commerce Department and have consistently demonstrated the highest professionalism, integrity and skill inside and outside the courtroom.”

Attorney General William P. Barr “appreciates that service,” she added, “and is confident that the new team will carry on in the same exemplary fashion.”

But according to a Justice Department lawyer who spoke on the condition of anonymity for fear of retaliation, no lawyers from the department’s federal programs branch — which customarily defends the administration’s policies in court — would be working on the census issue. A senior official confirmed that federal programs was being taken off the case.

Lawyers who had been working on the case apparently concluded that they faced three problems. They had told the Supreme Court that they were up against a strict deadline of June 30 for printing the census forms, and there were difficulties in finding a new justification for the question that would not seem invented out of whole cloth. They may have also concluded that there was no way to move speedily enough to restore the question in any event, given that constitutional and statutory frameworks seem to require a lengthy administrative process before new questions may be added to the census.

The change in the legal team appeared to signal even deeper problems for the administration’s effort to put the question on the next census, a proposal that critics have assailed as an ill-disguised plot to manipulate the final head count in ways that would benefit the Republican Party.
Editors’ Picks


Our Best Fourth of July Recipes: Hamburgers, Coleslaw, Homemade Ice Cream and More

Is Cold Brew Better Than Iced Coffee?


He’s Spent Just One Night on His Private Island. He’s Had Enough.
The department’s lawyers had for months defended assertions by Commerce Secretary Wilbur Ross that the Justice Department sought the citizenship question so that it could acquire better data to enforce the 1965 Voting Rights Act. Three federal courts ruled that that explanation was clearly an excuse for some other goal, and last month the Supreme Court agreed, saying the question could be asked only if the department came up with a believable rationale.

The Justice Department abandoned the fight after that ruling, telling a federal judge that the battle was over “for once and for all,” only to be blindsided last week by President Trump, who said on Twitter that the statements were “fake.” Mr. Trump suggested that the head count could be delayed until he found a way to add the citizenship question, perhaps by printing an addendum that could be tacked onto the questionnaire.

That prompted a cascade of troubles. On Wednesday, Justice Department lawyers returned to a Maryland court that was hearing a case against the question to recant their admission of defeat. “The tweet this morning was the first I had heard of the president’s position on this issue, just like the plaintiffs and Your Honor,” Joshua Gardner, a lawyer working on the census issue, told Judge George J. Hazel of United States District Court.

Mr. Gardner and other department officials told Judge Hazel and a second judge in Manhattan overseeing another census lawsuit that the search for a way to place the question on the census would continue. But lawyers for opponents of the question pounced on that declaration on Friday, arguing that the Justice Department had insisted repeatedly — including to the Supreme Court — that it was essential to wrap up the dispute by the end of June, lest the census be delayed for lack of time to print questionnaires and other forms.

The Supreme Court relied on that deadline, the plaintiffs noted, in leapfrogging the legal appeals process to take the case directly from a lower federal court to a hearing before the justices. But having lost the legal battle, they argued, the Justice Department says there is ample time to hunt for some other way to achieve its goal.

The government’s “‘heads I win, tails we’ll see’ approach undermines confidence in both their ability to conduct the 2020 census and public confidence in the rule of law,” the plaintiffs argued. “If any ordinary litigant engaged in such conduct, sanctions would be the minimum relief provided. And defendants are no ordinary litigants.”

The Justice Department has been under fire from the moment Mr. Trump took office. In district and appellate court, the department has defended the Trump administration against litigation spurred by the president’s travel ban, his immigration policies and his stance on the Affordable Care Act.
Much of that work has fallen to lawyers in the federal programs branch. Known for being particularly apolitical, lawyers in that division pride themselves on their ability to argue vociferously for any policy that the White House supports, no matter who is in office.

But career lawyers have pushed back against pressure from the Trump White House for nearly two years, particularly when asked to reverse legal positions that they had already argued in court. They have refused to sign a wide array of legal briefs, and some have even resigned.

The defiance culminated in a showdown last summer after the department, under Attorney General Jeff Sessions, declined to defend parts of the Affordable Care Act. A longtime career lawyer, Joel McElvain, resigned over that decision, and the department scrambled to find another career lawyer willing to sign the brief that outlined the decision to reverse course.

After that incident, lawyers in federal programs held a standing-room-only meeting to address rancor over the health care reversal. Attendees told The New York Times that lawyers asked whether political considerations had edged out a sound legal opinion, and whether they were considered the president’s enemies.

Rank-and-file employees had hoped that Mr. Barr, a veteran of the department, would act as a buffer against White House demands that they feel are not legally defensible.

Nearly a half-dozen current and former employees say morale has not risen considerably under Mr. Barr, citing the fact that he allowed the Justice Department to stop defending all of the health care law at the behest of Mr. Trump. And now he has replaced the entire team working on the census question.
  
    
    
Trump and His Aides Dismiss Reports of Disease and Hunger in Border Facilities
WASHINGTON — President Trump and his top immigration officials on Sunday contested reports that migrant children were being held in horrific conditions in federal detention facilities, as the administration argued that the government was enforcing oversight standards even as it struggled to house and care for an influx of migrants.

Accounts of disease, hunger and overcrowding have multiplied in recent days, but Kevin K. McAleenan, the acting secretary of homeland security, and Kenneth T. Cuccinelli II, the acting director of United States Citizenship and Immigration Services, maintained that the facilities were safe.

Pressed on a report by The New York Times and The El Paso Times in which Border Patrol agents and others who had visited a facility in Clint, Tex., described crying children, cases of chickenpox, scabies and shingles, and inadequate medical care, Mr. McAleenan dismissed the details as “unsubstantiated.”

“What I can tell you right now is that there’s adequate food, water,” he said in an interview on ABC’s “This Week.” “For over a year, there’s been showers there.”
Sign Up for On Politics With Lisa Lerer
A spotlight on the people reshaping our politics. A conversation with voters across the country. And a guiding hand through the endless news cycle, telling you what you really need to know.

SIGN UP
Still, he and Mr. Cuccinelli acknowledged that the government’s resources had been strained by the surge of migrants seeking asylum at the southwestern border.

“It’s an extraordinarily challenging situation,” Mr. McAleenan said. “I’m not denying that there are challenging situations at the border.”

Speaking to reporters, Mr. Trump called the report about the Clint facility a “hoax.”

“The Fake News Media, in particular the Failing @nytimes, is writing phony and exaggerated accounts of the Border Detention Centers,” he wrote on Twitter. “First of all, people should not be entering our Country illegally, only for us to then have to care for them. We should be allowed to focus on United States Citizens first. Border Patrol, and others in Law Enforcement, have been doing a great job.”

The Times said in a statement that it stood by the article. “We are confident in the accuracy of our reporting on the U.S. Border Patrol’s detention centers,” the statement said.

With Congress set to return on Monday after a weeklong recess for the Fourth of July holiday, lawmakers are preparing to confront the accounts of squalor in the border facilities and reports of current and former Border Patrol agents deriding migrants and making vulgar remarks about Democratic lawmakers in a private Facebook group.
Editors’ Picks


Our Best Fourth of July Recipes: Hamburgers, Coleslaw, Homemade Ice Cream and More

The House Where My Husband Doesn’t Exist


The Sports Bra Seen Round the World Has New Meaning 20 Years Later
Mr. McAleenan and Mark Morgan, the acting commissioner of Customs and Border Protection, have been called to testify this week before the House Oversight and Reform Committee to discuss the concerns.

Mr. Cuccinelli, speaking on “Fox News Sunday,” asserted that the detention facilities he had personally visited were safe and being run well. He focused partial blame on lawmakers, who struggled for months to reach an agreement on $4.6 billion in humanitarian aid for agencies and officials working at the southwestern border.

“If they keep coming, people in the House come down and complain about them keep coming while not helping fix the problem,” Mr. Cuccinelli said, referring to a group of Democratic lawmakers who toured Texas border facilities last week and shared troubling accounts from migrants held there.

“It’s the height of hypocrisy,” he added.

With the long-delayed aid approved before Congress left for its recess, Mr. McAleenan said the ability of the Department of Health and Human Services to care for migrant children had improved.

Within the Democratic caucus, however, the debate over the allocation of that funding left wounds, with several members objecting to approving the money without more oversight. Congress still needs to pass legislation to fund all of the agencies and departments into the next fiscal year.

“He can say throw more money at a broken system, at an inhumane system,” said Representative Rashida Tlaib, Democrat of Michigan and one of the lawmakers who visited Texas last week, referring to Mr. McAleenan’s remarks. Her vote against the aid, she said, “was because we knew this was not the choice that we needed our country to move forward on.”
  
    
    
Cables from UK's ambassador to the US blast Trump as 'inept,' 'incompetent'

(CNN)Diplomatic cables sent from the United Kingdom's ambassador to the United States back to London describe President Donald Trump as "inept," "insecure" and "incompetent," a UK government official confirmed Saturday to CNN.

The leak could cause serious diplomatic damage between the two "special relationship" allies.
While foreign envoys of all nations are often candid in classified dispatches back home, there are periodic episodes when such assessments leak, causing great political embarrassment. Months of efforts by the ambassador, Kim Darroch and his diplomats to build ties and trust with Trump and his political acolytes will be undermined.

Darroch used secret cables and briefing notes to warn the UK government that Trump's "career could end in disgrace," and described conflicts within the White House as "knife fights," according to the Daily Mail.
A UK government source told CNN the memos described in the Daily Mail story are genuine.
The Daily Mail says the memos span the period between 2017 to present day, covering everything from Trump's foreign policy to his 2020 reelection plans.
In one memo dated June 22, according to the Daily Mail, Darroch questioned Trump's claim that he pulled back from retaliating against Iran last month after the downing of a US drone because the President was told at the last minute that US air strikes could kill 150 Iranians.
He also said in a cable to the Foreign Commonwealth Office that while he believed Trump can't afford to lose much support, he thinks there's still a "credible path" for his reelection.
The White House told CNN it had no comment on the story.
The leaked cables come at a sensitive time in UK politics with Conservative Party members currently electing a new prime minister to succeed Theresa May, who was effectively toppled by her own members of Parliament for failing to deliver on her country's 2016 vote to leave the European Union.
"The British public would expect our Ambassadors to provide Ministers with an honest, unvarnished assessment of the politics in their country. Their views are not necessarily the views of Ministers or indeed the government. But we pay them to be candid. Just as the US Ambassador here will send back his reading of Westminster politics and personalities," a statement from the British FCO said.
"Of course we would expect such advice to be handled by Ministers and civil servants in the right way and it's important that our Ambassadors can offer their advice and for it remain confidential. Our team in Washington have strong relations with the White House and no doubt that these will withstand such mischievous behaviour," the statement continued.
The favorite for the job, Boris Johnson, is seen as likely to seek to forge a much closer relationship to Trump than May, who made strenuous efforts to court the President and developed a respectful relationship but never really bonded with him politically. If it leaves the EU, Britain will be seeking to seal a bilateral trade deal with the US and Trump is expected to drive a hard bargain. So there will be speculation that the leak of Darroch's memos was a politically motivated act by someone in London to clear space in Washington for an outspokenly pro-Brexit ambassador.
Darroch also used to work as national security adviser to former British Prime Minister David Cameron and as a top UK representative to the EU, so although he's a career diplomat, he is not seen as philosophically aligned with the crowd of hardcore Brexiteers expected to take over 10 Downing Street.
Johnson is unpredictable, politically incorrect, a populist and deeply critical of the EU and is often accused of blurring facts -- traits which he shares with Trump.
There is so far no reaction from the President's Twitter feed.
But Trump has never felt constrained from criticizing the British government.
Several times, he has embarrassed May after criticizing her handling of Brexit negotiations. He plunged into Britain's internal affairs in June by openly rooting for various Conservative candidates in the leadership elections. And he has waged a long-running feud with London's mayor Sadiq Khan.
Trump also raised some eyebrows in the UK by repeatedly praising Nigel Farage, one of the most prominent campaigners for Brexit.
Trump has in the past suggested Farage, whom he called "a friend of mine," should become the UK ambassador to the US. That idea was quickly ruled out by Downing Street.
Farage rushed to Trump's defense on Sunday, tweeting: "Kim Darroch is totally unsuitable for the job and the sooner he is gone the better."
Darroch had been riding high on the success of Trump's trip to the UK in June which largely went off without a hitch. His position with the Trump administration however now looks difficult at best. Though his memos are deeply sensitive given the source, the unflattering depiction of the Trump White House is one that will be recognizable to readers of US media outlets.
  
    
    
Joe Biden invokes Obama to defend record, says he's sorry for remarks on working with segregationists

mter, South Carolina (CNN)Joe Biden in a speech on Saturday invoked his time as vice president to Barack Obama to mount a vigorous defense of his record on issues of race and also apologized for comments he made last month about his ability to be civil and work with segregationist senators in the 1970s.

Biden's remarks on Saturday were his most forceful rebuttal to attacks on his record to date, a notable shift that signals the former Vice President acknowledges he will have to engage more directly with the criticism being launched against him from some of his 2020 Democratic rivals than he has done in the past.
He used his speech at an event in South Carolina -- where black voters made up about 61% of the Democratic primary electorate in 2016 -- to respond to criticism he has received from some of his 2020 Democratic opponents on his decades-long record in public office, including his opposition to desegregation busing and his involvement in the 1994 crime bill.

To do so, he pointed to his record on civil rights and accomplishments in the administration of the nation's first black president.
"I was vetted by him and selected by him," Biden said of Obama. "I will take his judgment of my record, my character, and my ability to handle the job over anyone else's."
Biden cast his career as a US senator in the context of a changing America and acknowledged he had changed as well.
"America in 2019 is a very different place than the America of the 1970s. And that's a good thing," Biden said. "I've witnessed an incredible amount of change in this nation and I've worked to make that change happen. And yes -- I've changed also."
"If you look at the issues I've been attacked on, nearly every one of them is for something well before 2008. It's as if my opponents want you to believe I served from 1972 until 2008 -- and then took the next eight years off. They don't want to talk much about my time as Vice 
Comments about segregationist senators
At a fundraiser in June, Biden recalled being a member of the Senate in the 1970s with Southern Democrats who opposed civil rights and desegregation, noting that while he disagreed with them, "there was some civility" and "we got things done." On Saturday, Biden said he regrets making those comments.
"Was I wrong a few weeks ago to somehow give the impression to people that I was praising those men who I successfully opposed time and again? Yes, I was. I regret it," Biden. "I'm sorry for any of the pain or misconception I may have caused anybody."
His Saturday speech comes after California Sen. Kamala Harris confronted him at the first Democratic debate about his comments on working with segregationist senators, as well as his past opposition to desegregation busing.
When asked in Hartsville, South Carolina, Sunday by CNN's Kyung Lah about her thoughts on Biden's apology, Harris said, "I think that he is right to recognize the impact of his words, and I applaud him for doing that, having the courage to do it," but she also made note of their differing stances on busing.
"There is still a point of disagreement between he and I," she said.
Asked again to respond to Biden's apology, Harris said, "He says he's sorry, and I'm going to take him at his word. But again that doesn't address the issue of busing in America."
She continued: "We cannot rewrite history about what segregationists were doing at that time on a number of issues including opposing busing."
Biden told CNN in an exclusive interview that aired Friday that his stance on busing was taken out of context and that he wasn't expecting Harris to attack him the way she did. When excerpts of his speech were released on Saturday, Harris spokesperson Ian Sams tweeted, "every candidate's record will (and should) be scrutinized in this race," adding, "It's a competition to become President of the United States. There are no free passes."
New Jersey Sen. Cory Booker, another 2020 Democratic contender, brought the issue to the forefront after Biden's comments on working with the segregationist senators, calling on the former vice president to apologize and saying Biden was "wrong" for using those relationships as examples of how to bring our country together."
Booker had also taken issue with Biden's use of the word "boy" while talking in the past.
"These are the kind of things that do cause hurt and harm," Booker told CNN soon after Biden's initial comments.
On Saturday, Booker responded to Biden's apology, saying, "First I want to say thank you. We are at a point in our country where we need our leaders to be able to speak towards race issues without falling into a defensive posture or shifting blame. I can't believe when that first sprouted up that Vice President Biden said I should apologize. So, I feel a sense of gratitude and we all should, I think at least, should give him that gratitude and that thanks."
Biden on the 1994 crime bill
In his speech on Saturday, Biden also confronted another part of his record that has been a source of criticism from his 2020 rivals: His role in passing the 1994 crime bill. Biden said his record on the issue has been "grossly misrepresented" but added that he accepts responsibility for what went right and what went wrong with the legislation.
"In the 1980s and 1990s, violent crime was out of control. The crime bill was designed to deal with that problem. That's why it was supported overwhelmingly by the Democratic party, by African American leaders all across the nation including a majority of the black caucus in the Congress," Biden said.
"It worked, it worked in some areas. But it failed in others. Like every major change, you go back and you make it better," he added, later saying, "I supported the bill. I will accept responsibility for where it went right. But I will also accept responsibility for what went wrong."
Biden on war and banking
On Iraq, the former vice president argued that Obama still entrusted him with a portfolio that included the country -- despite Biden's now-unpopular vote to authorize the use of force in 2002.
"I voted to give authority to Bush what turned into the Iraq War, but it didn't stop President Obama from within the first month turning to me to handle Iraq once we took office, giving me the responsibility to coordinate all the agencies. To bring home 150,000 combat troops from Iraq, including my son who spent a year there."
Biden also pushed back on suggestions he may be too close to the banking industry and defended his support for a bankruptcy bill which he famously sparred over with Massachusetts Sen. Elizabeth Warren, who is also challenging for the Democratic nomination.
"The fact of the matter is, I'm not beholden to banks. I supported the bankruptcy bill because I believe taking a very bad bill that was going to pass overwhelmingly and making it better made sense," he said.
  
    
    
Warren and Harris Rise in Democratic Primary, Challenging Male Front-Runners
LAS VEGAS — When Beth Krerowicz began reviewing the platoon of Democratic presidential candidates, her first instinct was to back Joseph R. Biden Jr., whom she saw as the strongest opponent to President Trump.

But recently, Ms. Krerowicz, 58, began to have second thoughts. So this week she trekked to a community center not far from the Las Vegas Strip to watch Senator Elizabeth Warren of Massachusetts detail her plans for reshaping the economy. Ms. Krerowicz, an executive assistant who is between jobs, said that she was now leaning heavily toward Ms. Warren, and that Senator Kamala Harris of California was her second choice.

“I want someone who I know will stand up, that has a backbone,” Ms. Krerowicz said, suggesting that Ms. Warren and Ms. Harris could perhaps form a ticket. “They’re both very, very strong women. I would love to see them together, but I think Elizabeth has the experience.”

In the span of just a few weeks, voters like Ms. Krerowicz have pushed the race into a new, highly uncertain phase, propelling a pair of women toward the top of the Democratic pack at the expense of the onetime front-runners, Mr. Biden and Senator Bernie Sanders of Vermont.
Sign Up for On Politics With Lisa Lerer
A spotlight on the people reshaping our politics. A conversation with voters across the country. And a guiding hand through the endless news cycle, telling you what you really need to know.

SIGN UP
Neither woman is yet in a position to take control of the race. Mr. Biden and Mr. Sanders retain considerable advantages, most notably the backing they enjoy among working-class voters and their significant financial reserves. Mr. Biden, 76, is still the clear front-runner, and both he and Mr. Sanders, 77, are not likely to see their support simply melt away.
But recent polls, and interviews with voters in the early primary and caucus states over the last week, found that Ms. Harris and Ms. Warren had plainly broken through, drawing on a deep hunger within the Democratic electorate for big ideas and groundbreaking female leadership.

Together, the two senators have functioned as something of a political pincer, squeezing Mr. Biden and Mr. Sanders from the left and the relative center, and endangering any hope of an easy march to victory for either man.

After Ms. Harris’s searing clash with Mr. Biden over his record on race in the first primary debate, she claimed for herself a chunk of Mr. Biden’s formidable support among African-Americans and white liberals. And Ms. Warren, with her relentless focus on economic inequality and political corruption, and her full portfolio of progressive policy proposals, has cut deeply into the coalition Mr. Sanders built during his 2016 campaign.
Editors’ Picks


Our Best Fourth of July Recipes: Hamburgers, Coleslaw, Homemade Ice Cream and More

He’s Spent Just One Night on His Private Island. He’s Had Enough.

On the Fourth of July, Melania Trump Dresses for Independence
Their performances in the first debate lifted both women, with Ms. Harris making an especially sharp ascent after confronting Mr. Biden — a showdown that convinced some voters she had the toughness necessary for the general election.

“I just think she has the moxie to bring it to the Donald,” said Claire Haws, a stay-at-home mother from Des Moines, who contributed to Ms. Harris’s campaign after watching her in the debate.

[Which Democrats are leading the 2020 presidential race this week?]

Yet both women still face a complex path forward, one complicated by the enduring strengths of Mr. Biden and Mr. Sanders, and perhaps most of all by each other. While they have distinct political bases, Ms. Warren and Ms. Harris are both relying on the support of women and educated liberals to propel their candidacies. That strategy also means they are dividing up powerful constituencies that could in theory make one of them a dominant figure.

  
    
    
As Democrats Demand Complete Mueller Report, Views Shift on Grand Jury Secrecy

WASHINGTON — What happens before grand juries is ordinarily secret, forever. But courts have made occasional exceptions to satisfy the demands of history.

They have unsealed President Richard M. Nixon’s 1975 grand jury testimony, taken after he resigned in the face of all but certain impeachment.

They have ordered the disclosure of evidence gathered by grand juries investigating espionage cases during the Cold War against Alger Hiss and Julius and Ethel Rosenberg. And they have opened files concerning a 1964 jury-tampering case against James R. Hoffa, the labor union leader.

Until very recently, the power of courts to make such decisions — to balance the competing interests of grand jury secrecy against the historic value of grand jury evidence — was not particularly controversial.
Sign Up for On Politics With Lisa Lerer
A spotlight on the people reshaping our politics. A conversation with voters across the country. And a guiding hand through the endless news cycle, telling you what you really need to know.

SIGN UP
Indeed, “every federal court to consider the issue” has concluded that judges have the “inherent power” to unseal grand jury materials, Chief Judge Diane P. Wood of the United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit, in Chicago, wrote in a 2016 decision unsealing documents about an espionage investigation of The Chicago Tribune during World War II.

In recent months, the landscape has shifted. Perhaps it is a coincidence, but the change came as House Democrats started to seek a complete copy of the report by the special counsel, Robert S. Mueller III, including grand jury materials.

In April, just before a redacted version of the report was released to the public, a divided three-judge panel of the District of Columbia Circuit ruled that judges had no inherent authority to unseal grand jury materials.

Then last month the full 11th Circuit, in Atlanta, announced that it would reconsider a February ruling from a divided three-judge panel that had ordered the release of documents concerning a 1946 mass lynching. A judge dissenting from the panel’s decision had written that courts had no power “to grant themselves the authority to decide that the historical significance exception should exist and what the criteria should be.”

If the recent developments are battlegrounds in a proxy war over the Mueller report, the collateral damage could include history itself.
Editors’ Picks


Our Best Fourth of July Recipes: Hamburgers, Coleslaw, Homemade Ice Cream and More

The House Where My Husband Doesn’t Exist


He’s Spent Just One Night on His Private Island. He’s Had Enough.
Grand jury secrecy is important. It allows investigations to be conducted discreetly, and it protects reputations. The Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure allow disclosure of grand jury materials in only a few circumstances, none of which include completing the historical record.

The Justice Department, under presidents of both parties, has said those rules are the end of the matter. Though judges are not listed among the people covered by grand jury secrecy rules, department officials said, they may not disregard them.

But that argument has until recently gotten very little traction. In 2012, a committee of federal judges rejected an Obama administration proposal to add a limited exception to the rules allowing the disclosure of some historical records. Such an exception, the committee said, was a solution in search of a problem.

“In the rare cases where disclosure of historic materials had been sought,” a committee report said, “the district judges acted reasonably in referring to their inherent authority. Therefore, there is no need for a rule on the subject.”

The D.C. Circuit case that unsettled that consensus in April concerned an abduction reminiscent of the murder in October of the Saudi journalist Jamal Khashoggi. In 1956, Jesús de Galíndez Suárez, a professor at Columbia University, disappeared from the streets of New York City.

Professor Galindez seems to have been kidnapped, flown to the Dominican Republic and murdered by associates of its dictator, Rafael Trujillo. A grand jury investigated whether John Joseph Frank, a former F.B.I. agent, had played a role in the matter. Stuart A. McKeever, a historian, sought access to those records.

Judge Douglas H. Ginsburg, writing for the majority, rejected Mr. McKeever’s request, saying courts were powerless to grant it. That was bad news for historians, but it did not directly address the status of the Mueller report.
To the contrary, Judge Ginsburg wrote that his ruling was not at odds with the D.C. Circuit’s 1974 decision in Haldeman v. Sirica, which allowed the release of sealed grand jury records on the Watergate investigation to the House Judiciary Committee, which was looking into possible grounds for impeaching Mr. Nixon. That disclosure, Judge Ginsburg wrote, was based not on the trial judge’s inherent authority but on a specific exception in the rules for materials to be used “in connection with a judicial proceeding.”

In dissent, Judge Sri Srinivasan said the Haldeman decision settled at least this much: “A district court retains discretion to release grand jury matter to a House committee in the specific context of an impeachment inquiry.”

Mr. McKeever’s lawyers have asked the full D.C. Circuit to rehear his case, McKeever v. Barr. In opposing the request, the Justice Department expressed concern that a ruling in Mr. McKeever’s favor could make grand jury records “available in all cases — not just closed cases of historical interest.”

Roman Martinez, a lawyer with Latham Watkins who represents Mr. McKeever, said courts should not lose sight of the basic issue.

“The American people have a strong interest in understanding key events in our nation’s history, including events that were the subject of grand jury proceedings,” he said. “District judges should be allowed to release historically significant grand jury materials when the passage of time has eliminated the need for secrecy and the public interest supports disclosure.”

“In those circumstances,” he said, “there’s no good reason to keep such materials hidden from the American people.”
  
    
    
Iran set to announce further reductions to nuclear commitments on Sunday
(CNN)Iran will announce on Sunday new reductions to its nuclear commitments agreed to in the unraveling Iran nuclear deal, the state-run Islamic Republic News Agency reported Saturday.

Sunday marks the end of a 60-day deadline Iran had issued to remaining members of the nuclear deal to ease restrictions on its banking and oil sectors. IRNA cited Iranian Foreign Ministry spokesman Sayed Abbas Araqchi and Behrooz Kamalwandi, the spokesman for the Iranian Atomic Energy Organization, with the news.
Iranian President Hassan Rouhani and French President Emmanuel Macron discussed the deal during a phone call Saturday, according to IRNA and the Élysée presidential palace in Paris.
In May of this year, Iran announced a partial withdrawal from the nuclear accord signed with the United States, China, France, Germany, Russia and the United Kingdom. Rouhani said at the time that Iran would no longer abide by some of its commitments regarding the production of fissile material, due to President Donald Trump reneging on the agreement in May 2018 and increased diplomatic and military pressure on Tehran.
Under the 2015 deal, formally called the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action, Iran agreed to slash its stockpile of enriched uranium by 90% and cap uranium enrichment at 3.67%. The agreement also reduced the number of its centrifuges by two-thirds.
During Saturday's phone call, Macron voiced "his strong concern about the risk of a further weakening of the 2015 nuclear agreement, and the consequences that would necessarily follow," the palace said in a statement. He agreed to explore options with Rouhani "for a resumption of dialogue between all parties" by July 15, according to the palace.
According to IRNA, Rouhani called on the European Union to act on its commitments to the nuclear deal and pointed to ending sanctions on Iran as a possible a way to move forward on the faltering accord.
"The European Union should fulfill more of its commitments and take more actions to salvage the deal," Rouhani said during the call, according to IRNA, later adding that "stopping all sanctions can be the beginning of dynamics between Iran and the P5+1." The P5+1 refers to the UN Security Council's five permanent members (China, France, Russia, the UK and the US) and Germany.
Rouhani also used the occasion to condemn US sanctions and pressures on Iran, calling it a "full-fledged economic war" and warning that the situation "could lead to further threats in the region and the world," according to IRNA.
The French palace added that Macron will continue talking with "Iranian authorities and the international partners concerned" over the next few days to try and decrease tensions related to the Iranian nuclear issue.
Rouhani warned on Wednesday that the nation would begin enriching uranium at a higher level within days, shortly after Iran announced it had in fact exceeded limits on its low-enriched uranium stockpiles.
"We will raise the level of enrichment to the amount we want and need," Rouhani said at a government meeting, according to the semi-official Tasnim News Agency.
Rouhani also urged the US -- despite having withdrawn from the JCPOA -- and European signatories to "go back to their commitments in the nuclear deal."
CORRECTION: This story has been updated to correct the date the United States withdrew from the Iran nuclear deal.
  
    
    
New prime minister urged to scrap Theresa May’s controversial migration target in ‘clean break’ from toxic policies

The next prime minister must distance himself from Theresa May‘s hardline immigration stance and scrap the discredited pledge to reduce net migration to the “tens of thousands”, a new report has urged.

Research by the British Future think tank found broad support among both Leave and Remain voters for ditching the target in favour of individual targets for different groups, such as skilled workers and low-skilled workers.

More than seven out of 10 Tory voters would back such a move, and 60 per cent of the general public, in a sign that Ms May dogged defence of her controversial target was out of keeping with public opinion.

Boris Johnson and Jeremy Hunt were urged to make a clean break with Ms May’s policies but both candidates face a “trust deficit” in the wake of controversies over the hostile environment policy and the treatment of the Windrush generation.

Sunder Katwala, director of British Future and co-author of the report, said: “Whichever candidate makes it to No 10, they will start with a major trust deficit on immigration, the legacy of Theresa May’s approach.
Mr Hunt has opposed the target – which The Independent has fought to end through our Drop the Target campaign - and insisted the a post-Brexit Britain will not become “Little England [that] pulls down the shutters and says, foreigners not welcome.”

Meanwhile, Mr Johnson has suggested an Australian-style points based system and said the UK must remain open to skilled migrants.

However, they face an uphill battle to get the public on board. Distrust was so deep that polling found Mr Johnson has lost the trust of 49 per cent of the public on immigration and trusted by 22 per cent – a net score of minus 27.

Fewer people said they distrusted Jeremy Hunt on immigration (41 per cent) but only 13 per cent say they trust him on the issue – a net score of minus 28.
Distrust in politicians is widespread, however, with no politician of any party securing a positive rating. Labour leader Jeremy Corbyn’s trust rating on immigration is minus 37.

Only 18 per cent of people – and a quarter of Tory voters – think Ms May did a good job on managing immigration.

James Kirkup, director of the Social Market Foundation think tank and contributor to the report, said: “Anyone who leads Britain needs to have an honest conversation about immigration, its challenges and its benefits.
  
    
    
Labour faces summer of internal feuding amid deselection threat to MPs
Labour faces a “fratricidal” summer of internal feuding which could see dozens of moderate MPs stripped of the right to defend their seats at at the next election, party insiders have warned.

For the first time, the party is operating under new rules for choosing election candidates in Labour-held seats which many believe is designed to remove critics of leader Jeremy Corbyn.

After a change agreed at last year’s annual conference, the threshold for a “trigger ballot” requiring a sitting MP to fight a reselection contest has been cut from half to one-third of local branches and affiliated unions.

The process kicks off on Monday, when sitting MPs are required to inform the party whether they wish to stand as candidates in the general election which many believe could come as early as the autumn.
Some well-placed insiders estimate that as many as 70 MPs – almost a third of the parliamentary party – could be “triggered”, with half of them going on to lose their battle for reselection.

A meeting last week of the Future Britain Group of Labour moderates saw around 30 MPs discuss strategies for seeing off the deselection threat and concerns about bullying and intimidation within local parties. Further meetings are planned.

Tom Watson, the deputy leader, who set the group up following the defection of a number of MPs to the Independent Group earlier this year, is understood to have sought clarification about the process from party officials.

Labour moved last week to assure Lewisham West and Penge MP, Ellie Reeves, that her reselection process will be delayed to ensure she is not forced to battle for her position while pregnant.
But other MPs are braced for what one insider forecast would be a “fratricidal summer” at a time when they believe they should be concentrating their attack on the new Conservative prime minister.

Bermondsey and Old Southwark MP, Neil Coyle, told The Independent: “The prospect of an election should be focusing the energy and time of all parts of the party on making sure we are battle-ready and instead we are going to see Labour people fighting among themselves.
“The spectacle of division and internal fighting when we have a government wreaking such damage on people’s lives and on the country is distinctly unattractive to voters.”

Mr Coyle, who has been a persistent critic of the Corbyn leadership, said he hopes to fend off a trigger ballot, and believes he can win a reselection battle if required to fight for his position.

But he said it would mean activists’ time and resources being “locked down in the constituency” rather than taking the battle to target seats.
“It’s pathetic, it’s avoidable and it doesn’t help Labour win elections,” he said. “It sends a signal to ordinary people that there are some around Jeremy who don’t care about winning, they just care about internal discipline and control.”

Ilford North MP Wes Streeting – who recently suggested Mr Corbyn should consider his position in the wake of a poll putting Labour in fourth place on 18 per cent – said that the “messy and unpredictable” process could backfire on the party’s left wing.

“It won’t just be Corbyn critics at risk but some of his own supporters too, because people are ambitious and have agendas other than factional politics,” he said.

“I don’t think the leadership have properly thought through the risk of a running commentary in the media on MPs scrabbling to clear the trigger ballot process.

“It is going to soak the life and energy out of so many people when we should be concentrating on winning seats from Conservatives. Labour MPs and local parties will be caught up in a time-consuming battle against other Labour people. It is not a pretty picture.”

Mr Corbyn faces the risk that deselected MPs could continue to sit in the Commons as independents until the next election, which may not come until 2022, potentially forming a large centre-left faction on the opposition benches.

And others who fight off deselection attempts will be able to claim a personal mandate on the basis of platforms which deviate from official policy on issues like Brexit.

Amid growing demands among activists for the party to throw its full weight behind a Final Say referendum and a Remain vote, under-threat MPs are likely to use a strong anti-Brexit stance to win support among members in their constituencies.

No timetable has yet been released for the completion of the reselection process, but it is thought likely it will conclude by the autumn in readiness for a possible early election around the time of the UK’s scheduled departure from the EU in October. Some in the party speculate that the leadership may wish to avoid September’s annual conference in Brighton being overshadowed by a bitter battle over the potential deselection of local MP and Corbyn critic Peter Kyle.

A Labour Party spokesperson said: “Ahead of a possible general election, Labour will begin a reselection process of MPs. We are preparing for a general election whenever it comes.

“Under long-standing Labour Party rules, reselection processes are held within every Labour-held constituency between each general election.”
  
</documents>