<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<documents>
	
		
		Employee Activism Is Alive in Tech. It Stops Short of Organizing Unions.
		In February, about a dozen employees at a small technology company called NPM embarked on an effort that is often frowned upon at start-ups: trying to unionize.

		For more than three months, the workers had battled the company’s new management over their hours, a changing workplace culture and diversity issues, said seven current and former NPM employees. So to give themselves more say, they moved to organize. The employees contacted labor groups, including the International Federation of Professional and Technical Engineers and the Tech Workers Coalition, to hold unionization discussions.

		“We wanted the leverage to negotiate for things that were important to us as workers, rather than having them told to us,” said Graham Carlson, who was a content marketing manager at NPM, which provides tools to web developers. “We felt the best way to address it was to address it collectively.”

		Three weeks after the workers began organizing, NPM laid off Mr. Carlson and four other employees, all but one of whom had been involved in the unionizing. After some of those employees filed a formal charge with the National Labor Relations Board, the federal agency that oversees such complaints, NPM settled with the workers last month. No union has been formed.
		We did not interfere with any of our employees’ efforts to unionize,” NPM’s chief executive, Bryan Bogensberger, said in a statement.

		Tech workers at Silicon Valley’s largest companies have engaged in an unusual degree of activism over the past few years — and it has gotten results. At Google, employees have written letters and signed petitions to force their leaders to address issues such as how artificial intelligence is used in products. Last November, 20,000 Google employees staged a walkout to protest the firm’s handling of sexual harassment, leading to new company policies. Workers at Amazon, Facebook, Microsoft and Salesforce have also pushed for various changes.

		But the failed unionization effort at NPM shows the obstacles to employee activism in the tech industry, and how moving from speaking out for change to collective bargaining so far remains a distant prospect.

		The difficulties are echoed at other tech companies where recent moves to set up unions have also stalled. At Kickstarter, the crowdfunding site, a unionization effort this year has floundered as organizers struggle to build support. And last year at Lanetix, a logistics software company, more than a dozen engineers were fired after trying to create a union, according to a complaint issued by the N.L.R.B.

		A representative from Kickstarter’s organizing campaign said it was “continuing to do the hard work of building a union.” David Gallagher, a Kickstarter spokesman, said its executives had told staff that “Kickstarter is better positioned to overcome its challenges, serve its mission, and do right by its employees and community without the framework of a union.” He added that the company was “in no way seeking to impair the rights of staff members to organize.”

		Lanetix’s former chief executive and the company, which has since rebranded as Winmore, did not respond to requests for comment.

		Labor advocates said there were limits to how much tech workers could achieve without actually unionizing. “You can have this magical moment — the Google walkout was inspiring for all of us — but there’s a question of sustainability,” said Liz Shuler, the secretary-treasurer of the AFL-CIO.

		But tech workers who aim to unionize face challenges. Many employees see their bosses as friendly peers rather than authority figures and are reluctant to mobilize against them. In other cases, highly compensated engineers may see themselves as independent operators who have plenty of leverage on their own and thus do not need to join a union effort.

		They think of themselves as white-collar labor; they think of themselves as people with money,” said CJ Silverio, the former chief technology officer of NPM who left the company last year and was not involved in the recent organizing effort. “They don’t see that collective bargaining will get them something.”

		If workers get as far as trying to organize a union, management sometimes takes aggressive action — including dismissals — to prevent them from doing so. And when workers appeal those dismissals to entities such as the N.L.R.B., tech companies often have the resources to resolve the cases without allowing a union to form.

		NPM settled the case brought by three of its former employees, who filed charges with the N.L.R.B. alleging they had been dismissed in retaliation for trying to set up a union, paying the workers more than $105,000, according to the employees and the company. Lanetix also settled with 15 workers for $775,000 last year over unfair labor practices claims after negotiations with the N.L.R.B.

		Sahil Talwar, who worked at Lanetix as a software developer and was part of the unionization effort, said tech companies worked to make unions seem alien. “Associating unions with blue-collar work and making it a stigma to talk about unions in white-collar circles, that’s very deliberate,” he said.

		NPM began as an open-source software project in 2009 before being incorporated in 2014. Based in Oakland, Calif., it has raised more than $10 million from investors and employs around 50 people, a company spokesman said.

		For years, NPM had a forgiving corporate culture, said the current and former employees, three of whom spoke on the record while the others requested anonymity because they feared retaliation. Employees joked that NPM stood for “nice people matter.” (It initially stood for Node Package Manager.) Engineers said they were encouraged to take regular breaks and avoid burnout.

		That changed last July when new executives were appointed. To prepare for the debut of a new product, employees were required to work extended shifts and be on call at all hours, the current and former employees said.

		In February, they sent a letter to management about their work hours but said they did not receive a satisfactory response. An NPM spokesman said the company had met one of the letter’s demands — for the tech support department to report directly to engineering.

		At a corporate retreat that month in Napa, Calif., employees raised their concerns with management. They said they had been told that they would need to adopt Silicon Valley’s hard-charging, never-sleep culture or leave the company.

		Mr. Bogensberger, the chief executive, presented slides warning employees not to be dramatic, which workers interpreted as a veiled reference to their complaints about overwork. Employees also said that women and minorities did not have equitable opportunities for promotion. The company spokesman said NPM had a nearly equal split of male and female employees, though it employs proportionally few minorities.

		At the corporate retreat, employees met to discuss unionization, two of the current and former employees said. In March, NPM laid off the five employees, leading to the filing of a charge of unfair labor practices with the N.L.R.B. before the company settled.

		“As a fairly outspoken proponent of socialism, it’s really weird and surprising to be accused of union-busting,” Laurie Voss, an NPM co-founder and chief data officer, wrote on Twitter in May. “The allegations in the complaint are not true.”

		Just because many tech workers appear skeptical of unions, and so many tech companies have avoided unions, doesn’t mean they will indefinitely. Mar Hicks, a historian who has written extensively about labor in the tech sector, said the kinds of actions many workers had already taken, like the walkouts, were often precursors to unionizing. Workers eventually realize that their confrontations with management won’t deliver lasting improvements without a formal organization to back them up.

		Some tech employees grasp that logic already. “I never felt I needed a union before,” said Frédéric Harper, a former NPM employee who participated in the organizing effort and N.L.R.B. case. “I reached a point where I think it’s maybe a good idea, maybe it’s needed.”
		
	
	
		
		NYU professor: Regulators must keep Facebook's Libra from becoming a default currency
		Mild horror" is an appropriate reaction to Facebook's cryptocurrency plans, says Scott Galloway, a marketing professor at NYU's Stern School of Business.

		"We are rightfully concerned," Galloway told CNN's Julia Chatterley on "First Move" Monday morning, in a discussion also about his new book "The Algebra of Happiness: Notes on the Pursuit of Success, Love, and Meaning."
		"To take over society is three legs of a stool: First you get control of the media, then you get control of the money and that leads to control of the military," Galloway added. "Facebook has not done a great job of taking control of the media ... Do we really want to give them control of the economy and our money right now? Buyer beware."
		He criticized Libra, a digital currency Facebook announced last month that will be managed by the independent nonprofit Libra Association in Switzerland, to grow Facebook (FB)'s power and influence. That's something regulators and others were worried about even before the Libra announcement, as Facebook has come under fire for issues like its failure to protect user data and foreign actors' use of the platform to interfere in the 2016 US presidential election.
		Facebook's 2.4 billion users around the world positions Libra to be adopted by a much wider audience than other cryptocurrencies. This could mean Libra has a shot at becoming a new default currency like the dollar or the euro, Galloway said, which could have serious implications for the global economy because it would not be managed by a central bank like traditional currencies.
		"We could have the mother of all negative unintended consequences if we let Facebook establish the new default currency," said Galloway, who is also the author of "The Four: The Hidden DNA of Apple, Amazon, Facebook and Google," about how Big Tech companies became so powerful and deeply ingrained in daily life.
		Facebook, however, has said Libra will be backed 1:1 by a reserve of stable currencies overseen by the Libra Association. The company has also said it is working with regulators on the cryptocurrency's rollout, and that it has plans in place to protect Libra users' data.
		Galloway called on regulators in the United States and globally to respond to Libra. He added that if anything goes wrong with the project, it will not be Facebook's fault -— but the fault of regulators not reacting appropriately and customers who buy in anyway.
		Leaders around the world have already begun to speak out with concerns about the project and American lawmakers have planned two hearings on Libra next week, where Facebook executive David Marcus has said he plans to testify. House Financial Services Committee Chairwoman Maxine Waters of California and other Committee Democrats sent a letter last week asking Facebook to immediately halt development of Libra while it examines the project further and considers regulatory action.
		Facebook gets more official pushback on Libra
		The company has not said whether it will comply with the lawmakers' request, but Facebook did release a statement: "We look forward to working with lawmakers as this process moves forward, including answering their questions at the upcoming House Financial Services and Senate Banking Committee hearings."
		Galloway said lawmakers have thus far done a poor job of regulating Facebook, and that Libra is a chance to course-correct. He also blamed users who have remained on the platform despite its missteps.
		"I think you're naturally seeing what I would call a well deserved and well earned gag reflex around this idea," Galloway said. "They're trying to do everything right: Set up an independent body in Switzerland, make it a nonprofit. But there's one problem ... it comes from Facebook. And people just are like, 'Burn me a million times, shame on you, burn me a million and one times, shame on me.'"
		Beyond regulating Libra, Galloway also spoke about rising calls from politicians, competitors and others to break up Facebook and fellow Big Tech giants Amazon (AMZN), Google (GOOGL) and Apple (AAPL). Federal regulators in June divided up oversight of those companies between the FTC and the Justice Department, paving the way for potential investigations into antitrust violations.
		Galloway said he thinks breaking up those companies is not only the "right thing" to do, but it would also be good for the economy.
		"WhatsApp, Instagram, YouTube would all be amazing, independent companies," Galloway said. "If you look at all the big breakups in the past in our economy, three to five years post-breakup, the companies are worth more disaggregated. So these stocks are going to skyrocket once breakup actually becomes a reality."
		That would mean happy investors and, in companies like Facebook and Amazon where executives control much of the stock, CEOs like Mark Zuckerberg and Jeff Bezos ending up even richer.
		
	
		
		
		Emojis are increasingly coming up in court cases. Judges are struggling with how to interpret them
		Can a knife emoji double as a threat to kill someone? Does a heart emoji from a manager constitute sexual harassment?

		More emojis are showing up in court cases throughout the United States. Attorneys are having to argue for different interpretations of the small illustrated characters that are used to express emotions, activities or objects. And courts are struggling to handle the nuances of emojis as evidence.
		"Many courts haven't had to deal with the emoji much, but the numbers are up and it will likely increase," Vinson  Elkins partner Jason Levine, who has worked on cases with emojis as evidence, told CNN Business. "Judges aren't prepared for the influx, especially ones who are older and may not be familiar with newer vernacular."
		The number of reported cases with emojis as evidence in the United States increased from 33 in 2017 to 53 in 2018, and is at nearly 50 so far in the first half of 2019, according to Eric Goldman, a Santa Clara University law professor who monitors court opinions that are made public.
		No court guidelines exist on how to approach the topic. Sometimes a judge might describe the emoji in question to jurors, rather than allow them to see and interpret it for themselves. In some cases, emojis are omitted from evidence altogether, Goldman said.
		Emojis are most prevalent in sexual harassment and criminal cases. An emoji with Xs for eyes — also known as the "dizzy face emoji" — was an issue in a 2017 murder case in Massachusetts. Prosecutors argued that the emoji showed that an individual who received it knew "something was happening."
		Emojis are increasingly showing up in workplace lawsuits, too. For example, in an employee termination case related to a possible violation of family medical leave, a manager sent a series of smiley face emojis. The plantiff's lawyers claimed it was evidence the company was happy to let her go.
		"Someone may use threatening symbols, a gun, a pointed finger, and then behind it put a symbol for 'just joking,'" said attorney Karen S. Elliott of Eckert Seamans Cherin  Mellott, a firm that has worked on cases with emojis. "There is a lot that could get lost in the translation. Was it a joke? Or was it serious? Or was the person just using the emoji to hedge so that they could later argue it was not serious?"
		Emojis are not a 'universal language'
		There are more than 2,823 emojis set by the Unicode Consortium, ranging from food and drink to hand gestures, activities and facial expressions.
		Emojis can be especially misinterpreted when used without text, according to ABI Research analyst Stephanie Tomsett. For example, a face with sunglasses could be used to convey a sunny day, feeling cool or "deal with it." Similarly, the emoji with smoke coming out of the nose could be read as "angry" when it's intended to mean "triumph."
		"Emojis cannot be considered a universal language," Tomsett said.
		That's especially true when you consider how symbols vary by culture. The thumbs-up gesture has been up for debate as offensive or vulgar in the Middle East, while it's a sign of something good in other parts of the world. A smiley face emoji is taken as sarcasm in China.
		But one of the biggest points of contention for emojis in court cases is that they render differently on varying platforms, whether you're using, say, an Apple iPhone or a Samsung Galaxy device. Although the Unicode Consortium sets the standard for emojis, software makers, such as Apple and Google, then design versions for their platforms, opening up a path for inconsistencies and miscommunication. For example, the pistol emoji looks like a real gun on some devices and a water or toy gun on others.
		In a 2016 study from the University of Minnesota, participants rated popular emoji characters on Android and iOS as positive or negative. In the case of the emoji called "a grinning face with smiling eyes," some people interpreted the image as "blissfully happy" on Android, while it looked like it was "ready to fight" on iOS.
		Another study found about 25% of participants were unaware the emojis they posted on Twitter could appear differently based on their followers' devices. After being shown how one of their tweets rendered across platforms, 20% said they would have edited or not sent the tweet.
		"Earlier on, we may have all thought all smiley faces were the same, so it might have seemed OK to the courts for the evidence to come in simply as a smiley face," attorney Elliott said. "Then someone realized that the smiley face from Google might be interpreted differently than the smiley face from Apple -- and that might make a difference in the evidence in the case."
		Was that emoji a joke or a threat?
		Some experts such as ABI Research's Tomsett argue there should be consistency across platforms to avoid confusion. But she believes standardized emojis are unlikely because platforms want to "stand out and offer unique experiences." However, she believes they could start to look increasingly similar to help alleviate some of these issues.
		Attorney Elliott argues courts will need to develop literature that requires lawyers to obtain the exact depiction of what was sent and received on each platform, and show it to the judge and jurors in a case. "Words may not adequately describe the precise emoji meaning," she said.
		Of course, emojis are commonly used to bring levity to conversations. Courts generally recognize attempts at humor, and defendants have invoked "I was just joking" defenses for centuries.
		According to Elliott, the courts and judges are becoming more skeptical about this defense in criminal cases because the recipient doesn't know whether it's actually a joke.
		"As long as the threat is conveyed, it remains a threat,' she said. "For example, you can't yell 'fire' in a crowded theater and then say 'just joking.'"
		Some judges omit emojis as evidence because they think it's superfluous, according to professor Goldman. He referenced a sex-trafficking case in which an expert witness detailed how a series of sent emojis, including a crown, high heels and bags of money, provided evidence of prostitution, noting a crown often references a pimp.
		"We might not think twice about a crown emoji, but in the sex-trafficking world, it added context," he said. "If a judge said 'omit emoji' and ... wasn't briefed by other parties on its meaning ... that would make it impossible for any of us to audit ... and understand what the court did to independently consider the evidence was irrelevant."
		However, Goldman believes the issue will eventually solve itself as more emojis surface in cases.
		"With the proliferation of any new technology, there is an adjustment period for everyone, including judges," he said. "As judges become more familiar and comfortable with emojis, they will figure out the best ways to adapt existing legal principles to [them]."
		
	
		
		
		SpaceX shares vibrant footage from its first-ever nose cone recovery
		SpaceX just shared some footage from a successful attempt to recapture part of a rocket's nose cone after it plunged into the ocean. The results are stunning.

		The maneuver last month marked the first time after a launch that a piece of the rocket's cone, which is also called a fairing, was recovered. The fairing guided itself into a giant net hoisted up by a crew boat. SpaceX has been trying to do this for more than a year.
		The company shared some footage this week from a camera on board the fairing during its descent. The video shows a stream of neon-blue light flowing around the object as it falls back to Earth after reaching a speed more than nine times the speed of sound.
		"Friction heats up particles in the atmosphere, which appear bright blue in the video," SpaceX said in a tweet that included the video.
		Also visible in the footage is a parachute — shaped like a giant stick of gum — that the fairing deployed.
		A second video captured by a camera aboard the net-wielding crew boat, named Ms. Tree, shows one of the fairing halves land gently on its target.
		The fairing rests on the top of the rocket, and it acts as a shield for satellites that SpaceX launches for its customers. Once the rocket is in space, it splits into two and falls away. After most rocket launches, the fairing halves are left to plummet back to Earth, where the ocean becomes their graveyard.
		SpaceX's rocket fairings costs about $6 million, CEO Elon Musk has said.
		And as he once put it: If "you had $6 million in cash on a pallet flying through the air, and it's going to smash into the ocean, would you try to recover it? Yes. Yes, you would."
		The company has always said it wants to reuse as much of its hardware as possible in order to drive down launch costs. But recovering and reusing a fairing had never been done before. SpaceX tried numerous different iterations of its fairing recovery plan before last month's success.
		Recovering and reusing parts of its rockets is at the core of SpaceX's plans to make its launch vehicles cheaper. The company has already mastered its technique for landing first-stage rocket boosters, which provide the initial boost at liftoff before detaching from the second stage.
		Rather than letting the booster fall into the ocean, which is how most rocket parts are discarded after launch, SpaceX devised a way to steer and land its first-stage boosters on ground pads or autonomous seaborne platforms, called drone ships.
		
	
		
		
		Samsung warns its profit fell 56% as memory chips and smartphones struggle
		Samsung is warning investors that its second quarter profit likely plunged 56%, as the company continued to struggle with sluggish demand for memory chips and smartphones.

		The South Korean tech giant said Friday that it expects to make an operating profit of 6.6 trillion Korean won ($5.6 billion) for the quarter ended June, down from about 14.9 trillion Korean won ($12.7 billion) for the same period a year ago.
		The earnings forecast was better than analysts' downbeat expectations, thanks to what Samsung (SSNLF) called a "one-time gain related to the display business." The company supplies display screens to other smartphone makers like Apple (AAPL).

		Samsung's profits have taken a beating over the past year, largely because of a slump in its memory chip business. The company's operating profit last quarter fell to its lowest level since late 2016, when it was dealing with the fallout from its Galaxy Note 7 smartphones exploding and catching fire.
		A supply surplus and slowing demand for memory chips have created a "tough" environment for Samsung, Rick Seo, an analyst with HSBC, wrote in a recent note to investors.
		Weak sales of Samsung's latest flagship phone didn't help. Analysts at brokerage firm Daiwa Capital Markets said in a note that sluggish sales of the company's Galaxy S10 will lead to lower smartphone revenue for the quarter.
		Samsung is the world's biggest seller of smartphones. It also has a huge business making key components for rival device manufacturers and is ramping up its 5G network equipment business.
		That makes the company a potential winner and loser from the current troubles facing Huawei, the world's largest telecommunications equipment maker and No. 2 smartphone seller.

		Washington added Huawei to a trade blacklist in May, barring US companies from selling vital tech and components to the Chinese tech giant. In the month immediately following the restriction, Huawei said it saw a 40% drop in overseas sales of its smartphone business.
		President Donald Trump changed course and eased restrictions on the Chinese company last week, but it still remains unclear what products American firms can supply to Huawei.
		SK Kim, an analyst with brokerage firm Daiwa Capital Markets, said Huawei likely helped memory chip sales in the second quarter as the company was stockpiling supplies. But the US restrictions on Huawei will have "a negative impact" on demand in the coming months, he said.
		That would put even more pressure on chipmakers like Samsung to drop prices.
		On the upside, Kim said Samsung's smartphone shipments are already seeing "positive impact from the US sanctions on Huawei" and he expects the company's smartphone and network equipment businesses will further benefit from Huawei's woes in the second half of this year.
		Samsung is expected to report full earnings at the end of the month.
		
	
		
		
		CNN Exclusive: Bill Gates calls Steve Jobs a 'wizard' who saved Apple
		Steve Jobs was a wizard who "cast spells on people" to help keep Apple afloat during the company's darkest days, according to longtime rival Bill Gates.

		The Microsoft (MSFT) founder discussed his and Jobs' leadership styles with CNN's Fareed Zakaria Sunday. Both men are known for being tough leaders who foster an intense workplace culture.
		Gates said people often emulate the negative elements of the Apple (AAPL) founder's personality, but Jobs was also a unique leader who took Apple from near-death to its pedestal as the most valuable company in the world (before Microsoft usurped that crown this year). Apple was on the verge of bankruptcy when Jobs rejoined the company in the late 1990s; it is now worth just shy of $1 trillion.
		Jobs was "a good example of 'don't do this at home,'" Gates said. But nonetheless, he added, "I have yet to meet any person who in terms of picking talent, hyper-motivating that talent and having a sense of design, of 'this is good, this is not good.' So he brought some incredibly positive things along with that toughness."
		Gates said Jobs had a way of turning around failures by "casting spells" both on his own staff and outside observers. Gates dropped a Harry Potter reference when he called himself a "minor wizard" for being able to see through Jobs' "spells."
		One prominent example: After Jobs' co-founded Apple, he built a company called NeXT that made an expensive flop of a computer. Still, he managed to bring widespread attention to NeXT and sold the company to Apple in 1996.
		"It was complete nonsense and yet he mesmerized those people," Gates said. "Steve is really a singular case where the company was on a path to die and it goes and becomes the most valuable company in the world with some products that are really quite amazing. There aren't going to be many stories like that."
		Jobs died in 2011, months after he resigned from Apple because of complications from pancreatic cancer. Jony Ive, the legendary designer who worked alongside Jobs to develop many of the company's flagship products, announced last month he plans to leave the company.
		As for the culture within Microsoft, Gates acknowledged that the intensity did occasionally go "too far," especially in the company's early years.
		"We had, to some degree, a self-selected set of people who were mostly males, I'll admit, and yes, we were pretty tough on each other," Gates said. "We counted on each other to work very long hours and I always wanted to set the best example of that. I think that intensity, even though a little bit it went too far, was great for my 20s, 30s, 40s."
		Now running the Gates Foundation, Gates said he's "not pushing quite as insanely," but that focus has continued to serve him.
		"I'm still clear about, 'Hey that toilet design is too expensive, it's a dead end, we're not going to put more money into that.' That works for being the co-head of the foundation," he said.
		
	
		
		
		Iconic 80s computer The Commodore 64 to return with fully-functional keyboard
		Modern versions of iconic gaming consoles have been popularized in recent years, but the rebirth of this latest product will surely resonate with early computer users.

		Manufacturer Retro Games announced this week it is working on an updated version of the beloved Commodore 64 8-bit computer launched in 1982 and cost $595 at the time. It was teased in a trailer set to the theme song of popular 80s-themed Netflix show "Stranger Things."
		Called THEC64, the computer is a more complete replica of the mini-version also released last year by Retro Games. The updated product comes with a full-sized retro keyboard, a classic joystick and a selection of classic games, including Speedball and Cyberdyne Warrior. It will cost $199.99 when it launches in early December.
		The chunky, tan-colored Commodore 64 computer brought personal computing into the home for millions of users in the early- and mid-1980s. People used their C64s, as they were known, for everything from basic office functions to primitive games like "Impossible Mission." It was limited to 64 kilobytes of memory -- about the equivalent of one long email.
		Commodore sold more than 17 million of its C64 systems, according to the manufacturer Commodore International. The Guinness Book of World Records once listed Commodore 64 as the best-selling computer model of all time.
		Retro Games initially sought funding for the computer in 2016 with an IndieGoGo crowdfunding campaign that failed to reach its target goal. The team refocused on developing and releasing the C64 Mini first as other retro mini-consoles, such as the NES and SNES Classic Editions, exploded in popularity.
		But the retro keyboard that came with the C64 mini console was purely for show. The team rectified that decision by putting a fully-functioning keyboard in the full-sized version.
		
	
		
		
		British Airways faces $230 million fine. It would be a record under Europe's tough data privacy law
		British Airways faces a record $230 million fine after a website failure compromised the personal details of roughly 500,000 customers.

		It would be the largest penalty yet under a tough privacy rule known as the General Data Protection Regulation, which came into force last year in the European Union.
		The UK Information Commissioner's Office said that weak security allowed user traffic to be diverted from the British Airways website to a fraudulent page starting in June 2018. The regulator said the company will have a chance to contest the proposed fine.
		Attackers were able to harvest customer details including log ins, payment cards, and travel booking details, according to the regulator. The airline disclosed the incident in September 2018.
		The £183.4 million ($230 million) fine is roughly 1.5% of British Airways' annual revenue. The carrier, which is owned by IAG (ICAGY), said it would fight the penalty.
		"We are surprised and disappointed in this initial finding," British Airways CEO Alex Cruz said in a statement.
		"British Airways responded quickly to a criminal act to steal customers' data. We have found no evidence of fraud [or] fraudulent activity on accounts linked to the theft," he added.
		GDPR forces companies to make sure the way they collect, process and store data is safe. Any organization that holds or uses data on people inside the European Union is subject to the rules, regardless of where it is based. Companies that breach the law can be fined up to 4% of their annual revenue.
		"People's personal data is just that — personal. When an organization fails to protect it from loss, damage or theft it is more than an inconvenience," Information Commissioner Elizabeth Denham said in a statement. "That's why the law is clear — when you are entrusted with personal data you must look after it."
		Gita Shivarattan, data protection counsel at law firm Ashurst, said the proposed fine showed that "European data protection regulators are clearly ramping up fines for data breaches."
		"It reflects the seriousness of the regulators where there is a significant breach of GDPR obligations," added Shivarattan.
		The Information Commissioner's Office has become an increasingly prominent regulator in the digital space. It fined Facebook £500,000 ($626,000) last year over the Cambridge Analytica scandal, the maximum allowed before GDPR came into force.
		
	
		
		
		Trump said he'd ease up on Huawei. Questions remain about what that means
		When President Donald Trump suggested last weekend that he would relax a controversial ban on American sales to Huawei, it was welcome news for the Chinese telecom giant and its suppliers. Days later, the questions raised by his remarks remain unanswered.

		At the G20 summit in Osaka, Japan, Trump said he would allow American companies to resume sales to Huawei of products that don't pose a security threat.
		Huawei is the world's leading telecom equipment provider and an important customer of American companies. It's also central to China's technology ambitions and the global rollout of 5G wireless networks. The US government targets it as a national security problem.
		Trump's announcement followed pressure from tech companies that said the ban was hurting their profits, and after Chinese officials reportedly said they would insist on concessions for Huawei as part of a US-China trade deal.
		"A lot of people are surprised, we sell to Huawei a tremendous amount of product that goes into the various things they make," Trump said. "I've agreed to allow them to continue selling that product."
		That was last Saturday. The administration has since offered few public details about what will happen next.
		The Commerce Department did not respond to requests for comment and has not released any additional guidance on Trump's remarks. Companies are awaiting a clear answer on just how -- and when -- they'll be able to resume billions of dollars in sales to Huawei.
		It also remains to be seen whether this easing of restrictions on Huawei will be enough to convince Chinese leaders to sign on to a trade deal. Trump said he would wait until the end of the negotiations to consider additional concessions for the company, even amid ongoing national security concerns.
		Here are a few of the significant remaining questions about the announcement.
		What products will US companies be able to sell to Huawei, and when?
		Trump's comments at the G20 did not change the law, something White House officials emphasized in recent days. Because Huawei remains on the Entity List, American companies still have to apply for a license to sell to it.
		White House economic adviser Larry Kudlow said on Fox News Sunday that Huawei would remain on the Entity List, which restricts exports unless US companies obtain a license to do business with the Chinese company. Going forward, Kudlow suggested, the Commerce Department would grant more licenses, which have been difficult to obtain in the month since the ban was implemented.
		Peter Navarro, a White House trade adviser, told CNN's Jim Sciutto Friday that the US government will divide Huawei into two parts: 5G and the rest of the business. American companies will still be forbidden from doing business with the 5G part, but they will be able to sell Huawei "a modest amount of low-grade chips."
		"It allows us basically what we need to do on Huawei, but it is a bad actor," Navarro said.
		Trump administration officials have said the loosened restrictions will allow only for the sales of "general merchandise."
		It's not clear which products this does and does not include, but experts expect it will mean the sale of cell phone or 4G equipment components will resume, while sales of products used to build Huawei's 5G network equipment will not. The White House wants to curb Huawei's involvement in 5G over concerns that its equipment could be used by the Chinese government to spy on other countries — a charge that Huawei denies.
		Michael Wessel, a commissioner on the US-China Economic and Security Review Commission, said that if the loosened restrictions did allow for sales of 5G equipment components, it would reignite the same security concerns the ban initially put in place to address.
		"For Trump, this is the art of the deal, but it's an inappropriate conflation of two different policy goals — trade and national security," Wessel said.
		It's unclear when any licenses to sell to Huawei would be granted. In the meantime, some American suppliers had already found a way around the ban: resuming shipments to Huawei of products technically not "American-made" because they are produced outside of the United States.
		But, while Trump's announcement eases controls for certain products, it may also get rid of those legal workarounds, according to Scott Kennedy, a senior adviser at the Center for Strategic and International Studies.
		What does this mean for Huawei?
		Huawei relies heavily on American products, especially for its smartphone business, a major driver of the company's overall $104 billion in revenue last year. The company had expected to have a much better year in 2019 but has downgraded its revenue expectations by $30 billion. After the export ban was announced, Huawei's overseas smartphone unit sales plummeted 40%.
		If sales from American companies like Google (GOOGL) and Intel (INTC) can resume, Huawei may have a chance to recover that business.
		However, continued US pressure on Huawei's 5G efforts would be a significant negative to the company. Huawei itself said Tuesday it doesn't expect any significant changes as a result of Trump's initial announcement.
		"President Trump's statements are good for American companies. Huawei is also willing to continue to buy products from American companies," Huawei founder Ren Zhengfei told the Financial Times. "But we don't see much impact on what we are currently doing. We will still focus on doing our own job right."
		The company is also embroiled in multiple legal battles with the US government, including an American effort to extradite Huawei CFO Meng Wanzhou from Canada for alleged Iran sanctions violations. It's unclear whether those legal proceedings will be affected.
		What about national security?
		American officials have for years worried that Huawei poses a national security risk. They're especially fearful of the Chinese company's involvement in 5G, as the network is expected to power key technological innovations like self-driving cars and smart cities. The US government has also accused Huawei of stealing American companies' intellectual property. Huawei fiercely denies these claims.
		After Trump announced the concessions for Huawei, lawmakers from both parties chided him for easing up on national security-related restrictions as part of a trade dispute.
		"If President Trump has agreed to reverse recent sanctions against Huawei, he has made a catastrophic mistake," Senator Marco Rubio, a Florida Republican, said on Twitter. "It will destroy the credibility of his administration's warnings about the threat posed by the company, and no one will ever again take them seriously."
		Trump administration officials, however, said they remain committed to addressing the national security concerns and the president said the loosened restrictions were for sales of products that did not pose a security risk.
		Kennedy, the Center for Strategic and International Studies adviser, said he thinks the shift could be a means of focusing more directly on the 5G technology that the government considers the most pressing concern.
		"It seems that they are no longer focused on putting Huawei out of business or hurting their overall profitability, but restricting them in 5G," Kennedy said. "But can the administration really confirm that? And then do they have a longer term strategy to achieve this?"
		The answers to these questions have profound implications for American companies, Huawei, the future of 5G and, perhaps, the willingness of the United States and China to agree on a final trade deal at all.
		
	
		
		
		Tesla sets a record for sales, and its stock jumps 7%
		Tesla delivered 95,200 cars in its second quarter, a record for the company.

		The numbers, released Tuesday, met the company's own goal and easily outpaced the 63,000 cars delivered in the first three months of the year. They also far surpassed the 40,740 cars delivered to customers in the year-ago quarter, when Tesla was still struggling to ramp up production of the Model 3, its best-selling car.
		Shares of Tesla (TSLA) jumped roughly 7% on the news.
		Tesla's delivery figures most closely map to sales because customers do not pay full price until they receive their car.
		Wedbush analyst Dan Ives, who has a neutral rating on whether to buy or sell Tesla stock, said in a note that he was impressed by the latest sales figures — particularly by the 77,550 deliveries Tesla recorded for the Model 3.
		He said the Model 3, which is priced more for the mass market than Tesla's luxury Model S and Model X SUV, "remains the linchpin of the Tesla growth story."
		The latest figures follow what was the biggest drop in sales in its history last quarter, when sales declined from the 90,700 cars Tesla sold in the last three months of 2018.
		Tesla attributed much of that drop to logistical issues as the company began shipping the Model 3 overseas. The company said Tuesday that it's made "significant progress streamlining" its global shipping and delivery operations. That has saved Tesla a bundle of cash, and boosted the number of sales Tesla was able to notch in foreign markets.
		The company is "well positioned to continue growing total production and deliveries" in the quarter that just began, according to the press release. Tesla also received more new orders last quarter than the total number of deliveries it recorded. That could indicate that there's still strong demand for Tesla vehicles.
		Some investors and Tesla critics had suggested that consumer appetite for the electric vehicles was petering out. It also faces more competition from traditional automakers that are introducing their own electric cars. CEO Elon Musk has repeatedly said that demand for Tesla vehicles is strong.
		Part of the drop in sales Tesla recorded during the first quarter was caused by somewhat unique circumstances. What had been a $7,500 tax credit for Tesla buyers dropped in half as of January 1. So many buyers rushed to buy cars at the end of 2018 to get the full reduction in their federal tax bill. That pulled ahead some sales that otherwise would have been recorded in the first quarter.
		The first quarter drop in sales also prompted new concerns about a cash crunch for the company, and caused problems for its once high-flying share price. Tesla (TSLA) shares have lost more than a quarter of their value since the start of the year.
		In April, the company posted a first-quarter loss of $702 million. Ives had earlier described the period as an "apocalyptic" three months for the car maker.
		Musk told shareholders at the time that the company could theoretically post positive earnings in the second quarter if it optimized its delivery schedule. But he added that wouldn't be in Tesla's long-term interests.
		Tesla has not yet said when it is reporting second quarter earnings. The company expects to post its first profit of 2019 in the third quarter.
		In the meantime, investors will be closely watching for hints about ongoing demand for Tesla's electric cars, as well as details about the company's cash reserves. Tesla has large debt payment obligations on the horizon.
		The tax credit for Tesla vehicles was once again cut by 50% on Monday, to $1,875 from $3,750 for buyers who were able to complete a sale by the end of June, and it's set to disappear completely at the end of 2019.
		Tesla has said in financial disclosure documents that losing the incentives "could have some negative impact on demand for our vehicles, and we and our customers may have to adjust to them."
		
	
</documents>