<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<documents>
	
		
		What NBC’s “Songland” Says About the Sad State of Songwriting
		“The Middle,” one of 2018’s best and biggest pop hits, passed through the hands of five producers, seven songwriters, and 15 different vocalists before it was released by Zedd, Grey, and Maren Morris. The song’s trajectory from demo to chart-topping single—down to the provenance of a curious medieval axe sample—was helpfully, and entertainingly, chronicled in a New York Times “Diary of a Song” video. Other entries in the series highlight just how many different ways there are to make a hit: Lizzo’s “Juice,” which took two producers and five writers; Sheck Wes’ “Mo Bamba,” three producers, one writer, one take; Kacey Musgraves’ “Slow Burn,” two producers, one writer, an unspecified amount of acid.

		These days, thanks to shifts in technology and cultural trends, the song-making process is somehow both more complicated and less transparent, so it remains a special treat to get a peak behind the curtain. That is the conceit of not only the Times videos but also the reality competition show “Songland,” which is currently halfway through its first season on NBC. Aspiring songwriters pitch their demos to a rotating cast of stars—so far, John Legend, will.i.am, the Jonas Brothers, Kelsea Ballerini, Meghan Trainor, and Aloe Blacc—with the hope that the guest artist will select their prospective hit, per the show’s favorite industry jargon, to be “cut.”

		Omnipresent throughout this process is a panel of professional hitmakers comprised of Ryan Tedder and Ester Dean—who’ve written some of this century’s most recognizable songs, for Beyoncé, Rihanna, and Adele—along with the prolific country songwriter-producer Shane McAnally. Each episode, four songwriters perform 90-second demos, typically including a verse, a hook, and a bridge. After some on-the-fly adjustments—change the tone and tempo to be more mournful, John Legend instructs; rephrase this cliché, suggests Tedder; let’s throw a Kanye beat on it, says Dean, pulling out an MPC on a couple of occasions—the artist selects three songwriters to move on to the next round.
		Each songwriter is then paired up with a panel member, who serves as their mentor and quasi-producer. They go into the studio and rework the song together, and then present it to the artist again, in some cases completely rewritten, in others only slightly updated to fit the star in question. (A will.i.am song is very different from a Kelsea Ballerini song, after all.) The process is represented as suspiciously easy; no writer’s block, no false starts, very little conflict. The show's producers manage to turn the tedium of the creative process into decently entertaining TV. Does “faces” actually rhyme with “strangers”? It doesn’t matter; the banter is good.

		The songwriters—many of whom describe collaborating with Dean, Tedder, and McAnally as “a dream”—are eager to absorb suggestions from the panel. While the experts do offer substantial critiques, they foster a palpably friendly atmosphere that borders on schoolteacher-y. Compliment sandwiches are employed gently to deliver potential improvements. It’s hard to believe that every song presented is as good as the panel’s head nods suggest, but it’s easy to understand why, in this current social climate of hate, there is little room for a Simon Cowell-style bully.

		This is an interesting time to launch a primetime show about songwriters: Some are getting unprecedented name recognition while many are being exploited by an industry that depends on their work. As Tedder himself put it, in an interview with NPR, “If a guy working in the mailroom of Sony comes across the next Beyoncé, he gets more notoriety for discovering that artist than the songwriter that writes the song that becomes that artist’s hit.” Moreover, he points out, songwriters are often the least paid participants in the industry. Earlier this year, members of the Songwriters Hall of Fame, led by Nile Rodgers, sent a letter to Spotify urging the streaming company to change its payment structure for songwriters. Alongside virtually every other streaming company (except Apple), Spotify had appealed a ruling from the Copyright Royalty Board earlier in the year that would have increased songwriters’ royalties through 2022. “Songwriters are not treated fairly,” Rodgers told NPR.

		Conveniently, the winning song on each “Songland” episode is available to stream or purchase immediately after airing. But on the show, there is no talk of songwriting splits or compensation at all; the real prize for the rookie, the implication goes, is exposure—just as it is across the music industry. (NBC did not respond to requests about the winning songwriters’ publishing deals.) “And it wasn’t about who ‘won’ because there are so many different opportunities for these songs once they get rewritten and re-recorded, even if it’s not right for John Legend,” McAnally told Rolling Stone. Maybe some of the writers—who are mainly peddling conventional pop songs that could be sandwiched between Halsey and Zedd on any given radio playlist, the kind of music I have come to associate with riding in the backseat of an Uber—will find luck elsewhere. But it’s easy to imagine an “America’s Top Model”-like scenario, where few contestants benefit as much as the experts do.

		“It’s this idea that I think every songwriter has had,” said Aloe Blacc on the show’s accompanying podcast, which offers more insight into the world of songwriting. “We’re trying to figure out how we can see ourselves on TV; we see singers, we see novices singing other people’s songs and we think, Why can’t we share new songs with these amazing singers, these new stars? Why can’t we show the process of songwriting?” Blacc’s “Songland” episode has an interesting twist: He’s not simply looking for any old hit single—he’s after an “anthem” to be placed in the upcoming action flick Fast  Furious Presents: Hobbs  Shaw. That purely commercial directive awkwardly articulates the sensibility of the show, but it also makes for the most engaging episode thus far. By being directly addressed, the artifice is stripped.
		As for the songs themselves, they’re mostly serviceable but hardly groundbreaking—the sorts of pop songs that can be as familiar as they are frustrating. Will.i.am’s winner, “Be Nice,” written by Adam Friedman, feels like a Bruno Mars throwaway; Meghan Trainor’s choice, the generic kiss-off “Hurt Me,” written by a 22-year-old known simply as Kole, was the first time fans of the show objected en masse, preferring a more introspective song. The other day, Dave Stewart, one half of the Eurythmics and a co-creator of “Songland,” shared with USA Today a playlist of the songs “that have captivated him in his career as a singer, songwriter and producer.” They include such tender classics as “A Change Is Gonna Come” by Sam Cooke, “California” by Joni Mitchell, and “Back to Black” by Amy Winehouse. But you’d be wrong to presume, as I initially did, that this sort of personal, soul-mining material would come out of the show’s first season. There are valiant efforts, and some iTunes chart traction, but halfway in, “Songland” is more an unintentional exegesis on the state of pop music than it is a springboard for emerging songwriters.
		
	
	
		
		Why A$AP Rocky Was Arrested in Sweden for Assault and What Happens Next
		The rapper is being held in Sweden and could face time in prison if convicted
		It’s a tumultuous time for A$AP Rocky. The New York rapper was scheduled for a trek across Europe this summer, performing live in support of his 2018 album Testing. Then, as fans back in the States were getting ready for their Independence Day celebrations, he was arrested and ordered to be held for two weeks in Stockholm, where he is under investigation for assault. Rocky, whose birth name is Rakim Mayers, reportedly faces up to six years in prison if he is convicted. Rocky’s lawyer Henrik Olsson Lilja has said his client’s actions were in self-defense.

		Here’s a summary of the events that led to Rocky being confined to a detention center in Sweden, and what may lie ahead depending on his potential release.
		March 11
		A$AP Rocky, who has been on his “Injured Generation Tour” since the start of the year, announces a string of European dates, including both festival appearances and standalone shows.

		June 26
		Rocky kicks off his European tour leg with two nights of concerts in Paris.

		June 30
		An altercation takes place in central Stockholm during the evening, and police are called. Local media at first only identify the alleged aggressor as a world-famous artist.

		July 1
		TMZ posts a video that appears to show four men, including A$AP Rocky, physically fighting with two other men.
		July 2
		Rocky shares two videos on Instagram, saying two young men had been following him prior to the incident. The men appear to claim that Rocky’s group broke their headphones. “IM INNOCENT,” Rocky writes in the comments. That night, Rocky performs at Stockholm’s Smash Festival, alongside Migos, Bad Bunny, and more. Afterward, he is arrested.
		July 3
		News of Rocky’s arrest spreads, raising new questions. TMZ reports that Rocky went to the police voluntarily and was arrested “immediately.” The site also claims that police were blocking the U.S. Embassy from meeting with Rocky and his team, reportedly a break from usual procedures and “a breach of Rocky’s human rights.” Rocky misses a scheduled performance at Norway’s Kadetten Festival.

		July 4
		Rocky misses a scheduled performance at Poland’s Open’er Festival.

		July 5
		Rocky is ordered to be held in Stockholm for at least another two weeks while Swedish authorities investigate an assault charge, The New York Times and the BBC report. The investigation will reportedly determine whether prosecutors decide to go to trial in the case, and if necessary they can apply for another two-week extension.

		Rocky’s lawyer, Henrik Olsson Lilja, tells The Times his client is being confined to a detention center after a court ruled he was a flight risk. Meanwhile, Rocky misses a scheduled performance at Dublin’s Longitude Festival.

		July 6
		Fellow A$AP Mob member A$AP Ferg says on Instagram that Rocky is “locked up in solitary confinement with no visit or phone call privileges.”

		July 7
		Rocky misses a scheduled performance at London’s Wireless Festival.

		July 8
		Rocky appeals his detention all the way to Sweden’s highest court, AFP reports. “Unfortunately the Supreme Court rejected our appeal today so Rakim is still detained,” Rocky’s lawyer tells Pitchfork in an email. “Now we continue to work with our defense plans.”

		July 10-September 28
		What will happen with Rocky’s remaining tour dates remains unclear. Through July 19, when his two-week detention period could potentially end, Rocky had been set to perform in Russia, Germany, Belgium, Ukraine, Italy, and Spain. Beyond that, his itinerary includes several other dates in Europe and North America stretching into early fall.
		
	
	
		
		Watch Car Seat Headrest Play New Song “Stop Lying to Me” in Documentary
		“I think the plan is for it to be on the next record, but it really is still a work in progress”—Will Toledo
		Car Seat Headrest have shared the final installment of “I Haven’t Done Shit This Year,” their behind-the-scenes documentary made in partnership with Tidal. The short film follows the trajectory of a new song called “Stop Lying to Me” through early rehearsals, a live performance, and the recording studio. In an interview, Will Toledo says of the song, “I think the plan is for it to be on the next record, but it really is still a work in progress.” Check out the video below.

		Last month, Car Seat Headrest released the live album Commit Yourself Completely. In August, they kick off a tour with Death Cab for Cutie.
		
	
	
		
		Sturgill Simpson to Discuss New Anime Film at Comic-Con 2019
		The forthcoming movie, Sound  Fury, “merges American rock music with anime in a way never seen before”
		Sturgill Simpson will be a panelist at San Diego Comic-Con 2019. The panel, titled “SOUND  FURY: Creators of Animatrix and Batman Ninja Unite for Sturgill Simpson,” will find Simpson accompanied by manga artist Takashi Okazaki (Afro Samurai) and filmmaker Junpei Mizusaki (Batman Ninja) to discuss Sound  Fury, their new film that “merges American rock music with anime in a way never seen before,” according to a press release. The panel will also include the premiere of the film’s 90-second trailer. It takes place Saturday, July 20.

		Sturgill Simpson recently contributed the title song to Jim Jarmusch’s new movie The Dead Don’t Die. He also appears in Queen  Slim, a new film written and produced by Lena Waithe.
		
	
	
		
		Stevie Wonder Says He’s Getting a Kidney Transplant
		He revealed that he’ll play three more concerts before undergoing the procedure this September
		Stevie Wonder has revealed that he is getting a kidney transplant this September, The Associated Press reports. He made the announcement yesterday (July 6) during a British Summer Time concert in London’s Hyde Park. According to The AP, Wonder said that he will play three more shows before he takes a break prior to surgery. In addition, he stated that he has a kidney donor. Find footage of Stevie Wonder’s announcement below (via BBC).

		Read Pitchfork’s Sunday Review of Stevie Wonder’s classic 1976 album Songs in the Key of Life.
		
	
	
		
		Ed Sheeran Copyright Trial Put on Hold for “Stairway to Heaven” Decision
		A case over similarities between Marvin Gaye’s “Let’s Get It On” and Sheeran’s “Thinking Out Loud” is delayed until Led Zeppelin’s outcome has been decided
		In 2016, the family of Ed Townsend, the co-writer of Marvin Gaye’s “Let’s Get It On,” filed a lawsuit accusing Ed Sheeran of plagiarizing elements of “Let’s Get It On” for his 2014 song “Thinking Out Loud.” Earlier this week, on July 2, Manhattan District Judge Louis Stanton vacated a trial date in September to wait for results in a similar copyright case involving Led Zeppelin’s “Stairway to Heaven,” as the BBC and Rolling Stone report (via Law360). “Take the summer off,” Judge Stanton joked about the delay, noting that if the Zeppelin case goes to the Supreme Court, it may wait until 2020. Pitchfork has reached out to representatives for comment.

		The suit against Sheeran claims that he plagiarized “the melody, rhythms, harmonies, drums, bass line, backing chorus, tempo, syncopation and looping” from Gaye’s hit. Led Zeppelin’s ongoing case involves similarities between “Stairway to Heaven” and a 1968 instrumental composition titled “Taurus” by the band Spirit.

		Read “What Led Zeppelin’s ‘Stairway’ Trial Says About Copyright’s Increasingly Blurred Lines.”
		
	
	
		
		Ed Sheeran, Bruno Mars, Chris Stapleton Link Up on New Song “BLOW”: Listen
		From Sheeran’s upcoming new album No.6 Collaborations Project
		Ed Sheeran, Bruno Mars, and Chris Stapleton have shared their new joint song “BLOW.” Watch the video below. It’s taken from Sheeran’s next LP, No.6 Collaborations Project, which is out July 12 via Atlantic. As the name suggests, the album features Ed working with different collaborators and featured artists on each track. Elsewhere on the project are Chance the Rapper and PNB Rock (on the previously released “Cross Me”), Justin Bieber (on “I Don’t Care”), Travis Scott, Stormzy, Cardi B, Camila Cabello, and more. “BLOW” is the album’s closing track.
		
	
	
		
		Listen to J. Cole’s Dreamville’s New Album Ft. Kendrick Lamar, Vince Staples, and More
		J.I.D, Ty Dolla $ign, Maxo Kream, Ari Lennox, and many others appear on Revenge of The Dreamers III
		J. Cole’s Dreamville has released its new label compilation Revenge of The Dreamers III. The record features Dreamville’s artists—Cole, J.I.D, Ari Lennox, EARTHGANG, Cozz, Bas, and Lute—and outside contributors like Vince Staples, Ski Mask the Slump God, Ty Dolla $ign, Young Nudy, and T.I., among others. Kendrick Lamar also makes an uncredited appearance on the opening track. Listen to Revenge of The Dreamers III below.

		Prior to the album’s release, Dreamville released a documentary about its creation. Revenge of the Dreamers II came out in December 2015. The first Revenge of the Dreamers was released in January 2014.
		
	
	
		
		Listen to Kanye West and Charlie Wilson’s New Song “Brothers”
		Featured in the latest episode of Irv Gotti’s BET series “Tales”
		Irv Gotti’s BET anthology series, “Tales,” premiered its latest episode last night. It featured a portion of a new song by Kanye West and Charlie Wilson of the Gap Band. Listen to “Brothers” below via Gotti’s Instagram.

		The song was previously teased in a trailer for “Tales” and marks the latest collaboration for West and Wilson. They most recently worked together on the song “No Mistakes,” which also featured Kid Cudi, from West’s most recent solo album ye.

		Gotti posted the full version of “Brothers” playing over footage from “Tales.” In the caption, Gotti wrote:

		There is a lot of speculation right now on who is Kanye West rapping about on the song brothers. So here is the song. That BET cut off because of there way of airing episodes. But it was always meant for the audience to hear the whole record. Listen. And decide for your self if you think Kanye is rapping about Jay Z or Virgil. Both Ye’s Brothers. And also let me know if you liked the episode and song. We did it for yall. My hip hop culture. -IG

		Find Gott’s full post here.

		Read “Kanye’s Sunday Service Coachella Performance Was a Sacrilegious Mess” over on the Pitch.
		
	
	
		
		Yesterday Remembers the Beatles But Forgets What Made Them Great
		According to the new film Yesterday, all it takes to scale the pop charts is a guy, a guitar, and love—though the lyrics of two of the most celebrated songwriters in human history don’t hurt either. In the world of this collaboration between British filmmaker Danny Boyle (Trainspotting, Slumdog Millionaire) and screenwriter Richard Curtis (Love Actually), most everything is identical to our own, save for the existence of the Beatles. After a global power outage, the band is inexplicably erased from the cultural memory of everyone but one man, Jack Malik (Himesh Patel), a former schoolteacher and struggling singer-songwriter. Jack soon realizes that his brain contains a gold mine: If he can remember the lyrics to every single Beatles song and pass them off as his own, he’s more than set for the rest of his life. He becomes a viral sensation and leaves behind his home in England—and more importantly, his lifelong manager, friend, and love interest Ellie (Lily James)—to relocate to L.A. and link up with a steely boardroom shark (Kate McKinnon) who ruthlessly retools his image.

		There’s endless, “Twilight Zone” potential for a concept like this. Considering the Beatles’ domineering impact over the last 50-plus years, it’s almost thrilling to imagine the creative possibilities in a world where they never existed. Would ambitious pop concept albums have come into fashion when they did? Would Brian Wilson have finished SMiLE as intended without “Strawberry Fields Forever” there to send him into a downward spiral? Would the Monkees or ELO or even Big Star have existed? What about the British Invasion? And who would we compare Migos to?

		If you’re interested in a movie that hints at any of the above questions, you’re unfortunately going to have to make it yourself. (The only ripples in history caused by the absence of the Beatles are Oasis, cigarettes, Coke, Harry Potter not existing.) For all the lip service paid to the Beatles’ universal greatness, Yesterday doesn’t even seem to understand why anyone ever thought John, Paul, George, and Ringo were so brilliant in the first place. It wasn’t just their words, which Jack fights so hard to remember, that changed pop music—it was the gorgeous melodies and symphonic soundscapes those words sat atop. Besides some lovely lyrics, there’s virtually no mention of what the Beatles actually contributed to music—no nods to their experimentation with different genres and innovative recording methods.
		The movie never really offers a sufficient reason as to why Jack’s take on the Beatles becomes successful, other than the fact that these songs were written by the Beatles, and the Beatles were geniuses, so of course their songs would tear up the charts no matter who records them, how they are performed, or when they are released. There are a few reasons for the public’s love of Jack Malik offered by the marketing shills who try to remake his earnest image: He’s not a team of 16 songwriters in a room and there’s no “featuring Cardi B or Justin Bieber,” just a baby grand piano and heartfelt words scribbled on a legal pad. Of course, there’s a double-edged irony here: Jack didn’t write the songs, and the relentless publicity machine behind him means he’s not the only one with a hand in his music. Under pressure from Ed Sheeran, whom Jack defeats in a songwriting competition, and his manager, the newfound star even changes the lyrics of “Hey Jude” to the supposedly more relatable “Hey Dude.”

		All that matters to Boyle and Curtis is the sentiment of Beatles songs, and it’s an approach the film itself takes, too. Like Jack’s shouted, muddled-sounding Beatles covers, content—not craftsmanship—is king when it comes to Yesterday. Boyle is usually a visual maximalist, even when such flair is entirely unnecessary and unmotivated, but Yesterday is oddly drab, beyond a few bizarre, iMovie-like dissolves to transition between scenes. Himesh Patel and Lily James are charming enough leads, but their ill-defined characters are little more than scratch tracks. The movie would rather focus on an extended cameo by a self-effacing Sheeran, who has more studio recordings of his own songs on the movie’s soundtrack than the Beatles do.

		Boyle and Curtis assume that a nice little love story, a reference to “When I’m Sixty Four,” and a flourish on the soundtrack that sounds like the cacophonous crescendo of “A Day in the Life” should be enough to appease Beatles fans. Maybe the Boomers this movie was made for don’t care what it looks like, but the Beatles were never so careless with the style of their own wildly imaginative films. Not to mention that there’s subversive potential contained within the movie’s premise: The entire history of rock’n’roll is white artists stealing from people of color, and now an artist of color is returning the favor and claiming the music of white artists as his own. But the movie never bothers to consider the kind of critiques its concept could be used to make.

		Yesterday ends with a rousing sing-along of “Ob-La-Di, Ob-La-Da,” a song that John Lennon notoriously regarded as just another piece of Paul’s “pure granny shit.” I suspect he might have used those same words to describe the Love Actually-ing of the Beatles’ legacy, too. The irresistible simplicity of songs like “She Loves You” or the conceptual complexity of albums like Sgt. Pepper’s alone weren’t what made the Beatles endure—it was both of those things in tandem. At least there’s comfort in knowing that, in our world, the Beatles’ meticulousness will be remembered. I can’t say the same for Yesterday.
		
	
</documents>