<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<documents>
	
		
		Spokesman: Bill Clinton 'knows nothing' about 'terrible crimes' alleged against Epstein
		WASHINGTON – A spokesman for former President Bill Clinton said Monday that Clinton "knows nothing" about Jeffrey Epstein's alleged crimes after the billionaire financier pleaded not guilty to sex-trafficking charges in Manhattan federal court.

		"President Clinton knows nothing about the terrible crimes Jeffrey Epstein pleaded guilty to in Florida some years ago, or those with which he has been recently charged in New York," according to a statement tweeted by Clinton's press secretary Angel Ureña.

		Epstein was arrested Saturday on sex-trafficking charges dating back to the 2000s, according to the Associated Press. On Monday, Epstein pleaded not guilty to one count of sex trafficking and one count of sex-trafficking conspiracy, which stem from accusations dating to 2002-2005. 

		According to the federal indictment, Epstein "sexually exploited and abused dozens of minor girls at his homes" in Manhattan and Palm Beach, Florida, along with other locations. He also allegedly paid some of his victims to recruit more underage girls, according to the indictment.

		Epstein's lawyers argued that the matter had been settled a decade ago with a plea deal in Florida. “This is ancient stuff,” Epstein attorney Reid Weingarten said Monday in court, calling the case essentially a “redo” by the government.

		In 2008, Epstein pleaded guilty in Florida to state charges of soliciting and procuring a person under age 18 for prostitution, which could have led to a lifetime in prison if prosecuted, the AP reported. Epstein was sentenced for 13 months in jail, under a non-prosecution agreement overseen by federal authorities in Florida. He was also required to reach financial settlements with dozens of his once-teenage victims and register as a sex offender.
		
		Billionaire Jeffrey Epstein pleads not guilty to sex-trafficking claims that 'shock the conscience'

		Epstein has been tied to Clinton and President Donald Trump. 

		In addition to being fellow residents of Palm Beach – where Trump’s Mar-a-Lago property is located – the president and Epstein socialized together before Trump’s 2016 election.

		On Saturday, Trump biographer Tim O’Brien tweeted this 2002 quote by the future president, taken from a New York Magazine profile: “I’ve known Jeff for fifteen years. Terrific guy. He’s a lot of fun to be with. It is even said that he likes beautiful women as much as I do, and many of them are on the younger side.”

		An attorney for the Trump Organization has said Trump had " 'no relationship' " with Epstein, the Washington Post reported Monday. But, the Post also reported that "outside of Trump’s own words, there is clear evidence that the two men — both members of the same highflying social worlds in Manhattan and Palm Beach — socialized together in the past."

		Clinton's spokesperson said in the statement that the former president had taken a total of four trips on Epstein's private airplane between 2002 and 2003, one to Europe, one to Asia and two to Africa, which included stops in connection with the work of the Clinton Foundation.

		According to the statement, staff, Clinton Foundation supporters, and Clinton's Secret Service detail traveled on every leg of every trip. In addition, in 2002 Clinton also had a meeting with Epstein at the former president's Harlem office and one brief visit to Epstein's New York apartment, where a staff member and Clinton's security detail were present.

		"He's not spoken to Epstein in well over a decade, and has never been to Little St. James Island, Epstein's ranch in New Mexico, or his residence in Florida," the statement concluded.
		
	
	
		
		Man says he killed black teen for listening to rap music. Activists want #JusticeforElijah
		PHOENIX - A man arrested on suspicion of killing a 17-year-old boy in an Arizona convenience store last week says that he killed the teenager, who did not say or do anything to threaten him, because he was listening to rap music, police said.

		The suspect, Michael Paul Adams, 27, admitted stabbing the teenager at 1:42 a.m. Thursday after he heard him playing rap music in his vehicle in a parking lot at a Circle K in Peoria, Arizona, according to police records filed in Arizona Superior Court.

		Adams had just been released from the Arizona State Prison Complex in Yuma on Tuesday, according to the Arizona Department of Corrections.

		Adams told police rap music makes him feel "unsafe" because he had been attacked by people who listen to rap music in the past, records say. He also said people who listen to rap music are a threat to him and the community.

		The suspect said he felt threatened by the music — not the teen himself — so he needed to be "proactive rather than reactive," police records said.

		Surveillance footage shows the teen walking into the convenience store and Adams walking in a few seconds later. Adams walked around the store before lunging at the teen, according to records.

		Adams used his pocketknife to stab the teen in the back and slit his throat.

		The teen ran out of the store before collapsing underneath the gas pump canopy, where police began CPR.

		He was taken to a hospital, but died at 2:05 a.m., records say.. 

		Adams was arrested on 67th Avenue near the Circle K, where he told an officer he was involved in the stabbing after being found with blood on his body and clothes.

		Adams was booked into a Maricopa County jail on suspicion of first-degree premeditated murder and is being held on a $1 million bond. He is scheduled for a preliminary hearing July 15.

		Adams’ criminal history includes theft, shoplifting, marijuana violation, disorderly conduct, assault with a weapon and aggravated assault of a correctional employee, according to Maricopa County Superior Court records.

		Jacie Cotterell, Adams’ lawyer, questioned his ability to access mental health services after he was released from prison. She said that he was “set up for failure." 

		Adams needed to see a mental health counselor but he was not given a way to access those resources, Cotterell said. “To be specific, he was given resources, he wasn’t given means to get to those resources,” she said.

		She said Adams' family did not know where he was after his release. "He was on the street,” she said.

		Bill Lamoreaux, a spokesman with the Arizona Department of Corrections, said in a written statement that Adams “was not designated seriously mentally ill.”

		He said Adams was provided contacts for community services such as continuing care, housing and welfare.

		Adams was provided transportation to Maricopa County from the Yuma prison. From there, "he was no longer under the Department’s legal jurisdiction and the Department had no further legal authority over him,” according to the statement from Lamoreaux.

		Lamoreaux said Adams will face justice in court.

		“The tragic death is terrible, and Mr. Adams will have to answer for his alleged actions,” he said in the statement.
		
	
	
		
		Tropical depression forecast to form in Gulf of Mexico this week, could strengthen into hurricane
		The hurricane season is awakening from its slumber.

		After several quiet weeks, the National Hurricane Center said Monday that there's an 80% chance a tropical depression will form by the end of the week in the Gulf of Mexico.

		If the depression's winds reach 39 mph, it would become Tropical Storm Barry.

		"Regardless of development, this system has the potential to produce heavy rainfall along portions of the northern and eastern U.S. Gulf Coast later this week," the hurricane center said.

		AccuWeather senior meteorologist Adam Douty warned that "residents from western Florida to eastern Louisiana should especially remain alert for an increase in downpours and a heightened risk for flooding later this week and into the start of the weekend."
		
		The National Hurricane Center said there's an 80% chance of a tropical depression forming near the Gulf of Mexico by the end of the week. The red X indicates where the nascent storm is now, the red shaded area shows where it could form.
		National Hurricane Center
		The storm could strengthen into a hurricane, according to BAM Weather meteorologist Ryan Maue, who said Gulf water temperatures are over 82 degrees in spots, which is "plenty sufficient for a (major) hurricane."
		Last year's monsters: From Florence to Michael, see the most devastating 2018 hurricane season photos

		Beyond the forecast of heavy rain, the hurricane center said, "At this time, it is too soon to determine the magnitude and location of any potential wind or storm surge impacts along the Gulf Coast." 

		The weather system that could spawn the tropical depression is hovering over Georgia, according to the hurricane center. That system will sink south toward the Gulf over the next few days.

		To help its residents prepare for the rain, the city of Tallahassee opened four sandbag distribution centers.

		Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis, a Republican, urged Floridians to be prepared.

		From 1950 to 2018, 67 named storms formed in July, averaging about one named storm in July each year, the Weather Channel said. 

		The strongest recent storm to make landfall in the USA in July was Hurricane Dennis, which hit the western Florida Panhandle on July 10, 2005, as a Category 3 hurricane.
		
	
	
		
		Here's a lesson for 401(k) investors: Don't just save, save to create wealth
		My mom, Tobie, worked two jobs, seven days a week from the time my dad walked out on my 10th birthday until she was almost 70 years old. She was grateful for the work – a full-time job as a supply clerk with the U.S. government and a part-time job (evenings and weekends) at Macy’s. In her 70s, after she retired, she worked part-time at the local middle school (until well into her 80s) – insisting, however, that she have Thursdays off for tap dancing lessons. 

		She saved money, bought savings bonds for her children and grandchildren and paid off her home in the San Francisco Bay Area. If hard work and determination could make one wealthy, my mother would have been a billionaire. But it can’t. You cannot save your way to wealth. You must save to invest to create wealth.

		Marilyn Monroe once said: “A wise girl knows her limits, a smart girl knows that she has none.” Most of us are not smart when it comes to investing; we limit ourselves. And that is too bad. Women tend to live longer than men, and a vast majority of us will eventually take over the family finances – we need to be prepared.
		Women, who instinctively do more research on every family transaction, tend to make excellent investment decisions. Let’s consider a hypothetical investment in a well-known company: Starbucks (SBUX). (Full disclosure: I own it personally and for my clients.) Importantly, though, this stock provides an interesting lesson for investors. 
		Let’s say you decided to buy SBUX on April 27, 2007, after it declined 30% from a recent high of $40 a share. The decline in the stock price was due to a decline in same-store sales. An ambitious management team opened too many stores too quickly, cannibalizing sales from existing stores. The stock sold down to $31 a share, which, for sake of argument, is where you bought it. Good news: In December 2007, celebrated CEO and founder Howard Schultz returned to the company, and Wall Street cheered. The stock price rallied. Then the financial crisis hit in 2008. The stock bottomed below $5 a share on Dec. 31. A $31 purchase price seemed foolish. 

		However, if you are a long-term investor and stuck with your purchase, you would be quite content. Since the bottom around Dec. 31, 2008, the stock is up 2058% versus 314% cumulatively for the SP 500 (SPX), or 34% annually compared with 14.5% for the SPX. Since April 27, 2007, when you purchased the stock at $31 a share (and before its epic decline to under $5 a share), your return is still a cumulative 548% versus 160% for the SPX.  Annualized, SBUX is up 16.6% versus the SP 500, which is up 8.2% since April 27, 2007.

		The lesson? You can work two jobs and save like Tobie. In doing so, you will set an excellent example for your children and grandchildren. OR, you can work hard and save to invest – an even better example. Our SBUX anecdote shows that even during times of severe economic stress, over time great companies generate excellent returns.

		Be patient and smart. Buy excellent companies (at a discount if possible), based on your own, unique research, and stick with them when the market gets skittish. You can make real money by being patient and even more if you are willing to commit additional capital during times of economic stress.

		Fear factor: Don't let volatility scare you; this is a good time to buy stocks

		Think long-term: 3 things to watch when you're buying stocks

		Ride the roller coaster: Dow swings are exhausting, but here's how to survive
		
	
	
		
		Another person has been arrested for allegedly licking Blue Bell Ice Cream in Louisiana
		SHREVEPORT, La. - Another apparent incident of someone licking ice cream at a store has surfaced. This time it's in Louisiana.

		Assumption Parish Sheriff's Office says a man posted a video of himself on Facebook opening a Blue Bell ice cream container, licking it, poking it with his finger and putting it back on the shelf.

		News outlets report 36-year-old Lenise Martin III was charged Saturday with property tampering and posting criminal activity for notoriety and publicity.

		Police Commander Lonny Cavalier says after being alerted of Martin's actions by management, deputies found Martin at the scene showing the sales clerk a receipt showing he bought the ice cream he licked. Deputies searched the freezer and confirmed the purchase but still decided to move forward with the charges.

		Cavalier told CNN that authorities believe Martin was inspired by a video taken earlier this month of a teen in Texas taking ice cream from a Walmart freezer, removing the top to lick it and then putting it back.

		"We believe it's a copy cat incident," Cavalier told the network.. "He did it and he did want to create some notoriety for himself by posting it on Facebook and that's exactly what he did."
		
	
	
		
		An attempted rapist fled his trial 30 years ago. Police just found him at a New York deli.
		HAWTHORNE, N.Y. — Thirty years after being convicted of attempted rape, a man believed to have fled to Guatemala is finally in jail in New York.

		Nelson Gustavo Caceres, 51, was convicted of first-degree attempted rape in 1989. But he fled while he on trial in suburban New York City, according to Westchester County Police. He was later sentenced in absentia to five to 15 years in state prison.

		In the 1990s, detectives believed he likely returned to Guatemala. Detectives from the Warrant-Fugitive Unit have had an open case for three decades on Caceres.

		During a recent review of the case, detectives came to believe Caceres may have returned recently to Mount Kisco, a village north of the city. Detectives conducted interviews there and set up surveillance at several locations.

		A person thought to be Caceres had been riding around in a red bike and frequenting a local deli, police said. Officers found a bike near the deli Friday night and arrested Caceres when he came to retrieve the vehicle. 

		“We received a good deal of cooperation in the Mount Kisco community during this investigation and are grateful for the public’s assistance,” Commissioner Thomas A. Gleason said.

		“Mr. Caceres will now serve the sentence that was handed down three decades ago and the victim in this incident will receive the justice she deserves.”

		In 1988, Mount Kisco police arrested Caceres after he dragged a woman into a wooded area and sexually assaulted her.

		The victim met him earlier in the evening and had reported that he became enraged when she would not go back to his residence, police said. 

		Caceres was indicted in 1988 and was free on bail. Now in Westchester County Jail, he also faces a charge of second-degree bail jumping, a felony.
		
	
	
		
		Indonesia sends rubbish back to Australia and says it's too contaminated to recycle
		Indonesian officials say containers of paper contaminated by electronic waste, used cans and plastic bottles
		Indonesia says it will immediately send eight containers of household rubbish back to Australia after inspectors declared the material too contaminated to be recycled.

		It is the latest in a series of announcements by south-east Asian nations that they will not be dumping grounds for overseas waste.

		Indonesian customs officials said the containers of paper from Australia were contaminated by electronic waste, used cans, plastic bottles, old bottles of engine oil and loose shoes. Some of this was deemed “B3”, an abbreviation of “bahan berbahaya dan beracun”, which refers to toxic and hazardous material.

		Opening the containers up for the press on Tuesday morning, gloved customs officials held up examples of the offending material, including used nappies and soft drink cans.

		Speaking at Tanjung Perak port in Surabaya, customs officials said eight containers holding 210.3 tonnes of waste would be returned.

		The containers arrived in Surabaya, Indonesia’s second-largest city, in mid-June after being sent from Brisbane by a shipping company.

		Customs in Surabaya said the offending material would be re-exported immediately, following coordination with the Indonesian import firm PT MDI.
		The customs office said it was obliged to protect Indonesia and its environment from imports of B3 waste and had coordinated with related government ministries, including trade and environment, as a show of how serious it was.

		Global recycling was thrown into chaos last year when China banned imports of foreign plastic waste, leaving developed nations struggling to find places to send their rubbish. Huge quantities have since been redirected to south-east Asia, but opposition to handling exported waste is growing in the region.

		In May, the Malaysian government said it would return up to 100 tonnes of Australian waste because it was too contaminated to recycle. It was part of 450 tonnes of imported plastic waste it sent back to countries across the globe. Malaysia’s environment minister, Yeo Bee Yin, said the rubbish was infested with maggots and declared Malaysia would “fight back” and “not be the dumping ground of the world.”

		The Philippines returned about 69 containers of rubbish back to Canada last month, putting an end to a diplomatic row between the two countries.

		Last week, Indonesia announced it was sending back 49 containers full of waste to France and other developed nations.

		Global concern over plastic pollution has been spurred by shocking images of waste-clogged rivers in Southeast Asia and accounts of dead sea creatures found with kilos of refuse in their stomachs. Environmental group WWF says about 300m tonnes of plastic are produced each year, with much of it ending up in landfills, waterways or oceans.

		As it repatriates unsanctioned waste, Indonesia has its own huge domestic rubbish issues to contend with. Many across the archipelago continue to burn toxic waste as a form of disposal, while each year tonnes of waste are dumped in the country’s rivers and oceans. Indonesia is the second-largest global contributor to marine plastic waste after China.

		Comment was sought from the Australian government.
		
	
	
			
		Conflict and insecurity driving spread of diseases like Ebola, WHO chief warns
		Deadly outbreak is ‘global wake-up call’, Dr Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus tells Guardian
		The head of the World Health Organization has called the world’s second worst Ebola outbreak a “global wake-up call” to the escalating risk of disease outbreaks spreading from conflict areas neglected by the international community.

		Only when there was “fear and panic” in the headlines did the international community put money into responding, said Dr Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus. The real issue was a lack of day-to-day funding for preparedness to combat serious epidemics before they become regional or international threats, he said.

		Speaking ahead of a new call for funding for the response to the Ebola outbreak, he added: “The problem is that [donors] refrain from paying until there is fear and panic. That has to change. We should not be funding by huge amounts when we panic, but should be funding to avoid panic.”

		Invoking the spectre of Spanish influenza, which killed tens of millions in the aftermath of World War I, he added that international health systems in an increasingly globalised world were only as “strong as the weakest link”.

		In an exclusive interview with the Guardian in Geneva, Tedros added that while he believed the outbreak in the Democratic Republic of the Congo could be controlled in the short term – given the right security conditions – the virus would inevitably return while political instability continued in North Kivu and Iruri, the provinces at the heart of the outbreak.
		Tedros also reiterated his resistance to declaring the current outbreak a public health emergency of international concern (PHEIC). This is despite calls from the British international development secretary, Rory Stewart, during a visit to the city of Butembo, the current epicentre of the outbreak.

		“I know we can finish this Ebola outbreak,” said Tedros, former foreign minister of Ethiopia, who became director general of the UN global health organisation in 2017. “But at the same time it can come back because all the [political and security] conditions remain the same.

		“There are some people who say we need to declare the outbreak as an [emergency] to mobilise resources. That’s really wrong. Resources should be available to prevent needing to declare a PHEIC. Preparedness is the solution, not firefighting.”
		WHO officials also disputed Stewart’s assertion in the Guardian that there was a shortage of vaccines, saying there was a sufficient supply for the current models of the epidemic.

		The outbreak is designated a “category three emergency”, the WHO’s highest level before a declaration of PHEIC. Three cases crossed the border briefly into Uganda last month.

		Tedros warned, however, that far from helping with the response to the outbreak, designating it as a PHEIC could actually complicate the response of health teams on the ground. It could see borders closed and increase economic hardship for an already highly marginalised and angry population that relies on cross-border trade and has already attacked health teams.

		Briefing a meeting of science journalists on Friday, ahead of Stewart’s intervention, Tedros reiterated his objections.

		“PHEIC only shows there is a very high risk of international spread, which is not the case based on the criteria. But if you take whether Ebola is an emergency in DRC or not, it is – it’s actually the highest level of emergency.”

		Although outbreaks of the disease in the neighbouring town of Beni and surrounding areas were largely brought under control last year, the outbreak in Butembo has proved hugely complicated, with violent attacks on health officials and treatment centres.

		The WHO has attracted criticism for its response to the DRC outbreak, not least over the issue of whether to declare it a global health emergency, a move critics say could prompt more donor countries to offer funds and other resources.

		“I’m not saying we cannot learn lessons and there was no shortfall,” Tedros told the Guardian, adding that the organisation would conduct a proper assessment of the current response.
		“But we have never had conditions like this in other places where we have had Ebola.”

		As an example of the political issues facing the response to the Ebola crisis, Tedros cited the DRC government’s decision to cancel voting in national elections in the Ebola-affected areas, as the outbreak moved to the city of Butembo last autumn.

		“When we heard about the decision to cancel the elections we said: ‘Don’t do that. It’s dangerous,’” he said, adding that he had personally appealed to ministers in the DRC as well as the African Union to reverse the decision.
		“That was a game-changer, to be honest,” he added. “An opportunity was missed and the community was angered and started attacking the responders.”

		Like other senior health officials involved in the response on the ground, Tedros blamed highly complex political and security issues for resurgences in the outbreak.

		“The political problems [in DRC] have broken the whole system – social, economic and so on. And to be honest when I talk to the community it is embarrassing for me, because they say, ‘You are only interested in Ebola because you do not want it in your own countries and you are trying to protect yourselves while mothers and children are dying here.’

		“The root cause of the problem is lack of peace, the lack of a political solution. The incidence of Ebola, malaria and cholera is the symptom.

		“It’s not about Ebola only. What concerns me is the lacking of understanding about how to make our world safe,” he said, citing the risk of an airborne pandemic.

		“We’re not investing in preparedness to detect outbreaks quickly. We are investing after the problem comes and knocks on our door when it’s too late. So how can we move on from that mindset? We have to be as strong as the weakest link and we need to invest in strengthening the systems of the weakest link.

		“We think that we are very far from the problem but in a globalised world even if it is only happening in one country it can be exported – so there is a risk, even as we speak, of spread. We should support the Congolese but also help ourselves.”
		
		
	
	
		
		Yemen: UAE confirms withdrawal from port city of Hodeidah
		Move is a significant moment in Yemen’s civil war, but officials say UAE remains in Saudi-led coalition against Houthis
		The United Arab Emirates has announced a “strategic redeployment” from the port city of Hodeidah in Yemen, as well as a more limited tactical retreat elsewhere in the country – marking a significant moment in Yemen’s four-year civil war.

		UAE officials said the move, under discussion for as long as a year, was designed to support a United Nations-led peace process that began in Stockholm last December. It was the first official UAE confirmation of a withdrawal, which has been reported in recent weeks by witnesses and foreign officials.
		The officials said the UAE would remain in the Saudi-led coalition that intervened in 2015 to try to restore the Yemeni government ousted from power by the Houthis, a rebel group backed by Iran.

		Oversight would be passed to Emirati-trained local Yemeni forces and foreign mercenaries, and UAE forces remaining in Yemen would focus on counter-terrorism efforts against al-Qaida and Islamic State rather than the battle against the Houthis. The UAE would also continue to support a secessionist movement in southern Yemen.

		Analysts have warned it is not yet clear whether local troops and Saudi coalition partners are up to the task of filling the vacuum, sparking fears that the current stalemate in much of the country could be upended.

		The UAE drawdown also weakens Saudi Arabia’s military capabilities in Yemen, adding to pressure for Riyadh to proactively pursue a political rather than military solution to the war.
		The withdrawal had been extensively discussed with Riyadh as well as the UN-recognised Yemen government based in Aden, the officials added.

		The UAE may be braced for accusations that the withdrawal is an admission of defeat, but the officials insisted the redeployment was a considered move reflecting the diplomatic progress being made by the UN in the strategically important Hodeidah.

		Hodeidah became a major focus of the war last year when the western-backed Saudi-led coalition tried to seize the port, which is the Houthis’ main supply line.

		In December the UN brokered a complex ceasefire in the city in which both the Yemeni government and Houthi forces were supposed to withdraw, leaving a new security force to take over the port and the city.

		Only parts of that withdrawal agreement have been implemented. The UAE said it was keen to see the peace process expanded towards a wider peace settlement with deadlines covering the whole country.

		The officials denied that the move would create a dangerous vacuum around Hodeidah, arguing that there were as many as 19,000 Yemeni troops in theport city area if progress towards a settlement collapsed.

		In 2018, by contrast, the UAE had argued that the military capture of Hodeidah would force the Houthis to the negotiating table.

		The international community pressed the UAE and the Saudis to wait outside the city, warning that an assault could lead to a bloodbath and disruption at the port could tip the country into full-blown famine.

		Emirati officials have also dismissed suggestions that the drawdown reflects a growing rift between Abu Dhabi and Riyadh: their military and political leaders have long differed on preferred strategy in both the bloody impasse in Yemen and dealing with the threat posed to Gulf interests from Tehran.

		UAE officials refused to go into details of precise troop movements and said some of the withdrawals were tactical, and so could be reversed. Witnesses have said a large-scale drawdown of troops and heavy weaponry is under way in Marib province and the interim capital of Aden as well as Hodeidah.

		Last week, Reuters reported it had been told by three diplomats that Abu Dhabi preferred to have its forces and equipment on hand should tension between the US and Iran escalate further after attacks on oil tankers in the Gulf and Tehran’s suspected downing of a US drone. Those tanker attacks have been ascribed to Iranian surrogates, but no final attribution has been made by the UAE. On Monday the UAE officials said the timing was not linked to those developments.
		
	
	
		
		Cities from scratch
		New cities rise from the desert, jungle and sea
		Spectacular timelapse satellite images show boom in cities built from scratch across Asia and Africa
		“We’re in the midst of new cities fever,” says Prof Sarah Moser. The head of the new cities lab at McGill University has documented more than 100 cities that have sprung up across Asia and Africa since the early 2000s for her forthcoming Atlas of New Cities.

		There’s Eko Atlantic, a “new Dubai” taking shape on reclaimed land off the coast of Nigeria, and Forest City, a “new Singapore” being built just over the Johor Strait from the original. There’s the New Silk Road city of Khorgos rising from the barren steppe that separates Kazakhstan and China, the “sustainable city” of Neom in Saudi Arabia, the Norman Foster-designed Masdar in Abu Dhabi, a few in Latin America … and even a Robotic New City in Malaysia.
		Most are in places where rapid urbanisation and population growth have overwhelmed existing cities. Sometimes masterplanned cities are a way for countries in the global south to kickstart an economic transition out of agriculture or from resource-based economies. They can also allow governments to write their country’s image afresh. “That’s a very seductive idea, especially in countries that were colonised,” says Moser.

		“It’s easy for leaders to whip up some nationalist frenzy and sell the new city as a source of national pride. The computer-generated models look beautiful too – all the old city problems are just gone – and it looks magically real. It’s compelling for people who live in overcrowded and polluted places.”

		Moser says the money to be made is staggering – measured in the trillions of dollars. “It’s extremely lucrative,” she adds. “There are real estate and tech companies circling like sharks.”
		Officials in coal-rich Inner Mongolia announced plans for a city of one1 million people in the parched desert and grasslands south of Ordos Dongsheng in 2003. Six years later the part-built development of Ordos Kangbashi became notorious around the world as a “ghost city”, as news reports highlighted the lack of people, aroundabout 30,000 at the time. Images showed a vast central public space – almost the size of Tiananmen Square in Beijing – and rows of identical empty apartment blocks.

		There are signs the city has started to fill up. A 2017 report from the state-run Xinhua news agency claimed a permanent population of 153,000, with almost 5,000 active businesses. Wade Shepard, author of The Ghost Cities of China, believes that by the city’s expected completion date of 2023 it should have met its revised population target of 300,000 people. “It regularly takes western cities five to 10 years to build civil engineering projects such as new subway lines,” he points out. “Ordos Kangbashi probably should have impressed the world with its rapid pace of development.”
		The former prime minister of Malaysia Mahathir Mohamad announced plans in the late 1980s to shift the nation’s administrative capital from congested, overcrowded Kuala Lumpur to a new city built on former oil and rubber plantations 25 miles (40km) to the south. Putrajaya would join the ranks of purpose-built capitals around the world: from Canberra in Australia to Islamabad in Pakistan, Abuja in Nigeria to Washington DC in the US.

		Construction began in the mid-1990s. Putrajaya was billed as an “intelligent garden city”: more than a third of the land is reserved for green spaces, with 200 hectares (494 acres) of wetlands and a 400-hectare manmade lake – as well as the world’s largest roundabout.

		Although the Asian financial crisis of 1997 put a temporary halt on development, the city is now fully functioning: almost all government departments have moved there, along with an estimated population of 88,000. It has been praised for its innovative architecture, community and environmental focus; a “manicured Malaysia” of office blocks, hotels and pretty parks.
		The city of New Cairo – in the desert 20 miles to the east of its namesake – was conceived in the late 1990s and established by presidential decree in 2000. Not to be confused with the as-yet-unnamed new administrative capital proposed by president Abdel-Fattah El-Sisi in 2014 (another 20 miles east and dubbed the “new New Cairo”), the original New Cairo was meant to attract a population of 5 million. A few hundred-thousand currently call it home.
		Where Ordos and New Cairo rose from the desert and Putrajaya from the jungle, the new city of Songdo was built on land reclaimed from the Yellow Sea. Songdo International Business District was envisioned as a sustainable, low-carbon, hi-tech “ubiquitous city” – with all the advantages of Seoul, 30 miles to the north, but without the congestion and air pollution.

		All major buildings are constructed to LEED green standards; a network of underground tubes sucks all household and office waste to processing facilities, eliminating the need for rubbish trucks; residents can remotely control lighting and air conditioning, while street sensors monitor traffic flow. Many of those futuristic features, though, are starting to look a little commonplace.

		Master-planned by New York architecture firm Kohn Pedersen Fox, Songdo is the world’s most expensive private real estate development. As of last year, the population was estimated at just over 100,000 people – around a third of its target. The 2015 completion date has been pushed back to 2022.
		
	
</documents>