<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<documents>
  
    
Deutsche Bank Scales Back Ambitions, Announcing Job Cuts and Reorganization
FRANKFURT — Deutsche Bank embarked Sunday on what may be its last chance to reverse a decade of decline, announcing that it would cut a fifth of its work force and slash operations in New York and London.

The reorganization and cost-cutting plan is reminiscent of the bloodletting that followed the financial crisis in 2008. Yet it comes at a time of relative prosperity, the cumulative effect of years of scandal and management missteps. The bank that once symbolized German economic prowess is effectively abandoning any hope of playing in the same league as Goldman Sachs or JPMorgan Chase, and struggling simply to remain relevant.

Ever since it planted its flag on Wall Street by acquiring Bankers Trust in 1999, Deutsche Bank has been trying to prove that global finance was not the exclusive territory of the American megabanks. But it did so by taking chances, including issuing hundreds of billions of dollars in high-risk derivatives and lending money to Donald J. Trump’s organization when other banks wouldn’t.

The financial crisis that began in 2008 exposed a history of sometimes criminal wrongdoing, including rigging interest rates, laundering money and violating United States sanctions against countries like Iran. The scandals, which persisted long past the crisis, eroded Deutsche Bank’s reputation and led to billions of dollars in fines. Regulators anxious to avoid any more financial crises forced Deutsche Bank and other lenders to take fewer risks.
Now the bank, based in Frankfurt, is refocusing on less glamorous, less hazardous businesses like helping German exporters manage financial transactions abroad. About 18,000 people will lose their jobs as Deutsche Bank closes or shrinks operations that sell stocks and bonds. One-third of the management board will leave the bank as part of the overhaul, and more than $300 billion in risky assets will be quarantined in a separate unit.

The question in the months ahead will be whether the turnaround effort by Christian Sewing, Deutsche Bank’s 49-year-old chief executive, comes too late. Other European banks like UBS of Switzerland and Barclays in Britain pared back their ambitions after the 2008 financial crisis, but Deutsche Bank clung to investment banking even as it continued to generate billions of euros in losses.

“We are returning to our roots and to what once made us one of the leading banks in the world,” Mr. Sewing said in a statement on Sunday.
The plan is also a big gamble, carrying significant immediate costs with no guarantee they will revive the bank. Severance payments and other expenses will total 7.4 billion euros, or $8.3 billion, through 2022, Deutsche Bank said. At the same time, revenue is certain to fall as the bank shrinks, creating the risk of a vicious circle of declining income and profits.

On Monday morning, Deutsche Bank shares opened higher in European trading, gaining about 4 percent before settling about 1.5 percent higher.
  
    
    
At Banks and Fund Firms, Access Is Too Often Denied, Blind and Deaf Investors Say
Albert Rizzi gave up on trying to manage his nest egg because as a blind person, he encountered digital barriers constantly. Many of the websites, mobile apps, PDFs and software programs he needed were not accessible. Sometimes, they just didn’t work.

So Mr. Rizzi, 55, the founder of My Blind Spot, an accessibility advocacy group in New York, filed a federal lawsuit in April 2018 against Morgan Stanley, the firm he uses to manage his personal retirement accounts.

Mr. Rizzi’s suit accused the bank of violating the Americans With Disabilities Act by “denying access to its websites to individuals with disabilities who are visually impaired” and who require screen-reader software to access digital content. Mr. Rizzi also cited the bank for not having an accessibility website or hotline. The case, which sought about $9 million in damages, was settled last summer, his lawyer, Lambros Lambrou, said.
In a separate case, Wells Fargo in 2011 settled an investigation by the Justice Department alleging A.D.A. violations because the bank failed to accept what is known as video relay services, or video phone calls, from deaf customers. The settlement required the bank to pay $16 million to some account holders and remedy a variety of accessibility problems.
Despite the passage of the A.D.A., lawsuits and heightened awareness of the needs of people with disabilities, obstacles to investing and money management persist. The fix often requires reverse-engineering software and procedures, which can be costly and time consuming. There are signs that some financial services companies are rethinking their approach to accessibility, but customers remain concerned.

“I am still struggling to read the statements from my brokerage account, and am often left to rely on sighted assistance, which can expose me to identity theft or worse,” Mr. Rizzi said. Recently, his personal financial information was compromised. “There is significant room for improvement across the board, and I have yet to, personally or professionally, find that one institution that has it right.”

By many accounts, the pool of blind and deaf retirement investors is small — not just because of accessibility problems but also because those people face low wages, unemployment, underemployment and a lack of financial literacy. The average annual earned income for an American with a disability is $26,487 — 38 percent less than for someone without a disability, according to a 2018 report by the American Institutes for Research. The Labor Department reports that only about 19 percent of people with a disability are employed, compared with nearly 66 percent of people without a disability.
The low work force participation rate is “due to the high number of people who see a better income from entitlements or the many who have not seen success in landing a job and more or less have given up trying,” said Chris Soukup, chief executive of Communication Service for the Deaf. This makes it harder for them to save for retirement through a job.

Retirement planning, however, is still relevant for people with disabilities, and some financial advisers have tailored their practice to help people even if they have few assets.

A Son’s Memoir of His Father’s Radical Beliefs, Pursuit by the F.B.I. and Ardent Love for America
Lee Kramer, the founder of Kramer Wealth Managers, is deaf and says the mission of his firm is to “bridge the gap between the financial world and the deaf community by providing comprehensive wealth management services accessible in A.S.L.”

Mr. Kramer’s staff is fluent in American Sign Language and often use videophones. Mr. Kramer said the firm’s clientele included 85 percent deaf and 15 percent hearing customers, and unlike many firms, his does not require a minimum investment from any of them. “We feel we have a duty of service to the deaf community,” he said.

Among Kramer’s clients are the Deaf-Hearing Communication Center in Swarthmore, Pa., and its 13 full-time employees.

“We don’t have to go through somebody to have a conversation about what we need,” said Neil McDevitt, the executive director of the nonprofit center, which provides sign language interpreting and real-time captioning services. “So if I want to talk to Mr. Kramer, I can call him on the videophone and we can have a conversation directly.”

Even though certified interpreters are bound by confidentiality, some people may feel uncomfortable sharing financial information through a third party, and not every interpreter is equally versed in financial terminology.

Mr. McDevitt, whose father was a financial planner, recalled many conversations at his family’s dinner table about saving for the future. Unfortunately, he said, many deaf children, especially those with hearing parents, miss out on these vital talks. A Gallaudet University survey found that the majority of deaf children are born to hearing parents and that fewer than a quarter of families use sign language regularly at home.

“Financial literacy has always been a challenge because for a very, very long time the hearing community didn’t quite believe that we could be or should be financially independent,” Mr. McDevitt said.
Kramer Wealth Managers has taken steps to improve this by maintaining a sign language library on a variety of topics, including annuities, bear and bull markets and wills, and a vlog with market commentary in sign language.

Mr. Kramer said he uses his knowledge of ABLE plans (tax-advantaged saving plans for people with disabilities that do not affect eligibility for public benefits), Social Security Disability Income and vocational rehabilitation support to develop financial plans for deaf clients. The firm also maintains a network of A.S.L.-fluent professionals including lawyers, accountants, mortgage brokers and real estate agents for client referrals.

Gena Harper, a senior vice president for Morgan Stanley in Oakland, Calif., begins her day at 5:30 a.m. commuting with Yulie, her seeing-eye dog. As both a financial adviser and an investor who is blind, Ms. Harper said she relied on VoiceOver on her iPhone; the screen-reader program known as Job Access With Speech, which she uses to navigate her computer and to read PDFs, Excel and Word documents; and a Braille embosser and display.

Still, “technology is the hugest impediment,” she said, because many of Morgan Stanley’s internal systems and apps remain “very inaccessible.” Getting her work done requires a lot of human intervention by a technology team devoted to helping her and other colleagues who are blind.

Despite the hurdles, “I truly find a way,” she said of working with customers who have disabilities. Her practice does not require a minimum investment from any clients, which is not true of all Morgan Stanley financial advisers. “So even if you don’t have any money or you have very little money, we will give you guidance.”

Ms. Harper said that in the last year, Morgan Stanley had made “a huge commitment with money, resources and people to make their systems accessible” and that her conversations with senior management led to the creation of the tech team.

Access at big institutions

Advocates for people with disabilities remain concerned about the blind and deaf client experience with big mutual fund companies like Vanguard and Fidelity.
“Most, if not all, of customer service help desk personnel have not been trained in inclusion, digital equity or what tools the disability community uses to navigate digital platforms, and we have a dead end at the first point of entry,” Mr. Rizzi of My Blind Spot said.

Amber DeRosa, the manager of Vanguard’s accessibility office, said Vanguard’s phone associates were trained to answer questions a blind client might ask and how to handle a deaf customer’s video call. They can also connect the customer with Vanguard’s accessibility team. Vanguard’s first accessibility website went live at the end of May.

“We’re making sure that anything new that we develop going forward has accessibility built in from the beginning,” she said. Vanguard does not provide Braille statements to customers. But Ms. DeRosa said the company was making improvements to its websites, mobile apps and PDF account statements so that they were more compatible with screen readers.

Some blind Vanguard investors reported not being able to make an independent stock trade online and having to call customer service to complete the transaction, which typically carries a higher transaction fee. Ms. DeRosa said the company “would always waive any type of fees” resulting from accessibility problems.

Fidelity has about 200 retail locations nationwide, which are equipped with Video Relay Interpretation services “so that an American Sign Language interpreter can be summoned within a minute to assist,” said Fidelity’s customer accessibility lead, Hale Pulsifer. An interpreter can also be provided on site on request, he added.

Mr. Kramer said Fidelity was one of the last companies to accept video relay calls and that there were problems with 401(k) account call centers. A few months ago, one of his clients placed a video call and Fidelity refused to take it, he said. “They required him to go to a physical location to verify his identity before they would take his instructions over the phone.”

Mr. Pulsifer said Fidelity accepted video calls and had “the same identity verification process for every caller.” He added that Fidelity tried to ensure that its websites and apps were “optimized” for screen-only use and keyboard-only use, and that any videos contained closed captioning. Fidelity also provides large print, Braille and audio statements and tests its websites with the latest browsers and screen readers.
Advocates say that the 61 million people living with disabilities in the United States constitute a significant market force that has largely been overlooked. It’s also likely to expand.

Mr. Rizzi of My Blind Spot said he wanted companies to “acknowledge that we are all ‘temporarily able’ and will age into the disability community through no choice of our own.”
  
    
    
How to Manage Your Credit Card Bills, Which Experts Say Are Late More Often
Even with a strong economy, a growing number of people are having trouble paying their credit card bills.

Late credit card payments, while still low, have been ticking upward for the past two years, the Federal Reserve Bank of New York reported in May. Card delinquencies have been rising for borrowers under 30, in particular, but also for borrowers in their 60s, the New York Fed said.

Experian, a major credit bureau, said the average card balance as of May was $6,553, up slightly from the average balance of $6,506 in the second quarter of 2018.

Consumer advocates say they are concerned that more people will find themselves in trouble, should the economy slow. “I’m very worried about it,” said Lauren Saunders, a lawyer with the National Consumer Law Center, which specializes in working with lower-income people.
There are steps, however, that consumers can take if they are having difficulty making payments. They can start by contacting their card companies to see if they can obtain a temporary interest rate reduction or a lower minimum payment. “I would recommend that people first reach out directly to creditors,” Ms. Saunders said. “The earlier you do, the more likely they are to work with you.”

Another option is to seek help from a nonprofit credit counseling agency. Participants can often get a free or low-cost budget review to help them identify areas where they may be able to cut spending and reduce their debt.

Consumers with more serious debt problems, however, may need a more structured approach, said Phil Heinemann, executive director of Debt Management Credit Counseling, a nonprofit organization in Lighthouse Point, Fla.

Those borrowers may be eligible for a debt management plan in which the counseling agency negotiates an interest-rate cut with the card companies. In exchange, borrowers agree to pay off the debt by making fixed monthly payments over three to five years.

If the proposed payment plan is approved, the agencies charge a monthly fee that varies based on the size of the monthly payment, but is typically capped by state law. The overall amount paid still represents a significant savings, Mr. Heinemann said, because of the lower interest rate on the debt, as well as the elimination of late fees and other penalties. (A handful of agencies, along with a few big creditors, are testing a new version of these programs that would cut the debt owed in half to make the programs more accessible for people trying to avoid bankruptcy.)
Mr. Heinemann said his typical client has about $10,000 in card debt, but he has seen much higher balances. It’s important, he said, that the borrowers are able to afford the agreed-upon monthly payment. If they miss two consecutive payments, he said, creditors typically drop them from the program.

Kristen Holt, chief executive of GreenPath Financial Wellness, a nonprofit debt counselor in Farmington Hills, Mich., that provides services nationally, said the agency had seen demand for debt management services rise this year. Often, she said, clients are referred to GreenPath by their creditors. GreenPath’s typical client has five different creditors, and an average debt of $20,000. The agency charges a one-time fee of up to $50 to set up a plan and monthly fees of up to $75.

Becky Willard, 73, said she had worked with GreenPath to pay off about $40,000 in credit card debt, mostly from medical bills after she learned she had breast cancer in 2002.

Ms. Willard, who had worked mainly part time, said she found herself struggling financially six years ago, after her partner died. “I had never been the primary earner,” she said. She sold her home in Orlando, Fla., and moved into a small condominium in Bradenton, about 100 miles away.

But, Ms. Willard said, her card debt seemed insurmountable. She learned online about GreenPath, and found its approach appealing. “They’d get the interest rates down,” Ms. Willard said, “so there’s light at the end of the tunnel.”

Ms. Willard found a full-time job caring for Alzheimer’s patients. Her earnings let her make twice-monthly payments of $475 toward her card debt. (Two of her major creditors, she said, reduced the rates on their cards to nearly zero percent.) “I worked my tail off,” she said.

She has just finished paying off the debt. Although it took her almost five years, she said, she is healthy and feels immense relief. “I am proud of myself,” she said.
GreenPath said Ms. Willard paid about $5,500 in interest and fees under her debt plan. If she had paid off the debt on her own, without the lower rates available under the management plan, she would have had to make payments for several years longer and paid about $30,000 in interest, the agency said.

Here are some questions and answers about credit card debt:

Will a debt management plan hurt my credit score?

A client’s credit score may fall initially. Most debt management plans require borrowers to close the card accounts enrolled in the plan, which may cause scores to drop, Ms. Holt said. But as participants make payments, scores typically stabilize and then begin to rebound.

How can I find a reputable credit counseling agency?

A good place to start is the list of nonprofit agencies that are certified by the Justice Department to provide mandatory counseling for people seeking personal bankruptcy protection. Such agencies often provide broader services, including debt management plans.

Nonprofit debt counseling agencies are different from debt “settlement” or relief agencies, which are considered riskier. Often, debt settlement agencies advise clients to stop paying their credit card bills and instead use the funds to build up a lump sum that can be used in negotiating a settlement. Some creditors, however, won’t negotiate with debt settlement firms, and borrowers may end up worse off, according to the Federal Trade Commission.

Chris Peterson, director of financial services with the Consumer Federation of America, said consumers should ask detailed questions to be sure they are working with a legitimate counseling agency. They should confirm that the agency is licensed in their state, he said. They should also ask what fees will be charged and get a price quote in writing for the agency’s services.

What if I am getting calls from debt collectors?

The Fair Debt Collection Practices Act sets limits on what collectors can do. For instance, they can’t contact you before 8 a.m. or after 9 p.m.

The Consumer Financial Protection Bureau has proposed changes to the law to limit the number of calls a collector can make per week, but also to allow collectors to contact delinquent borrowers by text and email.

Some consumer advocates worry the changes may lead to harassment of borrowers. The public can comment on the proposed changes until Aug. 19.
  
    
    
    	Global Recession Risks Are Up, and Central Banks Aren’t Ready
    Central bankers have a favorite mantra: Patch the roof while the sun is shining.

But 10 years after the Federal Reserve worked alongside the European Central Bank and the Bank of Japan to bring the global economy back from the brink, their ability to prevent the next downturn is limited.

Whether the world’s central banks are prepared to combat another slump is becoming less of a hypothetical question as the global economy shows signs of strain. The chances that the United States will enter a recession by next year have grown as manufacturing weakens and trade uncertainty drags on. In Germany, the unemployment rate has ticked higher, and industrial production is slowing. In Japan, weak factory production and waning exports heighten vulnerability.
A recession is far from inevitable — particularly one as deep and painful as the last. But the capacity for the type of decisive response that prevented an even worse outcome in 2008 has been hindered. Back then, central banks cut rates, bought up bonds, extended government backing to financial products, lent money to banks and in some cases coordinated with government authorities to make sure their rescue packages didn’t work at cross-purposes. It was an unprecedented period of experimentation, one that saved economies careening toward collapse.
But today, interest rates remain below zero in Japan and Europe. They are low by historical standards in the United States, leaving less room to cut in a downturn. Most central banks still hold huge amounts of the bonds and other securities they bought to prop up their economies the last time, which could make another buying binge more difficult and dampen its effects.Monetary policy is also running low on credibility. Major central banks have failed to hit their 2 percent inflation targets during this expansion, heightening the risk that prices will slip dangerously low come the next downturn. And while promises of lower-for-longer interest rates have been a major source of stimulus in recent years, those pledges might lose some of their punch in a world where investors already expect permanently low rates.

Those constraints are especially worrying at a time when governments show little appetite for working together to offset a broad-based global slowdown. The United States and Europe are in the midst of a trade dispute that followed President Trump’s decision to impose tariffs on steel and aluminum and his threat to levy taxes on German and other European cars. Mr. Trump has criticized the European Central Bank for taking steps to protect the eurozone economy, accusing it of trying to weaken the euro and put America at a disadvantage.Mr. Trump suggested last week that central banks were in something of an arms race, saying on Twitter that China and Europe were manipulating their currencies to gain an edge over the United States and that the Fed should start doing the same.

“We should MATCH, or continue being the dummies who sit back and politely watch as other countries continue to play their games — as they have for many years!” he wrote.Central bank officials insist that they are prepared to act aggressively if another recession flares. The E.C.B. stands prepared to stimulate the eurozone, and the Fed is signaling that it could soon cut interest rates to try to get ahead of mounting risks in the United States.

But economists across the globe say central banks can no longer be sole saviors the next time a downturn hits. That reality is colliding with political constraints in the United States and Europe, where lawmakers may prove unable — or unwilling — to quickly roll out expensive stimulus packages.

“Fiscal policy has a much more active role to play, and it is not yet equipped to do so,” Olivier Blanchard, a former International Monetary Fund chief economist, said last month at a central banking forum in Sintra, Portugal, specifically referring to Europe.

When it comes to monetary policy, “surely there is not enough room to respond to even a run-of-the-mill recession,” he said.

Christine Lagarde, who has been nominated to succeed Mario Draghi as head of the European Central Bank and currently heads the International Monetary Fund, has warned that central banks are likely to be the main line of defense given fiscal constraints.

“High public debt and low interest rates have left many countries with limited policy room for maneuver,” Ms. Lagarde said in a June blog post. She added that in a downturn, nations would need to use their economic tools together, with “decisive monetary easing and fiscal stimulus wherever possible.”
Global economic growth has crept back after a deep recession, and as recently as early 2018 a coordinated international expansion was underway. But progress has shown cracks in recent months, with trade flows slumping and manufacturing indexes pulling back from Asia to Europe.

The Morgan Stanley economist Chetan Ahya estimates that if Mr. Trump’s trade war with China isn’t resolved and the administration follows through with its threats to increase tariffs, growth could fall enough that “we could wind up in a global recession in about three quarters.” Risks seem to have abated slightly after the recent Group of 20 meeting, where Mr. Trump suspended a tariff escalation and restarted trade talks with China.

But uncertainties persist. Those talks could crumble again, leading to additional import taxes. And beyond America’s trade wars, the threat of a disorderly British withdrawal from the European Union and a continuing slowdown in China pose further risks to international activity.

Those factors prompted Mr. Draghi to strongly signal in June that the central bank was planning to revive stimulus measures it had used during the eurozone debt crisis.

While Mr. Draghi insisted the bank still had “considerable headroom” to buy bonds as a way of pumping money into the economy, some analysts think he acted pre-emptively precisely because he knows the central bank’s capacity is finite. Better to use the bank’s limited resources now when they can still do some good.

In the United States, the Fed is also considering acting sooner rather than later as it tries to judge whether a rate cut is warranted. Emerging research suggests that moving quickly and decisively might be the central bank’s best defense.

While the Fed is in comparatively good shape because it has gotten rates off rock bottom — they’re at 2.25 to 2.5 percent — that leaves it just half as much room to cut borrowing costs as policymakers had back in 2007. In fact, the Fed’s chair, Jerome H. Powell, has started a yearlong review of just what its options are.
“Having low interest rates really challenges the existing tool kits of central banks,” Mr. Powell said during remarks in New York last month.

Fed officials say they are prepared to revive large-scale bond-buying programs to stoke economic activity when the next downturn comes. The central bank is also contemplating new policy approaches that would leave rates lower for a longer period after a downturn. Recent research suggests such policies would have had benefits — though in some cases small ones — if applied after the 2008 recession.

Japan offers a cautionary example that mere willingness to act doesn’t guarantee success. Haruhiko Kuroda, head of the Bank of Japan, has pulled out all stops to reignite the country’s economy, cutting rates into negative territory and buying government debt and stocks in a bid to bolster markets and stoke confidence. The government has helped, spending readily to stimulate demand.

Despite all of that effort, inflation remains mired below Japan’s target, which is bad news since it increases the risk of outright deflation should growth weaken.

It is now unclear how much room Mr. Kuroda has for action should a deep downturn come, according to Makoto Hara, the author of a recent book on Japan’s central bank.

“Those taboo policies have become normal,” he said. “They’ve continued them until they became numb to them.”

Central banks in major economies are in their diminished positions largely because sustainable growth, inflation and interest rates have all fallen, trends that are attributable to long-running structural forces in the economy including aging populations and weakening productivity.
In the United States, the nonpartisan Congressional Budget Office sees gross domestic product increases leveling off near 2 percent. The International Monetary Fund estimates that output could drift lower in emerging markets and advanced economies alike.

That has coincided with fiscal restraint across the globe, as governments try to rein in spending and avoid further bloating debt levels.

American politicians restrained government spending after the 2008 recession, even when unemployment remained high and growth was tepid. Recent tax cuts and spending increases, ushered in by Republican lawmakers, have increased the federal debt, but there does not appear to be a broader embrace of deficit spending underway, particularly as the 2020 presidential election approaches.

America’s budget deficit is on track to surpass $1 trillion this year, and some lawmakers are already looking for ways to cut, not add to, federal spending.

Central bank leaders have increasingly warned that their firepower will be limited without help from fiscal authorities.

“Monetary policy will continue to do its job no matter what happens to fiscal capacity,” Mr. Draghi said, just a few days after European leaders largely failed to set up a mechanism to jointly provide stimulus when needed. But aid from governments “would do the same job faster and with less side effects.”

Mr. Powell echoed that sentiment last month. “It’s not good to have monetary policy be the main game in town, let alone the only game in town,” he said.
	
  
    
    Kohl’s Is Betting on Amazon Returns to Drive Sales
    It says volumes about the challenges facing brick-and-mortar stores that the “single biggest initiative” out of Kohl’s this year, according to the national retailer’s chief executive, is that it will now accept and process unwanted orders from Amazon.

Kohl’s said on Monday that it was now accepting Amazon returns at its more than 1,100 stores after running a pilot program in 100 locations. The retailer, which will pack, label and ship the returns for free, expects the program to benefit millions of shoppers along with bringing more people into their stores, Michelle Gass, the company’s chief executive, said in a statement.

The retailer, based in Menomonee Falls, Wis., tested the program, which has been closely watched by the industry and has elevated Ms. Gass’s profile, for about 18 months. It timed its national rollout to the back-to-school shopping season.“It’s an interesting marriage because what Kohl’s needs is store traffic, and what Amazon needs is to make customers happier with a place to return their items,” said Oliver Chen, a retail analyst at Cowen. “The dream is that it’s a fair but attractive split where that shopper will come in and purchase other items.”
Subscribe to With Interest
Catch up and prep for the week ahead with this newsletter of the most important business insights, delivered Sundays.

SIGN UP
National chains have been devising a plethora of ways to accommodate new digital shopping habits, particularly of younger consumers, beyond simply managing their own online pickups and returns at stores. Nordstrom recently established an urban chain of stores, called Nordstrom Local, that do not carry any merchandise. The locations, which are about the size of a Lululemon or Dunkin’ Donuts, are mainly hubs for online pickups and returns, and have attracted a younger crowd compared with Nordstrom’s average shoppers.

Retailers are also looking to accelerate the delivery of items to consumers. Walmart, in its own competition with Amazon, shared plans in May to expand next-day delivery to 75 percent of the United States this year. Kohl’s is unique in embracing Amazon, the nation’s e-commerce behemoth. The chain, which has tested its Amazon return strategy in Chicago, Los Angeles and Milwaukee, has also been increasing the number of its stores that carry Amazon products like smart home devices.

While Kohl’s has shared little about how the partnership works, it said on a May earnings call that it expected its expenses to increase because of store staffing and logistics for the returns program.

Ms. Gass, who took the reins at Kohl’s just over a year ago, emphasized on the call that working with Amazon was a “long-term bet” and beneficial for both companies. “What’s really key and what our data would suggest is that we’re also bringing in a new customer and we’re bringing in a younger customer,” she said. “That is significant.”

The company, best known for selling apparel and accessories to families, reported revenue of $20.2 billion last year and net profit of $801 million. It doesn’t separate its store sales from its internet sales. Most locations are in strip malls or free standing.

Kohl’s has also been trying to increase store traffic by selling and leasing space to neighbors like Planet Fitness and the grocery chain Aldi, Mr. Chen said.

“You sort of see this revolution happening on the basis of footfall,” he said. “Kohl’s wants to be working from a position of strength where people will still need groceries and still work out and definitely still shop at Amazon.”

He added, “They’re using their assets to their advantage.”

  
    
    Turkey is the poster child for what happens when politicians mess with central banks
    New York (CNN Business)Central banks aren't perfect, but they work best when politicians aren't calling the shots. That pillar of monetary policy is now under siege.

President Donald Trump continued over the weekend to try to bully his hand-picked central bank chief into slashing interest rates. Trump is begging the Federal Reserve to juice the economy, seemingly contradicting his own claim that the American economy is the "BEST IT HAS EVER BEEN!" (It's not.)
Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan took his dislike for his country's monetary policy to the next level over the weekend, firing his central bank chief. No official reason was given for the ouster of Murat Cetinkaya, but Erdogan was frustrated by Turkey's high interest rates, which he blamed as the cause for the nation's high inflation. (It isn't.)
The dramatic firing sent the Turkish lira sinking 2% against the US dollar and deepened doubts about the independence of the country's central bank.
"Under President Erdogan, the credibility of monetary policy has been severely undermined," said Jason Tuvey, senior emerging market economist at Capital Economics.
Central banks under assault
Turkey is the poster child for what can happen when political leaders meddle with central banks. Years of pressure from Erdogan limited the central bank's willingness to cool off the red-hot economy by raising rates. That led to higher inflation that the central bank only belatedly tried to tackle.
"Turkey is the classic case of how efforts by politicians to take control of monetary policy have undermined the inflation-fighting credibility of central banks," said Tuvey. Central banks in most modern economies are designed to be insulated from the short-term whims of politicians. The goal is to give central bankers the freedom to snuff out inflation — even if that hurts political leaders at the ballot box.
In Turkey, the annual inflation rate spiked to 25% last year as the central bank, under pressure from Erdogan, failed to aggressively raise interest rates. The Turkish lira crashed to record lows and the stock market plunged.
'Economic ignorance'
Turkey's new central bank chief, Murat Uysal, may launch a "large cut" of several percentage points at the next meeting, on July 25, "to appease" Erdogan, according to a research report published by Piotr Matys, Rabobank's emerging markets foreign exchange strategist.
Matys warned that such a move would be a "major policy mistake" given the lira's slide and suggested the reshuffling at Turkey's central bank "could mark the end of its independence."
Win Thin, global head of currency strategy at Brown Brothers Harriman, said the only "crime" of Turkey's central bank governor was failing to cut rates.
"We all know who really controls monetary policy now," Thin wrote in a note to clients.
But Erdogan's views are unorthodox. The Turkish president has called himself the "enemy of interest rates," which he sees as the cause of inflation.
"That's just economic ignorance," said Peter Boockvar, chief investment officer at Bleakley Advisory Group.
In reality, central banks use interest rate hikes as a way to cool off overheating economies to prevent inflation from spiraling out of control.
Is Powell feeling the heat?
Trump's own economic views have been questioned. He's put severe pressure on Fed chief Jerome Powell to slash interest rates even though the stock market is at all-time highs, credit conditions are strong and the jobs market looks healthy.
"Our most difficult problem is not our competitors, it is the Federal Reserve," Trump tweeted on Friday, adding that the US central bank "doesn't have a clue."
Boockvar said there is no way to square Trump's call for rate cuts with his argument that the American economy is the best it's ever been. And yet the Fed is widely expected to cut rates later this month.
For its part, the Fed has sought to ease fears that it is acting at the behest of Trump.
"The Fed is insulated from short-term political pressures," Powell said in a speech late last month.
Powell noted that Congress purposely designed the Fed to be independent "because it had seen the damage that often arises when policy bends to short-term political interests."
In a press conference last month, Powell also dismissed Trump's argument that he can be demoted. "I think the law is clear that I have a four-year term, and I fully intend to serve it," Powell told reporters. Still, some have questioned whether the Fed really should be independent.
"Why should monetary policy, this very powerful tool to control the economy, not be subject to the democracy just like every other instrument of government?" Art Laffer, co-author of "Trumponomics: Inside the America First Plan to Revive Our Economy," told CNBC on Monday.
Boockvar suggested that the Fed may already be feeling the heat.
"As much as the Fed and Jay Powell tell us they do what they think is right, they are still human beings and are subject to pressure," Boockvar said. "He's in a very tough situation when you have the president breathing down your neck."
Perhaps a new era is beginning, one where politicians have greater say over central bank policy. But it's hard to see how monetary policy based on political calendars, instead of economic fundamentals, will end well.
  
    
    New York (CNN Business) Steve Jobs was a wizard who "cast spells on people" to help keep Apple afloat during the company's darkest days, according to longtime rival Bill Gates.

The Microsoft (MSFT) founder discussed his and Jobs' leadership styles with CNN's Fareed Zakaria Sunday. Both men are known for being tough leaders who foster an intense workplace culture.
Gates said people often emulate the negative elements of the Apple (AAPL) founder's personality, but Jobs was also a unique leader who took Apple from near-death to its pedestal as the most valuable company in the world (before Microsoft usurped that crown this year). Apple was on the verge of bankruptcy when Jobs rejoined the company in the late 1990s; it is now worth just shy of $1 trillion.
Jobs was "a good example of 'don't do this at home,'" Gates said. But nonetheless, he added, "I have yet to meet any person who in terms of picking talent, hyper-motivating that talent and having a sense of design, of 'this is good, this is not good.' So he brought some incredibly positive things along with that toughness."
Gates said Jobs had a way of turning around failures by "casting spells" both on his own staff and outside observers. Gates dropped a Harry Potter reference when he called himself a "minor wizard" for being able to see through Jobs' "spells."
One prominent example: After Jobs' co-founded Apple, he built a company called NeXT that made an expensive flop of a computer. Still, he managed to bring widespread attention to NeXT and sold the company to Apple in 1996.
"It was complete nonsense and yet he mesmerized those people," Gates said. "Steve is really a singular case where the company was on a path to die and it goes and becomes the most valuable company in the world with some products that are really quite amazing. There aren't going to be many stories like that."
Jobs died in 2011, months after he resigned from Apple because of complications from pancreatic cancer. Jony Ive, the legendary designer who worked alongside Jobs to develop many of the company's flagship products, announced last month he plans to leave the company.
As for the culture within Microsoft, Gates acknowledged that the intensity did occasionally go "too far," especially in the company's early years.
"We had, to some degree, a self-selected set of people who were mostly males, I'll admit, and yes, we were pretty tough on each other," Gates said. "We counted on each other to work very long hours and I always wanted to set the best example of that. I think that intensity, even though a little bit it went too far, was great for my 20s, 30s, 40s."
Now running the Gates Foundation, Gates said he's "not pushing quite as insanely," but that focus has continued to serve him.
"I'm still clear about, 'Hey that toilet design is too expensive, it's a dead end, we're not going to put more money into that.' That works for being the co-head of the foundation," he said.
  
    
    New York (CNN Business) Apple has suddenly become one of the most polarizing stocks on Wall Street. Shares of Apple fell more than 2% Monday after an analyst at Rosenblatt Securities downgraded the iPhone maker's stock to a "sell."

Three analysts now rate Apple's shares a "sell," according to data from Refinitiv. Another 18 analysts have Apple (AAPL) rated a "hold" — which many on Wall Street view as essentially the same thing as a sell. And 23 analysts think Apple is a "buy."
Right now, the Apple bulls still appear to have the upper hand. The stock is up more than 25% this year, making it one of the best performers in the Dow so far in 2019. But Jun Zhang, the Rosenblatt analyst who downgraded Apple on Monday, paints a pretty bleak picture for Apple for the rest of the year.
"We believe new iPhone sales will be disappointing, iPad sales growth will slow in the second half of 2019 [and] other product sales growth, such as the HomePod, AirPod and iWatch, may not be meaningful to support total revenue growth," Zhang wrote in a report Monday.
Zhang said the iPhone XS may wind up being "one of the worst selling iPhone models in the history of Apple."
And even though service sales growth has been strong for several quarters thanks to Apple Music and Apple News, he believes that growth will start to slow.
It's notable that Zhang — whose official title at Rosenblatt is China analyst covering tech, media and telecom — did not cite any specific concerns about Apple sales in China. Apple's warning on that market stunned investors earlier this year. The bull case for Apple
Another analyst who looked at China demand came away with a far more bullish outlook for Apple.
Dan Ives, an analyst at Wedbush, said in a report Sunday that he remains positive on global iPhone demand, adding that thanks to some recent price cuts in China, there seems to be a "slight uptick" in production from Apple suppliers.
He added that there haven't been any "cracks in the armor" for Apple in China, despite worries about China retaliating against US tech firms in light of the US ban on equipment from Chinese tech and telecom giant Huawei.
Ives estimates that between 60 million and 70 million Chinese consumers could be in need of upgrading to a newer iPhone over the next 12 to 18 months.
And even Zhang, the Rosenblatt analyst, conceded there are several reasons why investors shouldn't necessarily bet against Apple.
Zhang pointed out in his report that Apple's most recent earnings guidance was "stable," the company has plenty of cash, and it has a "meaningful" stock buyback program in place that helps boost earnings per share by reducing the share count. 
  
    
    British Airways faces $230 million fine. It would be a record under Europe's tough data privacy law
    London (CNN Business)British Airways faces a record $230 million fine after a website failure compromised the personal details of roughly 500,000 customers.

It would be the largest penalty yet under a tough privacy rule known as the General Data Protection Regulation, which came into force last year in the European Union.
The UK Information Commissioner's Office said that weak security allowed user traffic to be diverted from the British Airways website to a fraudulent page starting in June 2018. The regulator said the company will have a chance to contest the proposed fine. Attackers were able to harvest customer details including log ins, payment cards, and travel booking details, according to the regulator. The airline disclosed the incident in September 2018.
The £183.4 million ($230 million) fine is roughly 1.5% of British Airways' annual revenue. The carrier, which is owned by IAG (ICAGY), said it would fight the penalty.
"We are surprised and disappointed in this initial finding," British Airways CEO Alex Cruz said in a statement.
"British Airways responded quickly to a criminal act to steal customers' data. We have found no evidence of fraud [or] fraudulent activity on accounts linked to the theft," he added.
GDPR forces companies to make sure the way they collect, process and store data is safe. Any organization that holds or uses data on people inside the European Union is subject to the rules, regardless of where it is based. Companies that breach the law can be fined up to 4% of their annual revenue.
"People's personal data is just that — personal. When an organization fails to protect it from loss, damage or theft it is more than an inconvenience," Information Commissioner Elizabeth Denham said in a statement. "That's why the law is clear — when you are entrusted with personal data you must look after it."
Gita Shivarattan, data protection counsel at law firm Ashurst, said the proposed fine showed that "European data protection regulators are clearly ramping up fines for data breaches."
"It reflects the seriousness of the regulators where there is a significant breach of GDPR obligations," added Shivarattan.
The Information Commissioner's Office has become an increasingly prominent regulator in the digital space. It fined Facebook £500,000 ($626,000) last year over the Cambridge Analytica scandal, the maximum allowed before GDPR came into force.
  
    
    Deutsche Bank shrinks and restructures
    “THE MOST fundamental transformation of Deutsche Bank in decades.” So Christian Sewing, the chief executive, described his plan, unveiled on July 7th, to revive the chronically ailing German lender. Deutsche is pruning its investment bank hard, quitting the trading of shares altogether and paring back its bond-trading operations. Costs will be cut by €6bn ($6.7bn) a year, a quarter of the total, by 2022. Eighteen thousand jobs, or a fifth of the payroll, will go. Some equity traders have already been told to clear their desks.

Mr Sewing’s plan has taken five months to hatch (during which time Deutsche also weighed up and dismissed a merger with its neighbour, Commerzbank). It looks bold. Yet it is also a belated recognition of reality. For years after the financial crisis of a decade ago, Deutsche clung to the hope that it would again go toe-to-toe with Wall Street’s giants in all areas of investment banking, as it had before the crash. “We kept too many options open,” Mr Sewing told journalists on July 8th. It has at last abandoned the last vestiges of that ambition.
  
</documents>