<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<documents>
	
		
		On the Fourth of July, Melania Trump Dresses for Independence
		President Trump may have stymied some expectations with his we-are-all-one-nation speech after the military fashion show — sorry, display — in front of the Lincoln Memorial on the Fourth of July, but it was Melania Trump in a slouching-off-one-shoulder mid-calf Carolina Herrera dress, standing silent and smiling by his side in every picture, who really put a twist on the messaging.

		After all, if there were ever a moment to go all-out in some form of patriotic dress, to use clothing to make a point, it was this one: a moment conceived by the president and promoted by the White House as a celebration/demonstration of American military might and historical triumphalism; a moment titled Salute to America; a purely symbolic moment designed to create images to go around the world. Mr. Trump himself dressed the part, in his white shirt, navy suit and bright red tie, a little flag pin on his lapel, as color coordinated with Old Glory as it was possible to be amid the tanks.

		Yet there was the first lady, in white with … rainbow stripes on her skirt. And fuchsia heels. Rainbow stripes?
		Sign up for the Open Thread Newsletter
		A look from across the New York Times at the forces that shape the dress codes we share, with Vanessa Friedman as your personal shopper.

		SIGN UP
		Was she using the Fourth of July to celebrate Pride? It was hard not to wonder. Certainly, some observers did.
		And though there was a fair amount of chatter online about the issue of wearing a white dress on what was a rainy day (it turned a little uncomfortably see-through), ultimately that happenstance was less provocative than the idea that the first lady might again be using her image as a way to speak her mind.

		Because Mrs. Trump does not work with designers to create her public-facing looks but rather buys them (a rarity these days among public figures, and a good thing), they rarely know when she is going to wear one of their products, or why — or so Wes Gordon, the creative director of Herrera, told me after Mrs. Trump had worn a dress from the brand during her recent trip to Japan. As a result, the labels themselves can’t shed much light on whether there is ever a more nuanced rationale behind Mrs. Trump’s choices than simply love of a pretty summer frock. (The Herrera dress in question this time was from the resort 2019 collection, and was on sale for $1,884 on FarFetch.com.)

		But you would have had to live under a rock for the past month not to have been met, pretty much everywhere you turned, with rainbow-stripe paraphernalia created in support of Pride Month and the L.G.B.T.Q. community. Even the president’s campaign shop has been selling rainbow-stripe T-shirts. The symbolism could not have escaped the first lady’s office, or her stylist, Hervé Pierre.
		Editors’ Picks

		The Sports Bra Seen Round the World Has New Meaning 20 Years Later
		Nor could the fact that, despite the merchandise, the president has worked to bar transgender people from serving in the military, and has been appointing to the federal bench judges who do not support trans rights.

		And Mrs. Trump does have a history with a similar dress being interpreted in a similar way: In 2017, at the White House congressional picnic — which happened to take place on the same weekend at New York’s Gay Pride parade — she wore rainbow-grid Mary Katrantzou, prompting the Hollywood Reporter to ask, “Could the FLOTUS be using her wardrobe to silently protest against her husband’s anti-gay agenda?”
		She also knows her symbolism: when she and her husband visited France for Bastille Day in 2017 — the visit that reportedly first gave the president the idea for his military extravaganza — she wore a white dress embroidered with red tulips and blue cornflowers, the latter being the French flower of remembrance, to watch the official parade.

		In any case, she was clearly aware of the watching eyes this time around, as, in what has become an increasingly rare gesture, she wore a dress from an American brand — as she did last Fourth of July when she appeared in blue gingham Ralph Lauren, and sort-of did in 2017, when she wore navy Esteban Cortázar, a Colombian-born, Miami-raised designer — as opposed to her usual European favorites, Dior and Dolce  Gabbana.

		Unlike those prior Fourth of Julys, however, when she was dressed largely in various permutations of red, white and blue, the reference this past Thursday seemed to be to another flag altogether.
		
	
	
		
			Fendi, the Legacy of Empire — and Lagerfeld
ROME — There has been some debate over how Karl Lagerfeld, former creative director of Chanel and Fendi, the man who essentially defined the role of the modern creative director until his death in February at age — well, no one is entirely sure; general guess is 85 — would have felt about the extravagant memorial held two weeks ago in Paris. He famously, after all, never wanted a grand public funeral. He hated looking back.

How would he have felt about the Fendi couture show held Thursday night at the Temple of Venus and Rome high atop the Palatine Hill in the Italian capital, the uplit arches of the Colosseum serving as backdrop, the moon lighting the paths — a show meant to be not a retrospective but rather a homage to the values he gave the brand (lightness, a sense of identity and history, a willingness to subvert all the bourgeois rules of fur) and a bridge to the future? That was a little easier to imagine.

He would have loved it.
He loved the idea, anyway, according to Serge Brunschwig, Fendi’s chief executive, when Mr. Brunschwig first proposed it a while ago. Fendi has made something of a fetish of its Roman roots, and has been embedding itself in the city for awhile now: It restored and now makes its headquarters in the Palazzo della Civiltà Italiana, a travertine architectural monument with six floors of grand arches on every side, initially commissioned by Benito Mussolini to represent his new Roman empire. It gave $2.6 million to restore the Trevi Fountain — and then, in 2016, held a fashion show over its waters. And now it has committed €2.5 million to restore the Temple of Venus and Rome, the largest temple of ancient Rome, designed by Emperor Hadrian and consecrated in A.D. 121. This show served to both celebrate and publicize the relationship. As well as to suggest — implicitly, of course — Fendi as the emperor of Italian fashion.
“Karl used to say ‘Fendi is my Roman side,’” Silvia Venturini Fendi said backstage before the show. “It is impossible to do a show in such a place without paying homage to the setting and the city.” There had been some debate over when, exactly, it should take place, but after Mr. Lagerfeld’s death, Ms. Fendi said, “we decided we had to do it, and dedicate this show to him. It was a way of showing we are a good, tight team and have learned so much from him.”

So they did it.
They did it in 54 looks, one for each year Mr. Lagerfeld worked at the company. They did it in extraordinary intarsia sables and minks inspired by patterns on the temple floors and ceilings, shaved and printed and marbleized and then cut into mosaics and pieced together in elaborate geometric patterns on tulle. They did it in organza and mousseline ball gowns printed to resemble the same inlaid stone effect and constructed to float around the body like parachutes before they touch the earth. In louche 1970s flares and matching jackets and big Betty Boop bikini briefs with 1950s bra tops under sweeping leather coats intricately cut to look like tiles. In delicate bias dresses embroidered with raffia sheaves of wheat and waving wildflowers inspired by a book on the Viennese Secession movement that Mr. Lagerfeld gave Ms. Fendi the last time they met, and by period figures like Hoffmann, Wagner and Klimt. And in narrow day dresses like columns made from wool sliced into different geometries and set on tulle, the better to cool the body.
		
	
	
		
			Gucci Goes for Gold (and Diamonds, Too)
The Italian fashion house shows its first high jewelry collection during the couture in Paris.

PARIS — Gucci’s much-touted inclusivity is not limited to community: It extends to products, too. There is little, it seems, that the brand and its creative director, Alessandro Michele, do not see as potential parts of their magic magpie mash-up vision, from sneakers to china and, as of this past week, haute jewelry, that top-end intersection of rare gems and elevated workmanship.

They can go low, they can go high, they can go everywhere.

The brand has already moved into the neighborhood. During the couture, the twice yearly gathering of the wealthy to view the finest and most expensive clothing creative minds can make, Gucci opened a boutique on the Place Vendôme, the 17th-century square in central Paris known as the center of the high jewelry universe.And it presented a collection called Hortus Deliciarum, or Garden of Delights, more than 200 pieces designed by Mr. Michele, in the same flamboyant and somewhat gender-fluid style that has become his runway trademark. Most of the necklaces and bracelets are statement size — no fragile chains or ethereal compositions for Mr. Michele — and use the lion, tiger and snake motifs rampant in the house’s costume and fine jewelry collections.
But it is the rings that dominate: Chunky hunks of yellow, white or rose gold, some twisted into snake shapes with glittering gem eyes, others forming rather expensive finger splints and a few with relatively simple settings for enormous stones (there is one almost 35-carat pink tourmaline that can’t be much smaller than a quarter).

Why would Gucci even want a relationship with high jewelry? The Kering-owned fashion house has a sales goal of 10 billion euros or $11.3 billion, for this year and recorded sales of €2.3 billion in the first quarter, up 20 percent year-on-year. And it repeatedly has credited much of its growth to millennials attracted by Mr. Michele’s exuberant fashion and — in particular — his accessories.
The pieces in the collection are billed as ranging from €50,000 to €800,000 (the high jewelry category usually starts at about €100,000). So experience-loving, material goods-shunning millennials don’t immediately come to mind as eager buyers of Mr. Michele’s version of what their grandmothers called cocktail rings. (Though the tiaras, — which Gucci labels hair accessories — might appeal for New Year’s parties.)

But as Bain  Co.’s worldwide luxury study in late 2018 pointed out, millennials and the Generation Z that followed (so everyone born between about 1980 and 2012) accounted for 47 percent of the luxury consumers in 2018 and for 33 percent of luxury purchases, including virtually all of the market’s growth.
Jewelry was one of the two top luxury growth categories — the other was shoes — with sales rising 7 percent last year in both markets.

Gucci has been edging toward high jewelry for some time. In late 2017 it presented what it called a “medium-high” version of its midrange fine jewelry collection, saying that a move upward was probable in its next offering. At the time, Maurizio Pisanu, then the house’s director of jewelry merchandising, said: “The new generation is going to want a more modern jeweler.”Other brands, however, beg to differ, and have offered arguments for their own continuing relevance in the past week.

Van Cleef  Arpels, for example, was inspired by “Romeo and Juliet” — “It’s been a beautiful story for a few centuries now,” said Nicolas Bos, the company’s chief executive — and the ballet retelling being created by Benjamin Millepied, one of the house’s longtime collaborators. Jewelry in the approximately 100-piece collection drew on Renaissance architecture, such as the diamond-set brooch that recreated Juliet’s balcony in Verona laden with ivy in emeralds, tsavorite garnets and diamonds. Yet several had a modern twist, including the Flora between-the-finger ring with an eight-carat cushion-cut sapphire and three stylized emerald-set flowers that echoed the paillette motif introduced by the house in the 1930s.
Sign up for the Open Thread Newsletter
A look from across the New York Times at the forces that shape the dress codes we share, with Vanessa Friedman as your personal shopper.

SIGN UP
Modern also was the look of The Ciels of Chaumet, an 88-piece collection evoking the shapes and colors of the sky, its elements and creatures, including highly stylized swallows that, in earrings of tsavorite garnets, yellow and green sapphires and diamonds, had a sharp two-dimensional look from the house’s traditional fil couteau, or knife-edge setting.
		
	
	
		
		How Celine Dion became the queen of couture week
The Canadian songstress has rocked a number of dramatic looks since the start of fashion's most rarefied event, turning heads and attracting photographers as she made Paris her personal catwalk.
Dion made her first appearance of the week in a Chanel unitard, complete with a chain logo belt, casting herself as a modern-day Catwoman while nailing the athleisure trend. A feathered, millennial pink Attico bustier, asymmetric jeans by Ksenia Schnaider and a furry Fendi bag followed. Then there was an Off-White graffiti-print bodysuit and blazer ensemble (no pants) originally modeled by Gigi Hadid. And this was all before Dion even began attending the shows.
At Miu Miu's presentation, the star chose a hot pink strapless ruched number with a big black bow by the brand that was a bold, swoon-worthy showpiece. At Schiaparelli, she wore a custom halter-necked dress by the maison's new creative director, Daniel Roseberry, along with a headpiece by milliner Stephen Jones.At Iris van Herpen, she was a walking optical illusion in a 3D printed gown from the designer's 2019 couture collection, and for Alexandre Vauthier, she wore an ivory off-the-shoulder minidress with oversized balloon sleeves of his design, epitomizing sartorial grandeur.Oh, and did we mention the '80s-inspired Ronald van der Kemp dress -- complete with yellow tutu skirt and tuxedo jacket top -- she wore to stroll the alleys of the French capital?
This level of glamor is nothing new for Dion, who has been at it for the last few seasons. In 2016, appearing at Paris Couture Week for the first time in 11 years, Dion stepped out wearing a trendy oversized Vetements Titanic hoodie that had the fashion crowd swooning, and made her into an unexpected style icon in the circuit. Ever since then, the 51-year-old has donned some jaw-dropping looks, from $26,000 head-to-toe Balmain ensemble to a striking Roberto Cavalli floral pantsuit.She's also revealed an enthusiastic love for fashion that's won the industry over. Sitting front row at the Giambattista Valli show in 2016, she whooped her way through as if it were a football game.
In July 2017, she modeled the latest couture off the Paris runways in a video for Vogue, dancing, singing and just being unabashedly cool, quirky and carefree. Last January, she wept watching the Valentino haute couture show.
No one quite saw Dion's style transformation coming: the singer has always been more revered for her ballads than her wardrobe. But the admiration for her transformation runs deep.
This is due in part to the fact that Dion's reinvention -- which she's achieved with the help of former "image architect" Law Roach and current stylists Pepe Muñoz and Sydney Lopez -- came after the loss of her husband, Rene Angélil, and brother Daniel, who died of cancer within two days of each other in 2016. In light of those circumstances, her fashion rebirth takes on more mature, personal tones.
Watching her Paris adventures, one has to wonder whether Dion has always been a fashion icon in the making. Whatever the case, we're certainly glad she's taken her place in the spotlight.
		
	
	
		
		Fendi stages couture fashion show amid ruins of ancient Rome
The Italian brand sent 54 new couture looks down the runway at the ancient Temple of Venus and Roma -- one for each year the late designer worked at the fashion house.
Luxury label Fendi paid tribute to its former creative director Karl Lagerfeld on Thursday evening with a spectacular fashion show set amid the crumbling ruins of ancient Rome.
The show also marked the beginning of an ambitious project to restore the ancient structure, built by Emperor Hadrian almost 2,000 years ago. Fendi's parent company LVMH has pledged 2.5 million euros ($2.8 million).
The brand's current creative director Silvia Venturini Fendi, the granddaughter of founders Adele and Edoardo Fendi, stepped out to an applause at the end of the show. Her Fall/Winter 2019-2020 collection, officially titled "The Dawn of Romanity," was the first in the fashion house's post-Lagerfeld era.
Venturini Fendi was a close friend and collaborator of Lagerfeld's throughout his tenure. She joined the family business in 1994 and has spent most of her time working as the brand's creative director of accessories and menswear. She's credited for the iconic design of Fendi's "Baguette" bag.
Anna Wintour, Susan Sarandon, Winnie Harlow and Catherine Zeta-Jones were among approximately 600 people in attendance. Guests were treated to a live performance by Italian composer Caterina Barbieri, as well as an open-air private dinner at the historic site. Rome's famous Coliseum, just short distance away, served as a stunning backdrop for many of the evening's photos.
Fendi's CEO Serge Brunschwig took to the stage to honor Lagerfeld, who joined Fendi in 1965, saying he had spoken to the legendary designer before his death about hosting a show at the temple.
According to Brunschwig, the evening event was also intended to celebrate "the relationship between Fendi and Rome," the city in which the luxury retailer launched in 1925. Fendi previously funded the restoration of Rome's historic Trevi Fountain, where it held a spectacular 90th-anniversary show in 2016.
Lagerfeld, who died in February at the age of 85, was one of the most influential and outspoken figures in contemporary fashion. Last month, Fendi joined Chanel -- where the designer also served as creative director -- to stage a star-studded memorial. Their "Karl For Ever" tribute saw more than 1,000 guests celebrating Lagerfeld's work and life at the Grand Palais in Paris.
		
	
	
		
		Brazil's fashion industry has a diversity problem
In February, the Brazilian fashion industry made global headlines. Donata Meirelles, then fashion director at Vogue Brazil, was celebrating her 50th birthday in the predominantly black city of Salvador, Bahia. During the celebration, journalist Fabio Bernardo snapped a photo of Meirelles, who is white, sitting in a traditional throne-like chair flanked by two baianas (Afro-Brazilian women wearing white lace gowns and headpieces), which he then shared on Instagram.
To many who saw the post (which has since been deleted), the scene evoked colonial Brazil, when white elites ruled over black slaves.
"What happened there is what happens in this country built on racism, bodies, sweat, blood and black tears," Afro-Brazilian actress and activist Tais Araujo, Vogue Brazil's November 2018 cover star, posted to her Instagram account in the days following the event. "This suffering is so naturalized that it is difficult for people who do not identify with the girls standing by the chair to feel what the black population feels. Everything becomes natural."
While the party was not an official Vogue event, the backlash was enough to warrant Meirelles' resignation from the title just a few days after the event, and a public apology from the magazine, who wrote on Instagram that they hoped the discussions sparked by the incident had "served as a learning opportunity." (Both Meirelles and Vogue Brazil declined to be interviewed for this story.)
According to a Brazilian Institute of Geography and Statistics study released in 2016, 54% of Brazilians identify as black or multiracial. And yet black people have been all but erased from the mainstream fashion industry -- in front of the camera, on the catwalk and behind the scenes.
Historically, model diversity at São Paulo Fashion Week has been so low that in 2009, following intense pressure from anti-racism activists and state prosecutors, the organizing body mandated that 10% of models in each show must be black.
At last edition of São Paulo Fashion Week (SPFW), which took place in April month, black models were still in the minority, and for the last three seasons, only one black designer -- Luiz Claudio of Apartamento 03 -- has participated. (SPFW CEO Paulo Borges told CNN that organizers are aware of the disparity and are discussing ways to bring in new players.)
		
	
	
		
		Mini bags can be cute, but also faintly ridiculous. Like my colleague Chloe Hall so astutely wondered about Kendall Jenner's micro-mini bag: What can you actually fit in that thing?

I'd never been tempted to try the trend until recently when my beloved Tory Burch Lee Radziwill bag was shrunken down to a petite size. You see, I have a weakness for retro-inspired shapes that I don't feel wrong calling a pocketbook (and think Lee is the ultimate style icon).

Additionally, I like my crossbody bags to have a top handle since it gives me options for how to carry (over the shoulder; cross body; in the crook of my arm). And while I have plenty of "work" bags, I'm usually at more of a loss on the weekends when the amount of stuff I need to tote around goes way down.
Confirmed: You can fit an XL cell phone.

For my non-office bags, I don't need much: Space for my phone (a Google Pixel XL—nearly identical to a large iPhone), lip balm, and my wallet and/or a pared-back handful of credit cards. Check, check, check. Everything fits (I skip the wallet if I want to close the bag; it works/doesn't spill everything/looks chic open too) and isn't so tiny that it's comical.
The removable crossbody strap makes it dual-purpose.

I'm very into the idea of two-for-one styling and bags can be strong contenders in this category. I've been carrying the petite Lee on the regular to run errands, go to Pilates, or grab lunch, but I also plan on removing the long strap and using the bag for formal events.
The removable crossbody strap makes it dual-purpose.

I'm very into the idea of two-for-one styling and bags can be strong contenders in this category. I've been carrying the petite Lee on the regular to run errands, go to Pilates, or grab lunch, but I also plan on removing the long strap and using the bag for formal events.
It lets me pretend I'm Lisa Rinna.

Rinna is one of the Housewives whose style I'm most drawn to. It's different than mine, but has a streamlined quality and consistency I really appreciate. As such, I loved when she debuted her mini Hermès Kelly this season (and had a moment explaining to the ladies how she isn't really one to splash out on handbags, but thought she ought to treat herself).

Regardless, I love how the Lee has the same vibe as a Kelly, but isn't trying to pretend it is a Kelly—the distinction is supremely important in my mind. It's classy, it's timeless, it's understated, and it gets the job done. What more do you need from a bag?
		
	
	
		
		I Want to Dress Like a Cool Dad This Summer
I would be lying if I said I haven’t clowned my dad for making a few fashion faux pas in his heyday (you have too, don’t lie). I mean, calf-length cargo shorts? Oversized baseball jerseys and those BBQ sandals? He had it coming. But little did I know my father’s practical approach to fashion would later spawn a fashion movement rooted in comfortability and an aesthetic streetwear culture would dub “dadcore.”

Dadcore fashion basically consists of you wearing clothing that focuses more on function and comfort than actual style. Today, you can’t walk into a store or scroll through Instagram without seeing something that reminds you of your old man. Sharp tailored suits and cardigans are no longer the DILF style staples, now it’s all about orthopedic-esque chunky sneakers, baseball caps and bucket hats, and cargo shorts and vests. Fashion has a serious case of daddy issues.
I never thought about tucking a t-shirt into a pair of khaki pleated pants or wearing a comfy pair of basketball shorts outdoors, but here we are and I have Justin Bieber to blame. He’s no father (yet?) but JB has this “dadcore” trend down pat. See, last year, JB was seen frolicking around the world with his then-fiancé (and now wife) Hailey Baldwin, crying, laughing, and singing on the street in lewks that ranged from Golf Dad to Athletic Dad to Cool Dad.

White t-shirt with basketball shorts and an iced coffee? Athletic Dad JB.
JB’s style was easygoing, carefree, and above all, comfortable as hell. Now with summer in full effect, “dadcore” seems like a promising summer style to throw into my rotation of puff-sleeve sundresses, linen two-piece sets, and body-skimming skirts. Do I want to feel restricted in bike shorts or free like a bird in baggy basketball shorts? Do I want to lug around a large tote bag or go full-on organized parent on a school trip with a fanny pack or crossbody purse? These pragmatic, not-so-fashionable "dad" pieces are insanely low-effort closet staples that are perfect to have on the days the NYC summer temperature reaches high into the '90s and can be easily dressed up with the right finishing touches.

Read on for all the pieces you need to invest in to successfully pull of dadcore this summer.

Nothing screams Old Man Steez like a good ol' pair of khakis. Skinny jeans have been quickly phased out and stiff high-waisted khaki pants with a relaxed fit—like the Dickies your old man wore literally everywhere—have returned to the spotlight. The trick to styling khaki pants is playing with proportions: add a cropped top into the mix for subtle sex appeal or drive the "dad" look home by tucking a white-shirt into the khakis and cuffing the hem.
		
	
	
		
		Louis Vuitton and Artist Alex Israel Debut a Limited-Edition Scarf Collection
Put away the neutrals, everyone, because summer's here, and that means it's time to break out the bold and bright colors. And Louis Vuitton's latest vibrant offering is just what you need to shield yourself from the heat in style.

The luxury fashion house debuted a collab with multimedia artist and designer Alex Israel that features an eight-piece collection of stunning textiles. The exclusive collection, which includes various scarves, shawls, blankets, and even a sexy bandeau, are all imbued with Israel's signature pop aesthetic, so expect bold colors like purple, pink, and yellow all mixed together. The capsule collection also spotlights some of Israel's most well-known designs, such as his cotton candy-colored Sky Backdrop (which was once featured in the MoMA) and his puffy Wave painting.

Supermodel Karlie Kloss was chosen as the face for this limited-edition collection:
This eight-piece collection isn't the fashion house's first time partnering with Israel; earlier this year, Louis Vuitton recruited Israel to design the packaging artwork for its perfume line Les Colognes Perfumes and also tapped him for a California-inspired take on its iconic Capucines bag. You can find the collab at the pop-up store within the Louis Vuitton X exhibition in Los Angeles and is available in select locations.
		
	
	
		
		Are You Ready for the Designer Flip Flop Trend?
If you were worried about the return of the '90s strappy sandal, you might want to avert your eyes because lip flops are officially back. But the modern iteration of the controversial footwear is a lot fancier than we remember. These aren’t the high school Havaianas ELLE.com first reported on after Copenhagen Fashion Week in 2018. No, high fashion brands are raising the stakes...and their price tags.

The thonged sandals popping up on our feed today are elevated with a minimalist touch. Gianvito Rossi's leather flats perfectly capture the beach-to-office vibe we’re chasing this summer. Sure, they cost about $600, but these could easily be worn with slouchy slacks and make you feel like an Olsen twin. Similarly chic, Reformation's recently launched sandal collection features a stiletto heel that makes a case for flip flops at a wedding. Yes, you read that right. Flip flops at a wedding are totally ok.
High heeled flip flops are here with some celebrity representation, too: Kim Kardashian West recently championed the trend, wearing a pair with Christian Dior's newspaper print (once worn by Carrie Bradshaw). If the mule flat was our go-to shoe in 2018, the fancy flip flop is our new favorite. Prep that space between your big toe and second toe, immediately.
		
	
</documents>